<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-07-24">
    <title>YH4F: Coding is over!</title>
    <body>
      <p>The second edition of Youth Hacking 4 Freedom, the hacking 
competition for young Europeans, has just ended. For the last six 
months, the participants have worked on developing their own personal 
Free Software projects.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>YH4F: Coding is over!</h1>

<p>The second edition of Youth Hacking 4 Freedom, the hacking 
competition for young Europeans, has just ended. For the last six 
months, the participants have worked on developing their own personal 
Free Software projects.</p>

<figure>
     <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/3f/12/898d5df0d133996094da93e2472e.jpg" alt="Image with a laptop with some code in the screen"/>
       </figure>

<p>Nearly 70 young people from across Europe signed up for the new 
edition of <a href="/activities/yh4f/index.html">Youth Hacking 4 Freedom</a>, a competition for European 
teenagers to develop their coding skills and win great cash prizes. 
</p>

<p>This second edition, <a href="/news/2023/news-20230220-01.html">which started last January</a>, 
was accompanied by a new activity: a monthly meeting where participants 
had the opportunity to discuss their technical problems and learn some 
tips from different Free Software experts. These meetings have also 
been a way to keep in touch, and a way to support each other, promoting 
one of the principles of Free Software, the creation of community. 
These open and voluntary meetings allowed those attending to talk and 
connect with each other in smaller groups.</p>

<blockquote> <italic>"The monthly meetings provide an opportunity to talk and 
connect with other participants and have helped form friendships 
throughout the contest. It has been great to see how well these
meetings have been received by the participants. And it is a most rewarding experience to be able to help young people 
from all over Europe to find other Free Software enthusiasts!"</italic>, <em> says Bonnie Mehring, YH4F project 
manager.</em>
</blockquote>


<p>After six hard working months of coding, it is now the turn of <a href="/activities/yh4f/jury.html">the YH4F jury </a> to evaluate the 
participants’ submitted projects. The jury is composed of Free Software 
professionals with different backgrounds and technological skills, who 
will review the projects within the next weeks taking into 
consideration different criteria such as the originality of the idea, 
the creativity of the project, and the quality of the code.</p> 

<p>In the first round of voting the jury will decide which of the 
submitted projects could be considered for one of the cash prizes. 
Then, the authors of those projects will be invited to an online 
interview to present them and answer the jury’s questions. Afterwards 
the jury will decide on the prizes.</p>

<h3>Brussels is awaiting!</h3> 
<p>The winners will be announced based 
on the judges' scores, and prizes will be awarded at the YH4F Awards 
ceremony in Brussels in mid-October, to which all winners will be 
invited for an all-expenses-paid weekend.</p> 

<p>Six winners will receive cash prizes ranging from €4,096 to €1,024 
each, at a ceremony featuring top Free Software speakers.</p>

<p><strong>Keep up to date on our next news to learn about this year's amazing projects and the winners!</strong></p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/3f/12/898d5df0d133996094da93e2472e.jpg" alt="Image with a laptop with some code in the screen"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230724-01.html</link>
    <tags>
	 <tag key="front-page"/>
	 <tag key="yh4f">Youth Hacking 4 Freedom</tag>
	 <tag key="education">Education</tag>
	 </tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1053"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
