<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-02-20">
    <title>Let's code!</title>
    <body>
      <p>Youth Hacking 4 Freedom, FSFE's coding competition for young 
Europeans, has just started. The kick-off event took place on the 26th 
of January with an online meeting for the participants of this year's 
competition. There they got the most important information about the 
contest while starting to get to know each other.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>Let's code!</h1>

<p>Youth Hacking 4 Freedom, FSFE's coding competition for young 
Europeans, has just started. The kick-off event took place on the 26th 
of January with an online meeting for the participants of this year's 
competition. There they got the most important information about the 
contest while starting to get to know each other.</p>


<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/1d/78/0fe59f43fcf66ce5a1631508883f.jpg" alt="The coding period of this new edition has started"/>
</figure>

<p>Almost 70 young people from all over Europe have signed up for the 
new edition of Youth Hacking 4 Freedom. During the contest they not 
only have the chance to work on their own Free Software projects, but 
also to win great cash prizes.</p>

<p>The kick-off meeting for this project took place on 26th January 
with an online event where participants had the chance to get their 
questions answered about the coding requirements and the coding period, 
which will end on 30th June. It was a fun event which gave everybody 
the chance to get to know each other a bit better and to meet other 
participants from all across Europe. However, the FSFE team was also 
excited to learn about the participants and to find out what they are 
looking forward to in the upcoming months.</p>

<p>One of this edition's participants, 1337misom<a id="ref-1" href="#fn-1" role="doc-noteref"/>, explains his motivation:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><em>“I have never really released any of my projects because 
they mainly solved problems for myself and weren't optimized for ease 
of use etc. So this will be my first shot at actually creating a 
program that lasts for more than a few weeks".</em></p> 
</blockquote> 

<p>The opportunity to work on a project they are really interested in, as well 
as gaining experience and having fun, is the main reason given by the 
participants. Jannes<a id="ref-1" href="#fn-1" role="doc-noteref"/>,
who has already taken part in the first edition of the contest last year,
said that he joined "to have fun, meet exciting people with even more exciting
ideas and develop a (hopefully) useful program in a limited time".</p>

<p>Over the coming months, participants will have the opportunity to 
discuss their projects once a month in an online meeting as well as 
through the dedicated Youth Hacking 4 Freedom Matrix room, where FSFE's 
team is also available to answer questions. These channels allow 
teenagers to share their ideas and questions, receive feedback from 
their peers, and see what other participants are working on.</p>

<figure>
  <peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/wWUP7M5fJg2FcvG2Fv12sN"/>
  <figcaption>
    Watch the video of the two day trip to Brussels where last year's winners 
    met, explored the city, and received their awards. For subtitles, 
    watch it in our <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/wWUP7M5fJg2FcvG2Fv12sN">Peertube 
    instance</a>
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The road to the awards ceremony in Brussels has already begun, and 
although most of the participants are not yet thinking about this 
event, they are excited about the opportunity to present a good and 
practical project and to have their code judged by a panel of experts. 
And although winning is not their main motivation, of course, “nobody 
is bitter for a sweet". <strong>Good luck!</strong>
</p>

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2> <!-- This headline is hidden, but please keep it anyway -->
<ol>
  <li id="fn-1">
    We are using the names that the participants are using in the internal contest Matrix chat.
  </li>
</ol>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/1d/78/0fe59f43fcf66ce5a1631508883f.jpg" alt="The coding period of this new edition has started"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230220-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
   <tag key="yh4f">Youth Hacking 4 Freedom</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/998"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
