<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-03-23">
    <title>EU: Proposed liability rules will harm Free Software</title>
    <body>
      <p>
The EU is currently debating the introduction of liability rules for 
software, including Free Software. The relevant proposals are the AI 
Act, Product Liability Directive (PLD), and Cyber Resilience Act 
(CRA). The way they are, all proposals will harm the Free Software 
ecosystem and thus the society and the economy.
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>EU: Proposed liability rules will harm Free Software </h1>

<p>
The EU is currently debating the introduction of liability rules for 
software, including Free Software. The relevant proposals are the AI 
Act, Product Liability Directive (PLD), and Cyber Resilience Act 
(CRA). The way they are, all proposals will harm the Free Software 
ecosystem and thus the society and the economy.
</p>


<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/d1b7eb0ca6ec38c89967dab6d3dd920b.png" alt="While we welcome the discussion on more cyber security we doubt that the introduction of liability alone will lead to more cyber security"/>
</figure>
<p>
The main debate happens around the Cyber Resilience Act. We will 
therefore discuss the risks and solutions using this Act as an example. 
</p>

<p>
While we welcome the discussion on more cyber security we doubt that the 
introduction of liability alone will lead to more cyber security. 
Especially in Free Software, far-reaching security measures are already 
in place.  Those measures differ from those of proprietary software.
</p>

<p>
The proposal to exclude Free Software “outside the course of a 
commercial activity” would fail to address a large part of software that 
will not be covered  but is deployed. At the same time smaller and 
non-profit projects would be harmed as they would have to bear major 
costs. 
</p>

<p>
We, therefore, propose a solution that will lead to more security while 
safeguarding the Free Software ecosystem:
</p>
<ol>
<li>Liability should be shifted to those deploying Free Software instead of those developing Free Software and</li>
<li>
Those who significantly financially benefit from this deployment should 
make sure the software becomes CE-compliant
</li>
</ol> 
<p>
Free Software with its four freedoms to use, study, share, and improve 
the code makes it easy for anyone to develop and improve the code while 
making it available to everyone. In cases of security incidents, 
developers - who might only get micro or small payments, are non-profit, 
or even do not earn a single Euro for their work - might be 
liable. To make them liable could lead to large burdens that 
projects could not handle alone. Free Software is everywhere nowadays, 
and those deploying Free Software, especially Free Software from small projects, must take on more 
responsibility, if only out of their own interest. 
</p>

<p>
Putting the burden of liability on these small or non-profit 
entities would harm the Free Software ecosystem and thus society and 
business equally, because due to the lack of funding and resources to go 
through these procedures, some of these projects might have to stop 
completely, but also it won't necessarily lead to more security. 
Moreover, many small Free Software projects already have well-working security assessments in 
place. Introducing new workflows or even consulting third parties 
would have financial consequences that would be almost impossible to 
bear. Ways to address the funding problem could be a dedicated fund to 
support these projects, or the introduction of a scoring system that 
shows how much a company invests in the security of the Free Software 
projects it uses. However, neither of these proposals can be implemented 
quickly, so the problem will persist. Therefore, transferring liability 
to those who deploy the software and try to profit significantly from it seems 
to be a better solution.
</p>

<p>
To address this, the current wording needs to be improved. The concept 
of “commercial activity” should be replaced with an approach that 
focuses on deployment rather than on development. And the responsibility to 
fulfill these requirements should be on the entity that benefits in the 
market. Likewise, exemptions for non-profit entities and micro 
enterprises should be introduced. In other words, liability should be 
moved towards those deploying these solutions that are substantial 
profit-oriented companies.
</p>

<p>
This will ensure that all Free Software solutions that are used on a 
significant level are assessed under the liability rules in the CRA, PLD, 
and AI Act, but the financial burden will be shifted to those who 
try to make a profit from these solutions. So they will be 
the ones having to make sure that someone runs through the procedures needed for 
their software to get the CE label. Deployers could collaborate and 
ensure that they fund projects they use or could run through the 
procedures themselves.  They ought to make sure that modifications are fed back 
into the projects.
</p>

<p>We presented this position also in a public hearing in the European Parliament.</p>

<figure>
  <peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/7X2vSXubdrbTPFTqjmT5Nm"/>
</figure>

<p>
It is a complex debate with far-reaching implications and changing 
positions every day. We will continue to work on this issue in the 
upcoming month. If you are interested in getting involved or joining our 
activities, please contact us via email.
</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/d1b7eb0ca6ec38c89967dab6d3dd920b.png" alt="While we welcome the discussion on more cyber security we doubt that the introduction of liability alone will lead to more cyber security"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230323-01.html</link>
    <tags>
 <tag key="front-page"/>
 <tag key="european-parliament">European Parliament</tag>
 <tag key="policy">European Public Policy</tag>
 <tag key="AI">AI</tag>
  <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1005"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
