<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-06-06">
    <title>Germany: dPhoenix on the road to failure?</title>
    <body>
      <p>
A Free Software office and collaboration suite for the public sector is 
one of the projects with which the German government aims to fulfil the 
goals of the coalition agreement. But a closer look at the project 
raises questions: Where is the source code? Who is responsible? What 
happens to the public money involved? We asked the relevant ministry.
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>
<h1>Germany: dPhoenix on the road to failure?</h1>

<p>
A Free Software office and collaboration suite for the public sector is 
one of the projects with which the German government aims to fulfil the 
goals of the coalition agreement. But a closer look at the project 
raises questions: Where is the source code? Who is responsible? What 
happens to the public money involved? We asked the relevant ministry.
</p>

<p>
Back in 2020, the north German IT service provider Dataport started the 
first pilots of its dPhoenixSuite as an alternative to Microsoft’s 
proprietary office and collaboration suite. The dPhoenixSuite integrates 
Free Software components such as Nextcloud, Matrix, Jitsi, Collabora, 
and UCS. The suite is already being offered on a small scale as a cloud 
service to German adminstrations, taking a stand where the German IT 
Planning Council is calling for a sovereign working environment for 
administrations, with Free Software solutions as a priority. But 
Dataport seems to fall short of this expectation.
</p>

<p>
The current issue 07/23 of Linux Magazin comes with a <a href="https://www.linux-magazin.de/ausgaben/2023/07/dataport-phoenix/">detailed 
and critical analysis</a> by Markus Feilner, which covers both the 
history and the problems of Dataport’s “Projekt Phoenix” and its 
relation to the “Sovereign Workplace” (“Souveräner Arbeitsplatz”), a 
long promised reference implementation under the responsibility of the 
German Federal Ministry of the Interior and Community (BMI), coordinated 
by the recently founded Centre for Digital Sovereignty of Public 
Administration (ZenDiS). Some of the major problems Feilner reveals are 
the missing dPhoenixSuite source code, a lack of understanding of Free 
Software and of collaboration within the Free Software community, a 
tendency to open-wash by claiming to be “based on open source”, unclear 
responsibilities, and an opaque relationship to the BMI’s “Sovereign 
Workplace” project.
</p>
<p>
We have been promoting the concept of <a href="https://publiccode.eu">“Public Money? Public Code!”</a> since 
2017, and we welcome and encourage every step towards Free Software in 
public administrations. However, the recent news developments around 
Dataport and the Sovereign Workplace are reason to be wary, especially 
of any attempts to open-wash.
</p>
<p>
Therefore, we have today sent a list of questions to the BMI, expecting 
that the answers will make the situation around the dPhoenixSuite and 
the Sovereign Workplace transparent.
</p>

<h2>Questions for the Federal Ministry of the Interior and Community (BMI):</h2>

<ol type="A">
<li><p>Dataport advertises its dPhoenixSuite as an “open source solution”. 
So far, however, only the source code of the underlying Free Software 
(also known as Open Source) components is available under Free Software 
licences. The code of the complete, integrated suite cannot be obtained 
from Dataport upon request.</p> 
  <ol type="1"> 
    <li>When will the full source code of the Sovereign Workplace be 
    published on OpenCoDE?</li> 
    <li>Will the code be published under a Free Software license, and if 
    yes, under which one?</li>
    <li>Is the Sovereign Workplace based on the same code stack as the 
    dPhoenixSuite?</li>
    <li>What part of the Sovereign Workplace code comes from dPhoenixSuite? 
    In which parts do they differ and why?</li>
    <li>Will it be possible for everyone to compile the Sovereign Workplace 
    from the source code and run it on one’s own infrastructure as soon as 
    it is published on OpenCoDE? Will an elaborate documentation to the 
    code be available?</li>
    <li>Are there plans do further develop the Sovereign Workplace in 
    collaboration with the community of the underlying Free Software 
    projects after the code has been published?</li>
    <li>Will further development using OpenCoDE take place openly 
    according to the tried and tested principles of “coding in the open” 
    and “release early, release often”, establishing and involving a 
    community?</li>
  </ol>
</li>
<li><p>According to public news and information from Dataport, the 
dPhoenixSuite is based on the Sovereign Workplace, which is to be 
published on OpenCoDE before the end of 2023. According to the BMI, the 
Sovereign Workplace is based on dPhoenixSuite.</p>
  <ol type="1"> 
    <li>Which of the two statements is correct? How did the two 
    different statements come about?</li>
    <li>Which contracts with reference to the Sovereign Workplace exist 
    between the BMI or ZenDiS on the one hand and Dataport on the 
    other?</li>
    <li>Is the Sovereign Workplace rather a fork of dPhoenixSuite or a 
    reference implementation? Once the source code has been published 
    on OpenCoDE, will the Sovereign Workplace be further developed 
    independently of dPhoenixSuite or will it remain coupled to 
    dPhoenixSuite?</li>
    <li>Can you provide us with an organisation chart of the Sovereign 
    Workplace project with all the authorities, offices, public bodies, 
    and responsible persons involved? If this is not possible: 
    Which authorities, offices, public bodies, and responsible persons 
    are involved in the Sovereign Workplace project (in each case with 
    details of their role and responsibility within the project)?</li>
    <li>Who is responsible for the Sovereign Workplace project in the 
    BMI?</li> 
    <li>What competences does the CIO have in coordinating the project 
    and in coordinating with Dataport?</li>
    <li>Where and by whom is the cooperation between Dataport and 
    BMI/ZenDiS on the Sovereign Workplace and the Phoenix project 
    controlled and coordinated?</li>
    <li>Where and under whose leadership are the components of the 
    Sovereign Workplace that are not adopted from the Free Software 
    community (for example gluecode and integration scripts) 
    developed?</li>
    <li>How many people develop code for the Sovereign Workplace at 
    the BMI or ZenDiS? Is this code also made available to Dataport 
    for the dPhoenixSuite?</li>
    <li>Are there any requirements from BMI/ZenDiS to Dataport for 
    the development of the dPhoenixSuite? If yes: Are these 
    fulfilled?</li>
    <li>Has the BMI exerted any influence on Dataport to publish 
    the complete dPhoenixSuite as Free Software?</li>
  </ol>
</li>
<li><p>Funding</p>
  <ol type="1">
    <li>What public funding has been spent on the Sovereign Workplace 
    so far?</li>
    <li>What funding is available for the project for the current year?</li>
    <li>What annual funding is needed until 2025 to further develop the 
    Sovereign Workplace?</li>
    <li>Did Dataport receive any funding from the BMI/ZenDiS for the 
    development of dPhoenixSuite or contributions to the Sovereign 
    Workplace?</li>
  </ol>
</li>
</ol>
<p>
We expect that the BMI’s response will give the public a better 
understanding of what is going on around the Sovereign Workplace and the 
dPhoenixSuite. We will stay tuned to this issue and report back as soon 
as we receive a response.
</p>

<h2>Free Software and “Public Money? Public Code!”</h2>
<p>
Free Software gives everyone the right to use, study, share and improve 
applications for any purpose. These freedoms ensure that similar 
applications do not have to be programmed from scratch every time and, 
thanks to transparent processes, others do not have to reinvent the 
wheel. In large projects, expertise and costs can be shared and 
applications paid for by the general public are available to all. This 
promotes innovation and saves taxpayers money in the medium to long 
term. Dependencies on vendors are minimised and security issues can be 
fixed more easily. The Free Software Foundation Europe, together with 
over 200 organisations and administrations, is therefore calling for 
“Public Money? Public Code!” - If it is public money, it should be 
public code as well. More information on the initiative on the <a href="https://publiccode.eu">“Public Money? Public Code!” website</a>.
</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/6c8d43ffc1013f647affa17d8f0929d5.jpg" alt="House consisting of 0s and 1s"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230606-01.html</link>
    <tags>
	 <tag key="front-page"/>
	 <tag key="de">Germany</tag>
	 <tag key="pmpc">Public Money? Public Code!</tag>
	</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1039"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
