<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-06-29">
    <title>IEA: EU Parliament advances in strengthening the role of Free Software, yet needs more to improve</title>
    <body>
      <p>The two EP Committees for opinion, IMCO and LIBE, have today 
adopted their texts on the Interoperable Europe Act. While both 
recognise the importance of Free Software for this regulation, the 
inclusion of the Free Software community in the Board remains 
uncertain. The wording on proper monitoring and evaluation goes in the 
right direction.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>IEA: EU Parliament advances in strengthening the role of Free Software, yet needs more to improve</h1>

<p>The two EP Committees for opinion, IMCO and LIBE, have today 
adopted their texts on the Interoperable Europe Act. While both 
recognise the importance of Free Software for this regulation, the 
inclusion of the Free Software community in the Board remains 
uncertain. The wording on proper monitoring and evaluation goes in the 
right direction.</p>

<figure>
     <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/b0/1a/fd4cdcfc9469a641626b5eb71aa4.jpg" alt="European building with the European Parliament symbol"/>
       </figure>

<p>The Committee on the Internal Market and Consumer Protection (IMCO) 
and the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs (LIBE) 
have today adopted   by a large majority their opinions on the 
Interoperable Europe Act.</p>

<p>The IMCO Committee, following some of <a href="/news/2023/news-20230323-02.html">our demands</a>, has highlighted 
the need for public bodies and institutions to prioritise the use of 
Free Software in order to support the creation of reusable solutions. 
Furthermore, it has also recognised our demand for clearer objectives 
and indicators to assest its achievement. Moreover, it has included 
measures to report and monitor the number of Free Software solutions 
developed and adopted by the public sector within the scope of the 
Regulation.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, no amendments to include more stakeholders in the 
Interoperable Europe Board were adopted, apart from the proposal to 
include the European Parliament as an observer. Therefore, it is now up 
to the lead Committee on Industry, Research and Energy (ITRE) to take  
further steps forward in the direction of enriching the Board.</p>

<p>On the other hand, the LIBE Committee has briefly included the wording to 
encourage Free Software solutions when it comes to enhancing 
transparency in the processing of personal data within the scope of 
this regulation. However, this wording still needs to be improved by 
more firmly prioritising the use of Free Software for such purpose.
</p>

<blockquote>
 <em>Lina Ceballos, FSFE Project Manager states: <italic>“We welcome 
 that the European Parliament has taken notice of some of our demands, 
 especially when it comes to proper monitoring and evaluation. However, 
 there is yet the need to include more stakeholders in the governance. 
 Thus we urge decision makers to recognise the role that the Free 
 Software community could play in the Interoperable 
 Board"</italic>.</em>
</blockquote>


<p>In the coming weeks, the Committee on Industry, Research and Energy 
(ITRE) will agree on its text, which will most likely be voted in 
plenary after the summer break, and then enter into the 
inter-institutional negotiations. We call upon the decision makers to 
not only anchor the progress that IMCO and LIBE have achieved with their 
opinion but also to undertake the actions needed for a more inclusive 
governance approach by including the Free Software community as part of 
the Interoperable Europe Board. This is also true for the Council, that 
<a href="/news/2023/news-20230623-01.html">wants to exclude relevant 
stakeholders from contributing to an Interoperable Europe</a>. </p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/b0/1a/fd4cdcfc9469a641626b5eb71aa4.jpg" alt="European building with the European Parliament symbol"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230629-02.html</link>
    <tags>
	 <tag key="front-page"/>
	 <tag key="european-parliament">European Parliament</tag>
	 <tag key="policy">European Public Policy</tag>
	 <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
	 <tag key="IEA">Interoperable Europe Act</tag>
	</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1044"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
