<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-06-23">
    <title>Council to exclude relevant stakeholders from contributing to an Interoperable Europe</title>
    <body>
      <p> The current draft from the Council on the Interoperable Europe Act 
is limiting the Interoperable Europe Board, and with this excluding 
relevant stakeholders from contributing to a more interoperable and 
innovative Europe.  There is also a lack of improved wording in the 
area of monitoring and budgeting.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>Council to exclude relevant stakeholders from contributing to an Interoperable Europe</h1>

<p> The current draft from the Council on the Interoperable Europe Act 
is limiting the Interoperable Europe Board, and with this excluding 
relevant stakeholders from contributing to a more interoperable and 
innovative Europe.  There is also a lack of improved wording in the 
area of monitoring and budgeting.</p>

<figure>
     <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/67/b6/6254c3286c9ade71e1b1d6b3868c.jpg" alt="EU building with flags from the different EU countries"/>
       </figure>

<p> The Interoperable Europe Act is aiming to enhance cross-border 
digital public services across the European Union. This proposal is 
currently discussed in the European Parliament and the Council. Through 
a Freedom of Information request, the FSFE caused access to the <a href="https://data.consilium.europa.eu/doc/document/ST-8907-2023-INIT/en/pdf">latest 
compromise text (.pdf) </a> of the Council. </p>

<p>From this draft, it gets clear that the Council is seeking to limit 
the overall participation in the Interoperable Europe Board by 
hindering the possibility to include experts and other stakeholders 
with observer status in such board.  This not only goes in the 
completely opposite direction of our demand for more inclusion of 
different stakeholders – <a href="/news/2023/news-20230323-02.html">especially the Free Software 
community</a> – but it also undermines the position of the Expert Group 
on Interoperability of European Public Services. </p> 

<p>This Expert Group consists exclusively of representatives of public 
authorities and <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/transparency/expert-groups-register/core/api/front/expertGroupAddtitionalInfo/43164/download">they demanded 
(.pdf)</a> back in 2021 to work <italic>“closely with different stakeholders”. Some 
of them “private partners, local entities (e.g involving regions, 
municipalities), EU standardisation and other international 
organistations (OECD, UN, international standardisation bodies, etc.) 
as well as citizens’ representatives depending on the subjects to be 
handled”</italic>. With the current proposal, none of these stakeholders could 
even be invited to a board meeting nor be an observer, <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/RegData/docs_autres_institutions/commission_europeenne/com/2022/0720/COM_COM(2022)0720_EN.pdf">
as proposed by the European Commission (.pdf).</a></p> 

<p>The European Parliament would also not be part of the Interoperable 
Europe Board, which the Parliament's rapporteur, Ivars Ijabs -Renew 
Europe member- understandably changes in <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/doceo/document/ITRE-PR-745497_EN.pdf">his draft report (.pdf) by suggesting to give the Institution a 
seat</a>. Members of the European Parliament, like Jordi Solé on behalf 
of the Verts/ALE Group, also call for the inclusion of Free Software 
communities, which is mostly  in line with <a href="/news/2023/news-20230323-02.html">our demands.</a> 
</p>

<p>Furthermore, the Council has failed in defining Open Standards, 
while doing very little to improve the way monitoring will be carried 
out after such legislation comes into force. The Council has also not 
taken note of the need for a proper budget allocation that will assist 
public administrations in executing the activities that will follow 
with this Act. At least a definition of ‘Open Source licence’ includes 
the four freedoms has been introduced [Art. 2 (8b)]. This underlines the 
strong link between Free Software and interoperability. </p>

<p> As the European Parliament will agree on its draft position on the 
Interoperable Europe Act in the coming weeks, we urge EU lawmakers to 
address this matter by improving the Commission’s proposal, in order to 
ensure a robust and inclusive governance structure in which different 
stakeholders, including the Free Software community, can be part of the 
Interoperable Europe Board. A proper monitoring workflow and evaluation 
together with a dedicated budget are also very much needed to move 
forward. Right now, Europe has the chance to pave the way for a 
legislation that allows efficient, innovative cross-border 
administration by recognising the crucial role that Free Software and 
its community play in interoperability. </p> 

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/67/b6/6254c3286c9ade71e1b1d6b3868c.jpg" alt="EU building with flags from the different EU countries"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230623-01.html</link>
    <tags>
	 <tag key="front-page"/>
	 <tag key="european-parliament">European Parliament</tag>
	 <tag key="policy">European Public Policy</tag>
	 <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
	</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1043"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
