<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-05-11">
    <title>EU Parliament wants to protect Free Software in AI regulation</title>
    <body>
      <p>
Today the European Parliament's responsible committees voted by a large majority to protect Free Software in the AI regulation. The plenary is called upon to uphold the idea. Likewise, this principle must be anchored in the ongoing Cyber Resilience Act and  Product Liability Directive and their upcoming votes.
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>EU Parliament wants to protect Free Software in AI regulation</h1>

<p>
Today the European Parliament's responsible committees voted by a large majority to protect Free Software in the AI regulation. The plenary is called upon to uphold the idea. Likewise, this principle must be anchored in the ongoing Cyber Resilience Act and  Product Liability Directive and their upcoming votes.
</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/31/97/3af0c42c3b6a4d16077e8d3b9772.jpg" alt="European Union flag with an image use for AI of a human head in the center"/>
</figure>

<p>
The two lead committees for the AI legislation, the Committee on Internal Market and Consumer Protection (IMCO) and the Committee on Civil Liberties, Justice and Home Affairs (LIBE), today voted by a large majority in favour of protecting Free Software in this legislation. Non-profit organisations and small Free Software projects up to the size of micro-enterprises,  are largely  to be  exempted from this regulation.
</p>


<blockquote><em> 
Alexander Sander, FSFE's Senior Policy Consultant, explains: "Instead of putting the responsibility on the Free Software developers, it should be put on the companies that profit from it on the market. Smaller organisations and non-profit activities, for example by foundations, must be excluded. With this vote, the Members of the European Parliament are thus recognising the reality of Free Software development and trying to protect it. The principle of transferring responsibility and liability to those who profit on the market instead of focusing on developers must also be anchored in the Cyber Resilience Act and the Product Liability Directive. This is the only way to not only protect Free Software and its contributors but also consumers and customers".
</em></blockquote>

<p>
The final vote on the AI Act is expected in the coming weeks, after which the trilogue with Parliament, Council and Commission on the final text will take place. With regard to the Cyber Resilience Act and the Product Liability Directive, the EU Parliament is currently discussing the recently submitted amendments. <a href="/news/2023/news-20230323-01.html">Further information</a>.
</p> 

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/31/97/3af0c42c3b6a4d16077e8d3b9772.jpg" alt="European Union flag with an image use for AI of a human head in the center"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230511-01.html</link>
    <tags>
 <tag key="front-page"/>
 <tag key="european-parliament">European Parliament</tag>
 <tag key="policy">European Public Policy</tag>
 <tag key="AI">AI</tag>
 <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1026"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
