<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-01-19">
    <title>Municipalities need Free Software: Recording and new mailing list</title>
    <body>
      <p>
  Dortmund is opening a new chapter in Free Software Governance and 
  inspiring municipalities all over Germany. The recording of our event 
  on 11 January 2023 is now online. Are you interested in Free Software 
  and working in a municipal administration or in politics? Join our 
  new mailing list to exchange information on Free Software in 
  municipalities!
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>Municipalities need Free Software: Recording and new mailing list</h1>  
  
<p>
  Dortmund is opening a new chapter in Free Software Governance and 
  inspiring municipalities all over Germany. The recording of our event 
  on 11 January 2023 is now online. Are you interested in Free Software 
  and working in a municipal administration or in politics? Join our 
  new mailing list to exchange information on Free Software in 
  municipalities!
</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/82/fd/197293efb2c0453d4323ed326447.png" alt="screenshot from conference with four people"/>
</figure>

<p>
  In December 2022, the City of Dortmund raised its profile as a 
  pioneer of Free Software and decided to set up a “Coordination Office 
  for Digital Sovereignty and Open Source”. On 11 January 2023, more 
  than 160 interested representatives from municipalities all over the 
  country informed themselves in an online event about the developments 
  leading to this step, about the guiding principle “Public Money? 
  Public Code!”, about Free Software Governance as the key to digital 
  sovereignty and about new perspectives for municipalities throughout 
  the country.
</p>

<p>
  The recording of the joint event of the the Do-FOSS initiative, the 
  Offene Kommunen.NRW association, the Kommunale Gemeinschaftsstelle 
  für Verwaltungsmanagement and the Free Software Foundation Europe <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/n8e8zKHjMHukYmzb4pEWJQ">can now be viewed online</a>.
</p>

<figure>
  <peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/n8e8zKHjMHukYmzb4pEWJQ"/>
</figure>

<p>
  For further discussion about Free Software in municipalities there is 
  now <a href="https://lists.fsfe.org/postorius/lists/fs-kommunen.lists.fsfe.org">a 
  new mailing list fs-kommunen (at) lists.fsfe.org</a>. We invite 
  interested parties from municipal administrations, politics and IT 
  companies as well as interested private individuals to use this list 
  for exchange of information and for networking on the topic of 
  municipal Free Software Governance. Also, Free Software related jobs 
  can be shared here.
</p>

<h3 id="free-software-and-public-money-public-code-">Free Software and “Public Money? Public Code!”</h3>

<p>
  Free Software gives everyone the right to use, study, share and 
  improve applications for any purpose. These freedoms ensure that 
  similar applications do not have to be programmed from scratch every 
  time and, thanks to transparent processes, others do not have to 
  reinvent the wheel. In large projects, expertise and costs can be 
  shared and applications paid for by the general public are available 
  to all. This promotes innovation and saves tax payers money in the 
  medium to long term. Dependencies on vendors are minimised and 
  security issues can be fixed more easily. The Free Software 
  Foundation Europe, together with over 200 organisations and 
  administrations, is therefore calling for “Public Money? Public 
  Code!” - If it is public money, it should be public code as well. 
  More information on the initiative on the <a href="https://publiccode.eu">“Public Money? Public Code!” 
  website</a>.
</p>
  
  </body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/82/fd/197293efb2c0453d4323ed326447.png" alt="screenshot from conference with four people"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230119-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="de">Germany</tag>
  <tag key="pmpc">Public Money? Public Code!</tag>
   <tag key="public-administration">Public Administrations</tag>
    <tag key="event">event</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/986"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
