<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-07-12">
    <title>"The world after Facebook, Twitter and YouTube. A new generation of the Internet?"</title>
    <body>
      <p>
Join our symposium in Cologne on September 22 to discuss the role of decentralised social media platforms in our society!
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>"The world after Facebook, Twitter and YouTube. A new generation of the Internet?"</h1>

<p>
Join our symposium in Cologne on September 22 to discuss the role of decentralised social media platforms in our society!
</p>

<figure>
     <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/2d/ab/1e119e24e0babd6863638cb9e6b5.jpg" alt="Hand holding a smartphone checking a Mastodon account with a flowery background"/>
       </figure>

<p> More and more people are turning away from social media platforms 
like Facebook and YouTube to alternatives like Mastodon and PeerTube. 
Why are they different? How are they changing the web? And how can you 
get involved in the Fediverse? Join our symposium and get an insight 
into these decentralised social networks through our talks and 
workshops on 22.09.2023!</p>

<p>The Free Software Foundation Europe, the Centre for Civic Education 
of the State of North Rhine-Westphalia and the Adult Education Centre 
Cologne are organising this free event. It is aimed at multipliers in 
political education, teachers, representatives of public institutions 
and educational establishments, as well as all interested parties.
</p>

<p>Prior knowledge and experience of decentralised social networks is not 
necessary, as the programme will include an overview of various 
decentralised services, often referred to as "Fediverse". Other topics 
include the potential and problems of decentralised services and their 
role for a democratic society. Three workshops will deal with the 
practical use of Fediverse services, the operation of own instances and 
the transfer of knowledge about decentralised social networks in an 
educational context.
</p>

<p><u><em><strong>The event will be held in German</strong></em></u>. Participation is free of charge, but online registration is required. We look forward to your participation!
</p>

<div>
<h4><strong>Event dates and registration</strong></h4>
<dl>
<dd><em>Date:</em><strong> 22.09.2023</strong></dd>
<dd><em>Time:</em><strong> 10:00 - 16:00</strong></dd>
<dd><em>Location:</em><strong> FORUM Volkshochschule im Museum am Neumarkt</strong>, Cäcilienstraße 29-33, 50667 Cologne, Germany</dd>
<dd><em>Note:</em> The event is fully booked.</dd>
</dl>
</div>


<div>
<h4><strong>Programme</strong></h4>
 <dl>
  <dt>10:00 - 12:00: Definition and fundamentals (plenary)</dt>
  <dd><strong>Keynote:</strong><em> The infrastructure of the open society in the digital age</em> - Katharina Nocun (publicist)</dd>
  <dd><strong>Input:</strong><em> What is the Fediverse? Overview and delimitation</em> - Tobias Diekershoff (friendica developer)</dd>
  <dd><strong>Input:</strong><em> Potentials and problems of centralised and decentralised services</em> - Stephanie Henkel (moderator at dresden.network)</dd>
  <dd><strong>Discussion and Q&amp;A session</strong></dd><br/>
 <dt/>
  <dt>12:00: Break for exchange and lunch snack</dt><br/>
  <dt/>
  <dt>13:00 - 16:00: Practice and parallel workshops</dt>
  <dd><strong>Practical input:</strong> From the everyday life of a Fediverse administrator - Sascha Foerster (Bonn.digital)</dd>
  <dd><strong>Workshop 1:</strong><em> Decentralised networks as a subject of political and school education</em> - Björn Friedrich (Studio im Netz e.V.)</dd>
  <dd><strong>Workshop 2:</strong><em> Using decentralised services for individuals and institutions</em> - Katharina Nocun, Tobias Diekershoff</dd>
  <dd><strong>Workshop 3:</strong><em> Running your own Fediverse instance</em> - padeluun (Digitalcourage)</dd><br/>
  <dd><strong>Closing panel:</strong><em> The future of the Fediverse</em> - Björn Friedrich, Katharina Nocun, padeluun, Sascha Foerster, Stephanie Henkel, Tobias Diekershoff</dd><br/>
  <dd><strong>Moderation:</strong> Friederike von Franqué (Wikimedia Deuschland)</dd>
</dl> 
</div>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/2d/ab/1e119e24e0babd6863638cb9e6b5.jpg" alt="Hand holding a smartphone checking a Mastodon account with a flowery background"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230712-01.html</link>
    <tags>
	 <tag key="front-page"/>
	 <tag key="de">Germany</tag>
	 <tag key="education">Education</tag>
	 <tag key="workshop">Workshop</tag>
	 <tag key="fediverse">Fediverse</tag>
	 </tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1049"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
