<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-03-23">
    <title>The Interoperable Europe Act needs a “Free Software first” approach</title>
    <body>
      <p>
	The Interoperable Europe Act (IEA) aims to assist public 
	administration to share, reuse and integrate information technology 
	and data across borders. Clear rules with concrete activities and 
	budget are missing. The role of civil society is overlooked, and 
	there are not yet clear definitions of Free Software and Open 
	Standards. 
	</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

	<h1>The Interoperable Europe Act needs a “Free Software first” approach</h1>

	<p>
	The Interoperable Europe Act (IEA) aims to assist public 
	administration to share, reuse and integrate information technology 
	and data across borders. Clear rules with concrete activities and 
	budget are missing. The role of civil society is overlooked, and 
	there are not yet clear definitions of Free Software and Open 
	Standards. 
	</p>


	<figure>
	  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/ec/9f/c38fa292722234d8cd67fea7f624.jpg" alt=" EU is aiming to create a dedicated legal framework on interoperability that until now has been non-binding"/>
	</figure>

	<p>
	With the IEA, the EU is aiming to create a dedicated legal 
	framework on interoperability that until now has been non-binding. 
	Interoperability is a core element of the ongoing digitalisation, 
	also of public services. Hence, the interplay among public 
	administration, the private sector, and civil society has to be 
	acknowledged as a crucial component to leading Europe into an 
	interoperable ecosystem. 
	</p>

	<p>
	Although we welcome that the European Commission already 
	acknowledges the importance of Free Software (also known as “Open 
	Source”) and Open Standards for interoperability, they are not 
	clearly defined. Moreover, the current text falls short of 
	recognising the role of other stakeholders in the proposed 
	governance approach, of civil society not only as 
	a provider of expertise but also as a decision-making actor. Lastly, 
	the text remains unclear with regard to concrete activities to 
	promote interoperability and a dedicated budget for such activities.
	</p>

	<h2>Let’s make things clearer</h2>
	<p>
	Free Software and Open Standards create the conditions for 
	interoperability. Free Software is crucial when building public 
	services that are accessible to everyone across borders and 
	sectors. Open Standards provide the conditions needed for those 
	systems to be able to communicate with each other enabling 
	the free sharing of data. These two prevent lock-in and other 
	artificial barriers to interoperability and promote choice between 
	vendors and technology solutions. 
	</p>

	<p>
	At the moment, Free Software and Open Standards are indicated as 
	factors to enhance interoperability; however clear definitions of 
	such are not given. Until now, the lack of definitions and clear 
	actions has led to loopholes not only in the interpretation but 
	also in the implementation of previous digital initiatives. We, 
	therefore, call upon the legislator to clearly define these two key 
	drivers in this legislation, and take the opportunity to propose 
	specific actions to promote interoperability by making use of them. 
	</p>

	<p>
	Furthermore, Free Software solutions and Open Standards should be 
	considered the default when it comes to interoperable digital 
	solutions, even more so when those are funded by public money. In 
	line with the proposed text, the“Interoperability assessment” can 
	come in handy when a public administration aims to procure a new 
	digital solution. The default should be a digital solution that 
	enhances such interoperability based on Free Software. If this is 
	not the case, public bodies must justify, based on this assessment, 
	the reasons for not arriving at such a decision. The Court of Auditors can 
	play an important role when monitoring such decisions and 
	publishing reports on publicly funded digital systems on a steady 
	basis. 
	</p>


	<h2>The more the merrier: stakeholder involvement</h2>

	<p>
	The main purpose of the public sector is to provide public services 
	that are necessary for the well-being of society. The 
	involvement of different stakeholders in the IEA should not come 
	into question. The interoperability of the public sector involves 
	the sharing of data and information among different public bodies 
	which can raise concerns among the public. Involving others, 
	especially civil society in the decision-making process will not 
	only help to build trust with the public but also ensure that 
	this regulation is guided by democratic and participatory 
	principles. 
	</p>

	<p>
	When it comes to innovation, it is important to bear in mind that 
	numerous non-governmental organisations are often at the forefront 
	of innovation and can offer new ideas and approaches. Innovation 
	doesn’t only happen in the public sector. Therefore, a larger 
	variety of stakeholders must be included as part of this governance 
	workflow, especially civil society actors. 
	</p>

	<p>
	At the moment the engagement of other stakeholders is reduced to 
	the so-called “Interoperable Community”, which aims to provide 
	expertise and input to the actual decision-making body, the 
	“Interoperable Board”. We, therefore, highlight the importance of 
	including others on this board, especially civil society. By 
	allowing a wide community to flourish, the EU could achieve its 
	most ambitious goal of building human-centred digital public 
	services. 
	</p>


	<blockquote> 
	<p><em> “The Interoperable Europe Act is a potential chance the EU has to make a major change in how procurement of digital services is handled. By going in the direction of Free Software first, the EU can assure that tax's payers money is spent in the most efficient way, while it will create the collaborative ecosystem that is needed to achieve interoperability in Europe” explains Lina Ceballos, FSFE Policy Project Manager.
	</em></p>
	</blockquote>

	<h2>Network of public administrations for re-using solutions</h2>

	<p>The IEA can be more ambitious in setting up the proper 
	assistance and network that public administrations need for the 
	digital implementation of such legislation. Currently, proposals 
	such as training are included. However, the text fails to address 
	the scope of such training or highlight the dedicated 
	budget needed for it. There is hereof clear importance of 
	training - with a proper budget allocation - for civil servants on 
	Free Software technologies, workflows, and their impact on 
	transparency and trustworthy interoperable digital infrastructure. 
	</p>

	<p>
	Bringing together best practices is also part of this initiative, 
	and it is included as one of the features that the “Interoperable 
	Europe portal” might offer. However, the promotion of the path 
	leading to those good practices is absent. In this regard, more 
	emphasis on the creation, use, and re-use of Free Software 
	solutions could strengthen the collaborative ecosystem that is 
	needed while bringing public administrations closer and enhancing 
	cross-border collaboration. 
	</p>

	<h2>Monitoring and evaluation</h2>

	<p>Monitoring plays a fundamental role within this proposal, 
	especially when it comes to how different member states approach these guidelines. The EU must enable the coordination and knowledge 
	exchange for innovative public procurement procedures among member 
	states, along with proper monitoring and evaluation strategies. 
	</p>

	<p>In order to implement proper monitoring and evaluation, the EU 
	needs to make sure to gather and make use of proper indicators and 
	statistics that show first how many of the new digital solutions 
	procured, or in-house developed, have been released under a Free 
	Software licence, and second, how many of the existing digital 
	solutions have migrated into a Free Software solution in order to 
	proceed with the “Interpretability Assessment”. 
	</p>

	<p>
	It is not possible to properly evaluate and monitor if one does 
	not have a clear understanding of the state of play and its 
	fluctuation over time. This will enable accurate oversight of the 
	way public funds are being used. Combining this monitoring with the 
	respective reports from the Code of Auditors both in the Member States  and at the EU level will only enrich the procedure. 
	</p>

	<h2>Conclusion</h2>

	<p>An open and interoperable digital public sector is critical to 
	addressing the social, economic, and political challenges of 
	democratic nations. 
	</p>

	<p>
	The proposed Interoperable Europe Act has the potential to be a 
	game changer by allowing the EU to lead by example on the 
	digitalisation path without having to reinvent the wheel over and 
	over again. However, concrete activities, along with a dedicated 
	budget, are needed to support member states and local 
	administration all over Europe. Much clearer definitions of the key 
	elements of this digital ecosystem must also be included. If  the 
	interoperability of digital public services is to keep the interest 
	of people at its centre, their involvement and agency in such 
	processes must guide these efforts. 
	</p>

	<p>
	This legislation is a potential opportunity to close the existing 
	loopholes as well as define clear monitoring and evaluation 
	indicators while laying the groundwork for the proper budget allocation 
	needed for these efforts. This is, indeed, the legislation where 
	Free Software and Open Standards must lead the way in the design 
	and delivery of accessible and open public digital services. 
	</p>

	</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/ec/9f/c38fa292722234d8cd67fea7f624.jpg" alt=" EU is aiming to create a dedicated legal framework on interoperability that until now has been non-binding"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230323-02.html</link>
    <tags>
	 <tag key="front-page"/>
	 <tag key="european-parliament">European Parliament</tag>
	 <tag key="policy">European Public Policy</tag>
	 <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
	</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1006"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
