<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-12-01">
    <title>Austria goes against Router Freedom </title>
    <body>
      <p>The Austrian Regulatory Authority for Broadcasting and 
Telecommunications, RTR, has decided  not to regulate the network 
operators with regard to Router Freedom, allowing Internet Service Providers (ISPs) to impose their 
equipment on consumers. For RTR, routers configured in “bridge mode” is 
synonymous with terminal equipment freedom. The FSFE laments this 
decision as a missed opportunity for Net Neutrality in Austria. 
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>Austria goes against Router Freedom </h1>

<p>The Austrian Regulatory Authority for Broadcasting and 
Telecommunications, RTR, has decided  not to regulate the network 
operators with regard to Router Freedom, allowing Internet Service Providers (ISPs) to impose their 
equipment on consumers. For RTR, routers configured in “bridge mode” is 
synonymous with terminal equipment freedom. The FSFE laments this 
decision as a missed opportunity for Net Neutrality in Austria. 
</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/9f/ec/5ea9fb812fdccd5e90966ebe309f.png" alt="Illustration of the network termination point showing a modem, as a private network, and the connecting internet demarcation, as a public communication network"/>
  <figcaption>The Austrian regulator RTR has decided that it should not formally determine the position of the NTP. This means that end-users cannot freely use their modems for internet connection.</figcaption> 
  </figure>

<p>In 2016, the Net Neutrality regulation established, for the first 
time in Europe, <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/routers/fsfe-router-freedom-activity-summary.pdf">freedom of terminal equipment for internet connection</a>. 
It means that, in theory, consumers would be able to choose and use their 
own routers and modems independently from those provided by the 
ISPs. However, <a href="https://umap.openstreetmap.fr/en/map/router-freedom-tracker_581123#4/53.12/18.37">the practical realisation 
of this right has not followed a linear process</a>, but has been marked by 
several difficulties, including the 2018 reform of EU telecom law, the 
implementation of technical rules, and the resistance from national 
regulators to interfere in the activities of operators. 

While several countries such as Germany, Finland, the Netherlands, and Belgium have 
decided on <a href="/tags/tagged-routers.html">full regulatory protection of Router Freedom</a>, other EU 
members have followed other paths, preferring to  exclude fiber 
networks (as in Greece and Italy) or deciding completely against freedom 
of terminal equipment, as in Latvia, Denmark, and now Austria. </p>

<h2>Consumer protection falls short</h2>

<p>In November 2023, the Austrian telecom regulator RTR published <a href="https://www.ots.at/presseaussendung/OTS_20231110_OTS0116/rtr-schliesst-evaluierung-der-routerfreiheit-ab">a 
decision on the evaluation of Router Freedom and the position of the 
network termination point (NTP) (DE)</a>, a demarcation of the limits of the 
public and private networks. The regulator has concluded not to 
regulate Router Freedom due to some alleged factors, including the 
limited usage by end-users of private routers and the enhanced 
operational costs for network operators.  RTR has also claimed that the 
mere fact that Austrian providers already offer end-users the 
possibility to connect their own routers to the ISP’s modem in “bridge 
mode” would constitute freedom of terminal equipment. This, as we explain 
below, is a contradiction in itself. Of particular concern is  RTR’s 
statement affirming that there is currently insufficient evidence of 
significant restrictions on Router Freedom  for a relevant proportion 
of users (page 3).</p>

<h2>A lost opportunity for Net Neutrality</h2> 

<p>RTR’s position fails 
to capture the notion of Router Freedom as a fundamental aspect of Net 
Neutrality, as freedom of terminal equipment has a profound impact on how end-users access the 
Internet. Router Freedom is the hardware component of  Net Neutrality, 
and its protection should be understood not only from the market 
perspective, but should embrace its nature as an essential element of 
the Open Internet.</p>

<p>Formally defining the position of the <a href="/news/2020/news-20200601-01.html">NTP at Point A</a> would 
officially include the modem and router within the end-user premises, 
and the public network would begin from the plug on the wall. That 
would constitute complete freedom of terminal equipment. RTR’s decision 
instead only guarantees that end-users can connect their routers to 
ISPs’ modems in “bridge mode”. Since operators can require use of their modems inside end-users’ premises, 
the decision cannot be considered compliant with Router Freedom.</p>
 
<p>Early on in 2021, when Austria was in the process of implementing 
the reform of the telecom sector, the FSFE, together with the Austrian organisation
<a href="https://epicenter.works/">epicenter.works</a>, urged the Austrian government to safeguard Router 
Freedom in the newly adopted legislation. <a href="/news/2021/news-20210506-01.html">We warned back then</a> that 
if the decision on Router Freedom were to be delegated to the 
national regulatory agency (RTR) this could lead to outcomes against 
consumer rights and interests.</p>
 
<p>In 2022, <a href="/news/2022/news-20220420-01.html">we engaged with a wide range of stakeholders</a>, including 
representatives from industry and policy makers, to demonstrate why 
Router Freedom is important for market competition, device innovation, 
and sustainability. At the time, we urged RTR to seize the opportunity 
to establish Router Freedom in Austria by defining the NTP in a 
position favourable to consumer interests.</p> 

<p>In May 2023, we sent to RTR our <a href="/news/2023/news-20230515-02.html">report on the Router Freedom survey</a>, 
demonstrating how ISPs still hamper 
consumer freedom of choice, exercise lock-in over internet equipment, 
and promote proprietary devices, negatively affecting consumer welfare, 
security, privacy, and data protection. Although more than 13% of the 
participants were Austrians, the regulator has not provided feedback on 
this.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/f7/ba/b3eeb6363c93efb45456a6aa8e11.jpg" alt="Graphic showing the participants of the survey answers regarding the importance of Router Freedom principles"/>
  <figcaption>The vast majority of participants in our survey agreed that Router Freedom is important for freedom of choice, privacy, security, and fair competition. More than a market or tech issue, Router Freedom is a policy demand.
</figcaption> 
  </figure>

<p>Besides, while other member states regulators have conducted open 
consultations and produced <a href="/news/2023/news-20231113-02.html">comprehensive reports and detailed studies</a> 
regarding Router Freedom, RTR has not provided any relevant data, nor 
conducted consultation procedures where civil society stakeholders were 
broadly involved. This lack of transparency negatively affects the 
monitoring on Open Internet in the country.</p>

<p>The FSFE laments that RTR was not able to find a balance among 
business, investment considerations, and consumer protection, 
preferring to align themselves with telecom operators instead of taking 
a step towards Net Neutrality and Open Internet.</p> 

<h2>Aiming at the future: there will be room for improvement</h2>

<p>As noted by RTR, the present decision is not definitive, and the regulator will re-evaluate this framework in the 
future. Neither deadlines nor a time schedule were provided, though. 
Although we regret the long period such regulatory decisions normally 
require, there will be still room for improvement, and we will 
continue to closely monitor the situation in Austria.</p>

<p>Zooming out, as an example, in <a href="https://op.europa.eu/en/publication-detail/-/publication/e1f1154f-ee2f-11ed-a05c-01aa75ed71a1">a study conducted on behalf of the 
European Commission</a>, Router Freedom was considered one of the 
priorities for the proper implementation of Net Neutrality in Europe. 
Regulators have to take utmost account of this freedom when 
designing their policies for the telecommunications sector. Besides, 
emerging issues regarding devices, optical fiber networks, and satellite 
connections are still  under intense debate on different levels at the 
EU and member states. Aspects of <a href="/news/2022/news-20220510-01.html">sustainability of the telecom sector</a> 
are also being discussed. All those elements have been monitored by the 
FSFE, and Router Freedom will be an important element for policy 
making.</p>


<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/e15021d00f32dc067d894525d6213354.png" alt="Illustration with the reasons why Router Freedom needs Free Software"/>
  <figcaption>Router Freedom enables the right to repair and promotes fair competition. Free Software in a router can greatly extend the device’s lifespan and increase energy management. These advantages can lead to major wins in future policy making.</figcaption> 
  </figure>


<h2>The Router Freedom initiative</h2> 

<p><a href="/activities/routers/index.html">Router Freedom</a> is the right that customers of any ISP are able to 
choose and use a private modem and router instead of equipment provided 
by the operator. Since 2013, the Free Software Foundation Europe has 
been successfully engaged with Router Freedom, promoting end-users’ 
freedom in many European countries. Join us and learn more about the 
several <a href="/news/2021/news-20210330-01.html">ways to get involved</a>. Please consider <a href="/donate?mtm_campaign=routers">becoming a FSFE donor</a>; 
you help make possible our long-term engagement and professional 
commitment in defending people’s rights to control technology.
</p>


</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/9f/ec/5ea9fb812fdccd5e90966ebe309f.png" alt="Illustration about the network termination point showing a modem, as a private network, and the connecting internet point, as a public communication network"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20231201-01.html</link>
    <tags>
 <tag key="front-page"/>
 <tag key="at">Austria</tag>
 <tag key="routers">Router Freedom</tag>
 <tag key="deviceneutrality">Device Neutrality</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1111"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
