<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-12-20">
    <title>CLOSED - FSFE is hiring an office coordinator</title>
    <body>
      <p>
  We are looking for an office coordinator for an open-ended 25-35 hours per week position in our
  Berlin office. As part of our office management team you will be the
  administrative backbone of our operations. Our ideal candidate has experience
  as an office administrator, secretary, event organiser, or another relevant
  administrative role. 
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>FSFE is hiring an office coordinator</h1>

<p>
  We are looking for an office coordinator for an open-ended 25-35 hours per week position in our
  Berlin office. As part of our office management team you will be the
  administrative backbone of our operations. Our ideal candidate has experience
  as an office administrator, secretary, event organiser, or another relevant
  administrative role. 
</p>

<h2>About the FSFE</h2>

<p>
  Free Software Foundation Europe is a charity that empowers users to control
  technology. Software is deeply involved in all aspects of our lives and it is
  important that technology empowers rather than restricts us. <a href="/freesoftware/">Free Software</a> gives everybody the rights to use,
  understand, share, and improve software. These rights help support other
  fundamental freedoms like freedom of speech, press, and privacy.
</p>

<p>
  The FSFE helps individuals and organisations to understand how Free Software
  contributes to freedom, transparency, and self-determination. We enhance
  users' rights by abolishing barriers to Free Software adoption, encourage
  people to use and develop Free Software, and provide resources to enable
  everyone to further promote Free Software in Europe.
</p>

<p>
  We are involved in <a href="/activities/">many activities</a> in the
  legal, economic, political, and technical areas around Free Software.
  Our work is made possible by a community of volunteers, supporters,
  donors, and staff. 
</p>

  <figure>
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/6a/ba/863f3dbd7fdfd6ffbd24c64f38af.jpg" alt="FSFE staff team at SFSCon 2022 in Bolzano, Italy"/>
  </figure>

<p>
  We are a distributed team of dedicated volunteers and employees from all
  around the world united in the spirit of empowering users to control technology.
  We know it will take a long time to achieve our mission, but we know we can
  achieve it together with persistence step by step. As a family-friendly organisation we can offer flexible working hours.
</p>


<h2 id="main-responsibilities">Main responsibilities</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Review financial documents, preparing them for accounting, and general (mainly electronic) filing.</li>
  <li>Communicate with our salary service, health insurance, bank, insurances, and other authorities.</li>
  <li>Handle sourcing vendors, (re)-ordering, organising, invoicing, shipping, and the inventory for our information material and merchandise.</li>
  <li>Manage office equipment including organising smaller and bigger office supplies, assets inventory, and key management.</li>
  <li>Pay invoices and salaries as well as travel expense claims.</li>
  <li>Issue outgoing invoices and monitor incoming payments.</li>
  <li>Organise, store, and print organisational documents as needed.</li>
  <li>Prepare financial reports and presentations</li>
  <li>Help to constantly improve our administrative processes.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="qualifications">Qualifications</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Proven experience as an administrator, administrative assistant, office coordinator, or another related role.</li>
  <li>Basic knowledge of accounting and German tax law.</li>
  <li>Knowledge and experience in understanding the financial side of the charitable non-profit sector are an advantage.</li>
  <li>Fluency in written and spoken German, intermediate command of written and spoken English; other European languages are considered an asset.</li>
  <li>Knowledge of how to handle the administrative side of EU-funded projects are a plus.</li>
  <li>Familiarity with office equipment and office management tools (Free Software tools is a plus).</li>
</ul>

  <figure>
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/59/77/a6f3026662736d1fbab6e3902aec.jpg" alt="Two staffers from finance team couunting money during inventory"/>
  </figure>

<h2 id="attitude">Attitude</h2>

<p>
  We are looking for a reliable, well-organised, and punctual team player with
  a problem-solving attitude and an eye for detail who would like to strengthen
  our administrative backbone in Berlin, so that the many people in the FSFE
  can continue to empower users to control technology.
</p>

  <figure>
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/f950c5bdd4accb6f9082f91f06a8f882.jpg" alt="A picture of our promo rack in the office"/>
  </figure>

<h2 id="apply">How to apply</h2>

<p>
  To apply, please send a maximum one-page cover letter – including
  the desired hours per week and when you could start – and a maximum two-page CV (only PDFs
  are accepted) by email to <email mailto="yes">jobs@fsfe.org</email>, with
  the subject "organisational wizard". Please do not include pictures of
  yourself in the application.
</p>

<p>
  Your personal data will be deleted 3 months after we have made our
  decision.
</p>

<p>
  Free Software is meant to serve everyone regardless of their age,
  ability or disability, gender identity, sex, race, religion, or
  sexual orientation. Hence, we encourage applications from all
  backgrounds and promise to judge all applications on merit, without
  reference to any of the characteristics listed. To promote diversity
  and equality in the Free Software community, we shall give preference
  to applicants who identify as part of a traditionally marginalised
  demographic in technology for applications of equal strength.
</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/f5/3b/b98dc3986fbb6ef00d0cc12073ab.jpg" alt="Two staffers from finance team counting money during inventory."/>
    <link>/news/2022/news-20221220-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="internal">FSFE Internal</tag>
  <tag key="career">Job Position</tag>
</tags>
  </news>
</newsset>
