<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--If you want to change to heart bullets back to normal points edit the index.en.xhtml in activities/ilovefs-->
<data>
	<version>12</version>
	<module>
	
		<h2>I ♥ Free Software Day 2025: Hidden projects</h2>

		<p>
		“I Love Free Software Day” is a long-lasting tradition. On this 
		day, we thank all the people behind Free Software projects or programs 
		and let them know that their work does not go unnoticed. Let’s 
		celebrate all the wonderful people working for Free Software together: 
		join the “I Love Free Software Day” celebrations all over Europe. Get 
		in touch with your <a href="/about/groups.html">local 
		FSFE group</a> and organise a fun meeting.
		</p>

		<p>
		We are grateful to those who work and contribute to the Free Software 
		universe: developers, designers, translators, advocates, contributors, 
		users, and more. There are a lot of different Free Software 
		communities out there, with different values or different focuses in 
		their work. But we all contribute to Free Software and value the 
		freedom to use, study, share and improve software. Let's celebrate our 
		appreciation for Free Software and the people behind it with a simple 
		<q>Thank you!</q>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		For this 12th edition of the "I Love Free Software Day" we have a 
		special focus on Free Software projects that are not on the 
		front line. In a world that is becoming more and more digital, Free Software is 
		everywhere. It is in your car, on your router, on the servers that run 
		our daily infrastructure. Often these projects are hidden so they do not 
		get the focus they deserve to keep our daily lives up and running. 
		This year our celebrations will focus on those hidden projects.
		</p>

		<h2 id="events">Join the celebrations for "I Love Free Software Day 2025"</h2>
		
		<p>
		You want to participate in the "I Love Free Software Day 2025"? Join 
		any of the events listed below **more are coming soon** and follow us 
		on <a href="https://mastodon.social/@fsfe">social media</a> to stay 
		updated:
		</p>

  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">

	  <li>🇬🇧  FSFE <strong>Potteries</strong>, Staffordshire (UK)
          <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
            <li>⏰ 13.02.2025, 18:30 (GMT)</li>
            <li>📍 Upstairs at <a 
            href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Potteries/KPA%20Clubhouse">KPA 
            Clubhouse, 97 Horwood Road, Keele University, Keele, 
            Staffordshire</a></li>
            
          </ul>
        </li>
	<li>🇩🇪 <strong>Nuremberg</strong>, Germany
	  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 13.02.2025, 19:00 (CET)</li>
	   <li>📍 TBA</li>
	   
	  </ul>		
	</li>
</ul>


	<p>
	If you want to organise an event in your local area feel free to take a 
	look at our toolkit <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/campaigns/ilovefs/toolkit/">toolkit</a> for local groups. In this kit you find resources 
	for organising your own I Love Free Software Day event. reach 
	out to us via <a 
	href="/contact/">email</a>. For "I Love Free Software 
	Day 2025" we want to organise events dedicated for Free Software 
	projects that are a part of our core infrastructure.
	</p>
	<ul class="ilovefs-ul">
		<li>
		Contact your local library and organise a talk about Free Software and the four freedoms
		</li>
		<li>
		Contact your <a 
		href="https://wiki.hackerspaces.org/List_of_Hacker_Spaces">local 
		hackerspace</a> and organise a Free Software meet-up with them
		</li>
		<li>
		Contact local Free Software companies and organise an event with them
		</li>
		<li>
		Reach out to your <a 
		href="/about/groups.html">local Free Software group</a>, local Linux 
	User Group or digital rights groups and organise 
		an event together!
		</li>
	</ul>
		
		
		<div class="icon-grid">
			<ul>
				<li>
					<img src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-use.png" 
						alt="ILoveFS heart with “use”"
					/>
					<div>
						<h3>Say thanks</h3>
						<p>Think about a Free Software project that you are grateful for and that deserves more attention. Reach out to them on the 14th of February to 
						say thank you. Organise a local group meeting or spread the word 
						about Free 
						Software. You can use our <a 
						href="https://sharepic.fsfe.org/#ilovefs">sharepics</a>, <a 
						href="/contribute/spreadtheword#ilovefs">stickers and 
						balloons</a>, or <a 
						href="/activities/ilovefs/artwork/artwork.html">artwork</a>, and <a 
						href="/order/order.html">
						merchandise</a> for <em>#ilovefs</em>.</p>
					</div>
				</li>
				<li>
					<img src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-study.png" 
						alt="ILoveFS heart with 'study'"
					/>
					<div>
						<h3>Remember the good times</h3>
						<p>Which Free Software project did you use in the past year? What 
						felt empowering? What was fun? For some inspiration have a look at 
						others’ <a 
						href="/activities/ilovefs/whylovefs/gallery.html">love 
						statements</a> and <a 
						href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/p/u3Ep8hRP5vFdbgUE9LKScW">videos</a>.</p>
					</div>
				</li>
				<li>
					<img 
						src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-share.png" 
						alt="ILoveFS heart with 'share'"
					/>
					<div>
						<h3>Share your love</h3>
						<p>That’s the fun part! We have created a <a 
						href="https://sharepic.fsfe.org/#ilovefs">sharepic generator</a>, 
						with which you can easily create your very own sharepics and share 
						your appreciation on social media (<em>#ilovefs</em>), in blog 
						posts, pictures and <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/p/u3Ep8hRP5vFdbgUE9LKScW">video 
						messages</a>, or <a href="/contribute/spreadtheword.html#ilovefs">directly to the Free 
						Software developers and contributors</a>.</p>
					</div>
				</li>
				<li>
					<img 
						src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-improve.png" 
						alt="ILoveFS heart with 'improve'"
					/>
					<div>
						<h3>Improve Free Software</h3>
						<p>Talking is silver, contributing is gold! Help a Free Software project with a donation, a translation or by assisting its users. If 
						you can, please consider supporting our work with a <a 
						href="/donate">donation to the Free Software Foundation 
						Europe</a>.</p>
					</div>
				</li>
			</ul>
		</div>

		<figure class="no-border">
			<img
				src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/53/44/afdfea246e5c2aec0d1d888da5da.jpg"
				alt="#ilovefs"
			/>
		</figure>

		<p>
		What is your contribution to this special day dedicated to the people 
		who enable you to use Free Software? Will you use our stickers and 
		balloons? Or make a picture or video with your new ILoveFS shirt? And 
		what about celebrating software freedom with your colleagues and 
		friends at a company gathering or public event? Whatever you do, show 
		it to the world by using the <em>#ilovefs</em> tag. And if you have 
		questions, <a 
		href="/contact/">just drop us an email</a>.
		</p>

		<p>Happy <strong><span class="text-danger">I Love Free Software</span></strong> Day everyone! ❤</p>
	</module>
</data>
