<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--If you want to change to heart bullets back to normal points edit the index.en.xhtml in activities/ilovefs-->
<data>
	<version>12</version>
	<module>

		<h2 id="theme-2025">I ♥ Free Software Day 2025: Hidden projects</h2>

		<p>
		“I Love Free Software Day” is a long-lasting tradition. On this 
		day, we thank all the people behind Free Software projects or programs 
		and let them know that their work does not go unnoticed. Let’s 
		celebrate all the wonderful people working for Free Software together: 
		join the “I Love Free Software Day” celebrations all over Europe. Get 
		in touch with your <a href="/about/groups.html">local 
		FSFE group</a> and organise a fun meeting.
		</p>

		<p>
		We are grateful to those who work and contribute to the Free Software 
		universe: developers, designers, translators, advocates, contributors, 
		users, and more. There are a lot of different Free Software 
		communities out there, with different values or different focuses in 
		their work. But we all contribute to Free Software and value the 
		freedom to use, study, share and improve software. Let's celebrate our 
		appreciation for Free Software and the people behind it with a simple 
		<q>Thank you!</q>
		</p>
		
		<p>
		For this 12th edition of the "I Love Free Software Day" we have a 
		special focus on Free Software projects that are not on the 
		front line. In a world that is becoming more and more digital, Free Software is 
		everywhere. It is in your car, on your router, on the servers that run 
		our daily infrastructure. Often these projects are hidden so they do not 
		get the focus they deserve to keep our daily lives up and running. 
		This year our celebrations will focus on those hidden projects.
		</p>

		<h2 id="events">Join the celebrations for "I Love Free Software Day 2025"</h2>
		
		<p>
		You want to participate in the "I Love Free Software Day 2025"? Join 
		any of the events listed below **more are coming soon** and follow us 
		on <a href="https://mastodon.social/@fsfe">social media</a> to stay 
		updated:
		</p>

<h2 id="community-groups">Celebrations and events in Europe</h2>

<h2 id="albania">🇦🇱 Albania</h2>
      <li><strong>Tiranë</strong>
	  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 15.02.2025 11:00 (CET)</li>
	   <li>📍 <a href="https://osm.org/go/xexSkTKX8?layers=N">KubFranceTirana, Pyramid of Tirana, Tiranë, Albania</a></li>
	   <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 Tirana event is open for anyone curious about technology and Free Software</li>
	   <li>Agenda:
	     <li>Presentation of LibreLabs</li>
        <li>Talks on I Love Free Software Day and why it matters</li>
        <li>Presentation of the Public Money, Public Code campaign and the progress so far</li>
        <li>Open discussion with free software advocates</li>
      </li>
    </ul>
    </li>
	
  <h2 id="austria">🇦🇹 Austria</h2>
      <li><strong>Villach in Carinthia</strong>
	  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 14.02.2025 16:00 (CET)</li>
	   <li>📍 Lederergasse 18, 9500 Villach, Austria</li>
	   <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 Carinthia event is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts from Carinthia. There will be a small installation party featuring F-Droid, Linux, and more, we express our thanks to maintainers, and enjoy good coffee and cake together. It’s the perfect setting to chat about Free Software topics and also to install some! :) More information is available on our <a href="https://www.carinthianlinuxday.at/">webpage</a>.</li>
	  </ul>		
	</li>
	
  <h2 id="germany">🇩🇪 Germany</h2>
      <li><strong>Nuremberg</strong>
	  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 13.02.2025, 18:00 (CET)</li>
	   <li>📍 Deutschherrnstr. 15-19, 90412 Nürnberg in the <a href="https://netways.de/events/">Schulungsraum, building K</a> from NETWAYS.</li>
	   <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 Nürnberg event is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts from Franken. There will be talks and networking with pizza and drinks.</li>
	   <li><strike>You can register here</strike>. Registration for this event is now closed.</li>
	   <li>Agenda:
	    <ol>
			<li> Welcoming and I Love Free Software Day by Bonnie Mehring</li>
			<li> <a href="https://exchange.icinga.com/joseffriedrich/check_systemd">check_systemd</a> by Josef Friedrich</li>
			<li> openSuse by Douglas DeMaio</li>
			<li> Geekofoundation by Patrick</li>
			<li> SUSE history and ESG by Dirk Müller</li>
			<li> OpenCloud by Klaas Freitag</li>
			<li> Pizza - Fun - Networking</li>
	    </ol> </li>
	  </ul>		
	</li>
	<li><strong>Berlin</strong> 
	<ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	 <li>⏰ 14.02.2025, from 14:00 till 16:00 (CET)</li>
	<li>📍 <a href="https://www.berlin.de/stadtbibliothek-spandau/">Bezirkszentralbibliothek Spandau</a>, Carl-Schurz-Str. 13 (Not far from Spandau railway station)</li>
		    <li>What: Lectures, Linux and other Free Software to try out</li>
	        <li>Please note: The event will be held mostly in German but many of the attendees can switch to English. The Berlin group of the Free Software Foundation Europe will meet for the 
	    I Love Free Software Day this year in the seminar room of the Spandau District Central Library. In addition to saying Thanks! together, there will be lectures on Free Software and 
	    hands-on notebooks with Linux for those interested in trying out Free Software. Details about the programme can be found on the page of the Berlin 
	    group in the <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Events/Berlin/2025-02-14">FSFE wiki</a>.</li>
	    <li>Afterwards we want to look for a pizzeria nearby: if you want to join us, you are welcome to register without obligation so that we can make a reservation in advance if necessary.</li>
    </ul>
    </li>
    
	<li><strong>Frankfurt am Main</strong>
	  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 14.02.2025, 19:00 (CET)</li>
       <li>📍 <a href="https://ccc-ffm.de/">Chaos Computer Club Frankfurt e.V.</a>, more information about the event <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/RheinMain">here</a>.</li>
	   <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 CCC FFM event is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts from Hesse.</li>
	  </ul>		
	</li>
	
    <h2 id="italy">🇮🇹 Italy</h2>

<li><strong>I Love Free Software Day in Bozen-Bolzano</strong>
      <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
			<li>⏰ 10.02.2025, 20:00 till 23:00 (CET)</li>
			<li>📍 Spazio77, via Dalmazia 77 - Dalmatienstraße 77 - Bozen-Bolzano - Italy </li>
			<li>The I Love Free Software Day from the Linux User group in Bozen-bolzano is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all South Tyrol Free Software enthusiasts. For more information 
			visit our <a href="https://lugbz.org/i-love-free-software-day-2025/">webpage.</a></li>
		</ul>
		</li>    
    
    <li><strong>I Love Free Software Day in Sicilia</strong>
      <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
			<li>⏰ 11.02.2025, 09:00 till 14:00 (CET)</li>
			<li>📍 Via Leone XIII 48/d, 93100, Caltanissetta (CL), Sicilia </li>
			<li> The I Love Free Software Day from the FSFE local group in Sicilia is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Sicilians Free Software enthusiasts.</li>
		</ul>
		</li>
		
		<li><strong>I Love Free Software Day in Este (PD)</strong>
      <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
			<li>⏰ 15.02.2025, 14:30 till 18:30 (CET)</li>
			<li>📍 <a href="https://osmapp.org/way/158649144">Patronato Ss. Redentore primo piano, Este (PD)</a></li>
			<li> The I Love Free Software Day from the EsteLug in Este is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts. For more information visit our <a href="https://este.linux.it/novita/i-love-fs-2025/">webpage.</a></li>
		</ul>
		</li>
		
			<li><strong>I Love Free Software Day in Bergamo</strong>
      <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
			<li>⏰ 15.02.2025, 16:00 till open end (CET)</li>
			<li>📍 Biblioteca Tiraboschi, via San Bernardino 74 (BG) </li>
			<li> The I Love Free Software Day from the Bergamo Linux User Group is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts. We will have a session
			about the famous <a href= "/activities/ada-zangemann/">Ada &amp; Zangemann</a> book. For more information visit our <a href="https://biblioteche.comune.bergamo.it/sites/bgsbu/assets/SBU-Bergamo/Ragazzi/TIR_AdaeZangemann.png">webpage.</a></li>
		</ul>
		</li>
     
     
     <h2 id="luxembourg">🇱🇺 Luxembourg</h2>
      <li><strong>Luxembourg Ville</strong>
		<ul class="ilovefs-ul">
			<li>⏰ 13.02.2025, 18:00 (CET)</li>
			<li>📍 <a href="https://www.syn2cat.lu/">Level 2 Hackerspace</a> 87 route de Thionville L-2611 Luxembourg, Europe</li>
				<li>ILoveFS Luxembourg is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts where you get the chance to: express your gratitude for Free Software, discuss the future of Free Software, and network with other community members over pizza and drinks. <a href="https://pretix.eu/oslu/ilovefs-lu-2025/">Reserve your spot now!</a></li>
		</ul>
   	</li>

  <h2 id="netherlands">🇳🇱 Netherlands</h2>
      <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
			<li>⏰ 14.02.2025, 19:30 (CET)</li>
			<li>📍 <a href="https://hackerspacenijmegen.nl/Opensource-avond-2024">Hackerspace Nijmegen</a>  Villanovastraat 4 Nijmegen</li>
				<li>ILoveFS Netherlands is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts. We are happy to discuss the future of Free Software, and network with other 
				community members over pizza and drinks. <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Events/Netherlands/2025-02-14">More information is on our webpage!</a></li>
				<li> Please <a href="https://share.fsfe.org/apps/forms/s/3Jwsx3WMXT3g3TjgLLcs9KPi">register</a> for attending the event</li>
		</ul>
      
  <h2 id="poland">🇵🇱 Poland</h2>
      <li><strong>Warsaw</strong> 
    	<ul class="ilovefs-ul">
       		<li> ⏰ 12.02.2025 19:00 (CET)</li>
       		<li>📍<a href="https://ilfs.reszka.org/">Warsaw Hackerspace</a>, Żelazna 103A, 01-017 Warszawa</li>
	        <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 Warsaw event is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts from Poland. There will be a workshop, a discussion panel, and networking with pizza and drinks. You can learn more at the <a href="https://ilfs.reszka.org/">event website.</a></li>
		</ul>
    </li>
    <li><strong>Poznań</strong>
	  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 13.02.2025 18:00 (CET)</li>
	   <li>📍 Wydział Informatyki i Telekomunikacji at Politechniki Poznańskiej, ul. Polanka 3, Poznań</li>
	   <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 Poznań event is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts from Poland. There will be lightning talks and networking with pizza and drinks. You can learn more at <a href="https://hspoz.pl/ilovefs2025/">their website.</a></li>
	  </ul>		
	</li>
	<li><strong>Wrocław</strong>
	  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 14.02.2025 18:00 (CET)</li>
	   <li>📍 Sala 20, budynek C-3, Politechnika Wrocławska</li>
	   <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 Wrocław event is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts from Poland. There will be a workshop, a discussion panel, and networking with pizza and drinks. You can learn more at <a href="https://ilfs.linuksowa.pl/">their website.</a></li>
	  </ul>		
	</li>
	
	<h2 id="portugal"> 🇵🇹Portugal</h2>
	<li><strong><a href="https://ansol.org/ansol.html">ANSOL</a>, the FSFE's <a href="/about/associates/associates.html">associated organisation</a></strong> 
	 <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 14.02.2025 22:00 till 23:00 (UTC)</li>
	   <li>📍 Celebrates the "I Love Free Software Day" online.</li>
	   <li> See more information on their <a href= "https://ansol.org/eventos/2025-02-14-ilovefs/">webpage</a></li>
	   </ul>
	   </li>

  <h2 id="spain">🇪🇸 Spain</h2>
      <li><strong>Barcelona</strong>
	  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 13.02.2025, 19:00 (CET)</li>
	   <li>📍 <a href="https://akasha.barcelona/">AKASHA Hub Barcelona</a>, Carrer de la Verneda, 19, Local 1, Barcelona</li>
	   <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 Barcelona event is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts from Catalonia. There will be talks and networking with pizza and drinks.</li>
	  </ul>		
	</li>
	
	<li><strong>Madrid</strong>
	  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
	   <li>⏰ 13.02.2025</li>
	   <li>📍<a href="https://makespacemadrid.org/"> Makespace de Madrid</a> (C Ruiz Palacios 7) 28020 Madrid, Spain</li>
	   <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 Madrid event is open for everybody and we are happy to welcome all Free Software enthusiasts from Madrid. 
	   There will be talks and networking with pizza and drinks.</li>
	  </ul>		
	</li>
  
  <h2 id="switzerland">🇨🇭 Switzerland</h2>
      	<li><strong>Zürich</strong>
		  <ul class="ilovefs-ul">
		   <li>⏰ 13.02.2025, 17:00 (CET)</li>
		   <li>📍<a href="https://www.ccczh.ch/">Hackerspace Chaos Computer Club Zürich (third floor)</a>, Neue Hard 12, 8005, Zürich, Switzerland  </li>
		   <li>The I Love Free Software Day 2025 Zürich event is aimed at people who are interested in free software and who want to advocate for the ideals of free software. More information is available on our <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Events/Zurich/2025-01-16">webpage</a>.</li>
		  </ul>		
	</li>
	
  <h2 id="UK">🇬🇧 UK</h2>
      <li>FSFE <strong>Potteries</strong>, Staffordshire
		<ul class="ilovefs-ul">
		<li>⏰ 11.02.2025, 18:30 (GMT)</li>
		<li>📍 Upstairs at <a 
		href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Potteries/KPA%20Clubhouse">KPA 
		Clubhouse, 97 Horwood Road, Keele University, Keele, 
		Staffordshire</a></li>
		<li> More information is available on the <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Potteries/Calendar">local group's calendar</a></li>
		</ul>
	</li>

<h2 id="get-active">❤ Get active ❤</h2>
  
	<p>
	If you want to organise an event in your local area feel free to take a 
	look at our toolkit <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/campaigns/ilovefs/toolkit/">toolkit</a> for local groups. In this kit you find resources 
	for organising your own I Love Free Software Day event. reach 
	out to us via <a 
	href="/about/contact">email</a>. For "I Love Free Software 
	Day 2025" we want to organise events dedicated for Free Software 
	projects that are a part of our core infrastructure.
	</p>
	<ul class="ilovefs-ul">
		<li>
		Contact your local library and organise a talk about Free Software and the four freedoms
		</li>
		<li>
		Contact your <a 
		href="https://wiki.hackerspaces.org/List_of_Hacker_Spaces">local 
		hackerspace</a> and organise a Free Software meet-up with them
		</li>
		<li>
		Contact local Free Software companies and organise an event with them
		</li>
		<li>
		Reach out to your <a 
		href="/about/groups.html">local Free Software group</a>, local Linux 
	User Group or digital rights groups and organise 
		an event together!
		</li>
	</ul>
		
		
		<div class="icon-grid">
			<ul>
				<li>
					<img src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-use.png" 
						alt="ILoveFS heart with “use”"
					/>
					<div>
						<h3>Say thanks</h3>
						<p>Think about a Free Software project that you are grateful for and that deserves more attention. Reach out to them on the 14th of February to 
						say thank you. Organise a local group meeting or spread the word 
						about Free 
						Software. You can use our <a 
						href="https://sharepic.fsfe.org/#ilovefs">sharepics</a>, <a 
						href="/contribute/spreadtheword#ilovefs">stickers and 
						balloons</a>, or <a 
						href="/activities/ilovefs/artwork/artwork.html">artwork</a>, and <a 
						href="/order/order.html">
						merchandise</a> for <em>#ilovefs</em>.</p>
					</div>
				</li>
				<li>
					<img src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-study.png" 
						alt="ILoveFS heart with 'study'"
					/>
					<div>
						<h3>Remember the good times</h3>
						<p>Which Free Software project did you use in the past year? What 
						felt empowering? What was fun? For some inspiration have a look at 
						others’ <a 
						href="/activities/ilovefs/whylovefs/gallery.html">love 
						statements</a> and <a 
						href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/p/u3Ep8hRP5vFdbgUE9LKScW">videos</a>.</p>
					</div>
				</li>
				<li>
					<img 
						src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-share.png" 
						alt="ILoveFS heart with 'share'"
					/>
					<div>
						<h3>Share your love</h3>
						<p>That’s the fun part! We have created a <a 
						href="https://sharepic.fsfe.org/#ilovefs">sharepic generator</a>, 
						with which you can easily create your very own sharepics and share 
						your appreciation on social media (<em>#ilovefs</em>), in blog 
						posts, pictures and <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/p/u3Ep8hRP5vFdbgUE9LKScW">video 
						messages</a>, or <a href="/contribute/spreadtheword.html#ilovefs">directly to the Free 
						Software developers and contributors</a>.</p>
					</div>
				</li>
				<li>
					<img 
						src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-improve.png" 
						alt="ILoveFS heart with 'improve'"
					/>
					<div>
						<h3>Improve Free Software</h3>
						<p>Talking is silver, contributing is gold! Help a Free Software project with a donation, a translation or by assisting its users. If 
						you can, please consider supporting our work with a <a 
						href="/donate">donation to the Free Software Foundation 
						Europe</a>.</p>
					</div>
				</li>
			</ul>
		</div>

		<figure class="no-border">
			<img
				src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/53/44/afdfea246e5c2aec0d1d888da5da.jpg"
				alt="#ilovefs"
			/>
		</figure>

		<p>
		What is your contribution to this special day dedicated to the people 
		who enable you to use Free Software? Will you use our stickers and 
		balloons? Or make a picture or video with your new ILoveFS shirt? And 
		what about celebrating software freedom with your colleagues and 
		friends at a company gathering or public event? Whatever you do, show 
		it to the world by using the <em>#ilovefs</em> tag. And if you have 
		questions, <a href="/about/contact.html">just drop us an email</a>.
		</p>

		<p>Happy <strong><span class="text-danger">I Love Free Software</span></strong> Day everyone! ❤</p>
	</module>
</data>
