<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2024-05-06">
    <title>LLW 2024: A forum for difficult legal topics of Free Software in Gothenburg</title>
    <body>
      <p>
For the second year in a row, the Swedish city of Gothenburg hosted an 
edition of the Free Software Legal &amp; Licensing Workshop (LLW), the 
annual conference for Legal Network members. The 2024 edition brought 
new faces and great discussions and presentations on current legal and 
licensing issues related to technological developments such as AI. 

</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>LLW 2024: A forum for difficult legal topics of Free Software in Gothenburg</h1>

<p>
For the second year in a row, the Swedish city of Gothenburg hosted an 
edition of the Free Software Legal &amp; Licensing Workshop (LLW), the 
annual conference for Legal Network members. The 2024 edition brought 
new faces and great discussions and presentations on current legal and 
licensing issues related to technological developments such as AI. 

</p>

<figure>
	<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/43/6d/c08bc290b3231bf066e89e3fcc43.jpg" alt="Image from LLW 2024 showing the registration table with the logos of 2024 LLW sponsors"/>
</figure>

<p>
Under a sunny and blue sky, the beautiful Swedish city of Gothenburg 
once again hosted <a href="/activities/ln/llw.html">FSFE’s Free Software 
Legal &amp; Licensing Workshop (LLW)</a>, a two and a half day 
conference for members of the Legal Network community to meet 
face-to-face and share legal expertise in a safe space. It was great to 
have attendees engaging with the speakers in interesting legal 
discussions, as well as to see them use the venue to engage in impromptu 
discussions on legal theory, policy, and case law related to Free 
Software topics. This shows how valuable this conference has become for 
Free Software legal professionals, who arrived from Europe, the 
Americas, and Asia, and the importance of a healthy community to 
encourage discussion of the most current Free Software legal topics and 
to network in order to build a culture of knowledge exchange in the 
legal sector.
</p>

<p>
Discussion, even controversial, can help legal experts to make better 
decisions while  accomplishing the mission of empowering users to 
control technology. Good examples are Artificial Intelligence and 
Machine Learning, that continued to be hot topics during this year’s 
edition, with a number of discussions on the conference agenda touching 
on the legal ramifications of AI developments on software and licensing.
</p>
 
<p>
Nevertheless, there were many other developments from the past year for 
attendees to discuss as well, from new legislative initiatives and case 
law in various jurisdictions within and outside the European Union, to 
presentations to introduce various community-initiated compliance tools, 
to conversations about more philosophical ideas regarding Free Software 
and community.
</p>

<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
"I have been working for 2 years in this field now. In the past 2 days I 
learnt more on those topics than in the 2 years before", said one 
participant in LLW 2024
</blockquote>
<p/>

<p>
This conference also gives newcomers who may be a little shy about 
participating in discussions on the mailing list a chance to introduce 
themselves and meet various more established members of the community in 
person. The FSFE believes in the importance of supporting young 
professionals, which is why this conference also offers a mentoring 
programme, so that experienced members can help integrate newcomers into 
the Free Software legal community, as well as to help them build 
professional connections and expertise.
</p>

<p>
We appreciate all Legal Network members who took the time to participate 
in person and hope to see them again next year. It is extremely 
heartening for us to see the Free Software legal community grow in 
strength and knowledge with regular meetings like the LLW.
</p> 

<p>
We want to thank our sponsors: Intel, Red Hat, Microsoft, Amazon, Bosch, 
Ericsson, Siemens, Volvo, Bird &amp; Bird, Google, the law firm Heuking, 
and the Open Invention Network.
</p>

<h3>The Legal Network</h3>
<p>
<a href="/activities/ln/index.html">The Legal Network</a> is a neutral, 
non-partisan group of experts in different fields involved in Free 
Software legal issues. Currently the Legal Network has over 400 
participants from different legal systems, academic backgrounds and 
affiliations.
</p>

<p>
The aim of the Legal Network is to promote discussion and foster better 
knowledge of the legal constructs that back Free Software. The 
conversations on the Legal Network are intended to be dynamic, 
thought-provoking, and up to speed with the most recent developments.
</p> 

<p>
The Legal Network is a safe space to promote legal knowledge about Free 
Software so that companies can make strategic decisions about Free 
Software development based on an understanding of how Free Software 
licensing and other related legal issues work. This allows Free Software 
developers and legal professionals who work within larger companies to 
continue to contribute to software freedom.
</p>

<p>
<a href="/activities/ln/application.html">Admission to the Legal 
Network</a> is restricted, and the discussions held there are 
confidential. Nevertheless, this does not mean that the content of the 
mailing list is contained away from the larger Free Software community. 
The <a href="https://www.chathamhouse.org/about-us/chatham-house-rule">Chatham 
House Rule</a> applies to all discussions on the Legal Network mailing 
list and at Legal Network events, which enables members to use the 
information received, but not to reveal the identity nor the affiliation 
of the speaker or any of the participants involved in the discussion.
</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/43/6d/c08bc290b3231bf066e89e3fcc43.jpg" alt="Image from LLW 2024 showing the registration table with the logos of 2024 LLW sponsors"/>
    <link>/news/2024/news-20240506-01.html</link>
    <tags>
	<tag key="front-page"/>
	<tag key="legal">Legal</tag>
	<tag key="llw">Legal Licensing Workshop</tag>
	<tag key="licensing">Licensing</tag>
	<tag key="se">Sweden</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1153"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
