<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2024-06-27">
    <title>Defending DMA against Apple: The FSFE signs joint position paper</title>
    <body>
      <p>Together with nine stakeholders organisations, the FSFE has 
submitted a joint position paper to the European Commission, with whom 
we are working on the implementation of the Digital Markets Act. This 
paper, supported by legal and data-backed arguments, addresses Apple’s 
non-compliance with the law, particularly concerning software freedom, 
alternative Free Software app stores and interoperability 
obligations.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>
  
<h1>Defending DMA against Apple: The FSFE signs joint position paper</h1>

<p>Together with nine stakeholders organisations, the FSFE has 
submitted a joint position paper to the European Commission, with whom 
we are working on the implementation of the Digital Markets Act. This 
paper, supported by legal and data-backed arguments, addresses Apple’s 
non-compliance with the law, particularly concerning software freedom, 
alternative Free Software app stores and interoperability 
obligations.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/ee/3d/407431339a047caf4fc5f1ea05db.png" alt="Illustration showing what looks like a snake in the shape of an apple in black with a red shadow"/>
  <figcaption>
  CC-BY-SA 4.0. by <a href="https://rahak.net/work.html">Rahak</a> for 
  FSFE. Limitations to Free Software, vendor 
  lock-in, and lack of control over personal data are current hurdles 
  faced by end-users in digital markets
  </figcaption>

 </figure>
  
  
<p> The Digital Markets Act (DMA) regulates large tech companies in the 
EU, setting the main rules for designating gatekeepers and enforcing 
their obligations. As a designated “gatekeeper”, Apple was required to 
present a strategy for complying with the DMA. Since March 2024, the 
European Commission (EC) has been investigating it for 
<a href="https://digital-markets-act.ec.europa.eu/latest-news_en">non-compliance</a>.</p>
 
<p>Following a series of interventions, in order to assist the DMA 
enforcement procedure, <a href="https://edri.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/Joint-submission-on-Apple-DMA-non-compliance.pdf">the 
FSFE signed a joint position</a> to the EC, 
highlighting the main problematic aspects of Apple in relation to Free 
Software.</p>

<p>As far as the FSFE is concerned, the main points relate to:</p> 

<ul> 
<li><strong>Software freedom</strong>: By blocking side-loading of apps and the 
unfettered installation of alternative app stores, Apple is violating 
Art.6(4). Concretely, paragraph 4 obliges the gatekeeper to provide 
users with the possibility to easily install apps from other sources 
than the gatekeeper’s own software application store. Recital (41) 
clarifies that the gatekeeper is prohibited from undermining or 
restricting that possibility in any way.</li>

<li><strong>Vendor lock-in vs interoperability</strong>: By hampering effective 
interoperability with of hardware functions, the company is violating 
Art. 6(7). Apple has introduced an opaque and non-accountable system to 
grant interoperability that impedes Free Software projects to 
effectively access hardware and software functions of devices. The DMA 
prescribes the opposite: interoperability should be granted free of 
charge and effectively, so third parties can enjoy the same privileged 
access to hardware and software as the gatekeepers.</li> 

</ul>

<p> The FSFE welcomes the EC’s efforts <a href="https://digital-markets-act.ec.europa.eu/commission-sends-preliminary-findings-apple-and-opens-additional-non-compliance-investigation-2024-06-24_en">in 
finding Apple to be in breach 
of the law</a>. However, this is only the first step in a regulatory 
process aimed at reducing the company’s monopolistic control over 
devices. </p>

<h3>Apple threatens Free Software – please help protecting software freedom!</h3> 

<p>The DMA includes several provisions <a href="/activities/dma/dma.html">directly impacting Free 
Software</a>. It mandates “gatekeepers” to allow installing of software 
(sideloading), to enable alternative app stores and repositories to be 
used in devices, and several interoperability obligations, allowing 
third party developers to access the same hardware functions as the 
gatekeepers.</p> 

<p>Apple’s unfair behaviour against Free Software highlights the 
critical need to monitor the implementation of the DMA. The FSFE 
collaborated with F-Droid, the AppFair project, and other 
interoperability experts to scrutinize Apple’s DMA compliance, and it’s 
impact on Free Software. Since then, we coordinated several expert 
workshops with stakeholders, <a href="/news/2024/news-20240318-02.html">discussed with regulators in 
FOSDEM</a>, had 
<a href="/news/nl/nl-202406.html#interoperability-apple">official 
meetings with the EC’s DMA team</a>, and submitted a <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/device-neutrality/202404-FSFE-apple-report-EC.pdf">comprehensive 
position to the EC</a> detailing several problematic elements in the Apple 
compliance that will harm the Free Software.</p> 

<p>Free Software is key for a democratic society and we should not 
allow gatekeepers to threaten our rights and freedoms. Apple has a huge 
revenue from blocking Free Software on iOS, and has dedicated a lot of 
resources to interpret the DMA as it deems fit. For instance, <a href="https://webcast.ec.europa.eu/compliance-with-the-dma-apple-2024-03-18">Apple 
publicly stated that <strong>iPhones and iPads are not general purpose 
computers</strong></a>, and users are not allowed to run the software they want.</p>

<blockquote><em>Holding companies like Apple accountable under 
the DMA is a complicated, time-consuming and resource-intensive 
activity. It can even be a dangerous one as the risk of retaliation is 
real. We face it with courage and determination. If you are not yet an 
FSFE supporter, <a href="https://my.fsfe.org/donate?amount=300&amp;period=m">please 
join our cause today</a>.</em></blockquote>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/small/35/37/6f6d8017ffdd470670108a7743a4.png" alt="Poster about Device Neutrality showing a bird scaping from a cage with a black background"/>
  </figure> 

<p>Defending Free Software against large corporations takes a long 
time, maybe more than a decade.Our long-term commitment includes 
engaging with Free Software communities across Europe, conducting 
research and analysis for legal and policy positions, participating in 
official hearings, and we are getting prepared to be involved in 
strategic litigation.</p> 

<p>
Inflation is hitting everyone, especially 
organizations like ours that rely on individual donations. Your regular 
support is vital to help us continue standing up to those who seek to 
circumvent the law and undermine our freedoms.</p>

<div class="color-box background fullwidth" data-color="dark-green">
 <a class="btn btn-lg btn-default" href="https://my.fsfe.org/donate?amount=300&amp;period=m">Donate now</a>
</div>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/ee/3d/407431339a047caf4fc5f1ea05db.png" alt="Ilustration showing what looks like a snake in the shape of an apple in black with a red shadow"/>
    <link>/news/2024/news-20240627-01.html</link>
    <tags>
 <tag key="front-page"/>
 <tag key="highlights">highlights</tag>
 <tag key="news">News</tag>
  <tag key="deviceneutrality">Device Neutrality</tag>
   <tag key="european-commission">European Commission</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1174"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
