<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<dl>
<dt>1 September 2001</dt>
<dd>
 <i>EU, European Patent Office</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/dipl_conf/pdf/em00003a.pdf">Link</a><br />

The Revision Act shall be open for signature until the first day of
September two thousand and one at the European Patent Office.
</dd>

<dt>24 April 2001</dt>
<dd>
  <i>DE, Citizens</i><br />

<a href="http://softwarepatente.net/index_e.html">Link</a><br />
Symposium
Softwarepatents: slowing down or accelerating the economy?
</dd>

<dt>25 March 2001</dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/pr/pr10.html">Link</a><br />

Christian Pierret - State Secretary of Industry<br />

I am against software patents in Europe. It would kill innovation and promote juridical terrorism because multinational software publishers would multiply legal disputes against start-ups

</dd>

<dt>15 December 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Patent Office</i><br />

<a href="http://www.europa.eu.int/comm/internal_market/en/intprop/indprop/softpaten.htm">Link</a><br />
Software patents - Commission closes consultations

</dd>

<dt>15 December 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, Citizens</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/consultation/ec-consult.html">Link</a><br />

More than 1100 mails were sent by European citizens.

</dd>

<dt>15 December 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, Citizens</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/consultation/ec-consult.html">Link</a><br />

This document constitutes the official EuroLinux response to
the consultation on the harmonization of software patent Law launched
by the European Commission.
</dd>

<dt>11 December 2000</dt>
<dd><i>ES, Citizens</i><br />

<a href="http://www.dit.upm.es/~joaquin/report_en.pdf">Link</a><br />

Joaquin Seoane (proffesor of the Universidad Politécnica de Madrid)
and Ram'on Garc'ia Fern'andez report on software patents for the
public consultation on the harmonization of software patent Law launched
by the European Commission.

</dd>

<dt>5 December 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Patent Office</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/dipl_conf/documents.htm">Link</a> <br />
The Diplomatic Conference to revise the European Patent Convention
publishes texts adopted by the Diplomatic Conference.
<p />
<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/dipl_conf/pdf/em00003a.pdf">
ACT REVISING THE CONVENTION ON THE GRANT OF EUROPEAN PATENTS</a>
<br />
<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/dipl_conf/pdf/em00022.pdf">
CONFERENCE RESOLUTION</a>
<br />
<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/dipl_conf/pdf/xm00004a.pdf">
FINAL ACT OF THE CONFERENCE</a>
<br />

</dd>

<dt>29 November 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Patent Office</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/dipl_conf/pdf/xm00004a.pdf">
Link</a><br />
<pre>
FINAL ACT
OF THE CONFERENCE OF THE CONTRACTING STATES
TO REVISE THE EUROPEAN PATENT CONVENTION
THE DIPLOMATIC CONFERENCE,

Assembled to revise the Convention on the twenty­ninth day of November
two thousand, has drawn up and adopted the text

­ of the Act revising the European Patent Convention (Revision Act)
­ of a Diplomatic Conference Resolution.

The Revision Act shall be open for signature until the first day of
September two thousand and one at the European Patent Office.
</pre>

</dd>

<dt>20 November 2000 </dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Patent Office</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/dipl_conf/overview.htm">Link</a><br />
Diplomatic Conference to revise the European Patent Convention

</dd>

<dt>2 November 2000</dt>
<dd><i>DE, Government - Citizens</i><br />

<a href="http://swpat.ffii.org/vreji/papri/patpruef/">Link</a><br />

This article is to clarify some of the problems and inconsistencies,
with which the author as a former software developer and current
patent examiner at the German Patent Office is confronted when
examining computer program related patent applications.

</dd>

<dt>27 October 2000</dt>
<dd><i>DE, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://www.spiegel.de/druckversion/0,1588,100120,00.html">Link</a><br />
German Ministry of Justice demands that the computer program exception
not be removed at the coming conference and threatens to opt out of
the EPC otherwise

</dd>

<dt>19 October 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Commission</i><br />

<a href="http://europa.eu.int/comm/internal_market/en/intprop/indprop/softpaten.htm">Link</a><br />

Software patents - Commission launches consultations<br />

The European Commission announced the opening of an official
consultation on the economic and social impact of software patents in
Europe. In order to help European Authorities to conduct an open
consultation, the EuroLinux Alliance of software publishers and non
profit organisations debuts a public forum and a rich knowledge base.
</dd>

<dt>11 October 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Patent Organisation</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/legal/epc/e/ma2.html">Link</a><br />
IMPLEMENTING REGULATIONS TO THE CONVENTION ON THE GRANT OF EUROPEAN PATENTS
of 5 October 1973

as last amended by Decision of the Administrative Council of the European Patent Organisation

of 11 October 2000
</dd>

<dt>14 September 2000</dt>
<dd><i>DE, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/statements/view_html?key=968937455.986">Link</a><br />

Justus Kampp (Germany)

</dd>

<dt>7 September 2000</dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/statements/view_html?key=967730717.369">Link</a><br />
Gilles Savary - Député Européen (France) <br />

Je pense que nous devons distinguer les concepts de droits d'auteur
des concepts de brevetabilité. Les droits d'auteur peuvent à la limite
se concevoir, car ils sont la rémunératon d'une création et de sa
diffusion; la brevetabilité est au contraire l'appropriation privée
d'une diffusion qui est une diffusion extrêmement encadrée et donc
privative pour le plus grand nombre.
</dd>

<dt>September 2000</dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://www.pro-innovation.org/rapport_brevet/brevets_plan-en.pdf">Link</a><br />
Study by an official French organisation (Conseil Général des Mines)
<p />

The purpose was to determine how to ensure that intellectual property
rights could continue, in the new dimate of information society, to 
meet their twofold objective : encouraging inovation and guaranteeing
the sharing of knowledge.
<p />
Portions of this study were used by french government officials during
European Commission meetings. For some they did not use the parts of
the document that contained the most striking arguments against 
software patents.

</dd>

<dt>11 August 2000</dt>
<dd><i>DE , Citizens</i><br />

<a href="http://swpat.ffii.org/img/flags/de.png">Link</a><br />
The Federation for a Free Information Infrastructure (FFII)
sends an open letter to the German Federal Ministery of Justice.

</dd>

<dt>2 August 2000</dt>
<dd><i>DE, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://swpat.ffii.org/news/epue28/indexen.html">Link</a><br />
Jörg Tauss - chairman of the German Parliamentary Commission on the New Media
<p />
 In the circles of technological policy experts, you can often here people asserting that the patent system must be extended to certain areas of information technology, whose investments would otherwise not be sufficiently protected. This assertion has however until now always been touted like a self-evident truth, and nobody I know of ever cared to substantiate it in the light of facts from the German or European IT economy.
<p />
Even if the patent advocates succeeded in finding areas of information technology, in which patents are having or have had some positive effects, it would nonetheless still be necessary to investigate, whether these effects are not outweighed by possible detrimental side-effects of the patent system.
<p />
But while the legislative authorities are still completely clueless on this matter, the judicial authorities are already taking action, granting thousands of software patents and pressing for a change of the legal rules. We as legislators should therefore now take up these questions with highest priority.
</dd>

<dt>10 July 2000 </dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://www.culture.gouv.fr/culture/actualites/conferen/propriete-int.htm">Link</a><br />
Catherine Tasca - Ministre de la culture et de la communication
<p />
In a speach during the Conférence internationale sur " la gestion et
l'utilisation légitime de la propriété intellectuelle ", Catherine Tasca
speaks against software patents.

</dd>

<dt>10 July 2000</dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government </i><br />

<a href="http://www.osslaw.org/lettre_brevets.html">Link</a><br />
Jean-Yves LE DÉAUT - Député de Meurthe-et-Moselle
<p />
Jean-Yves LE DÉAUT sends a letter to the government against Software
Patents.
</dd>

<dt>Summer 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Commission</i><br />

A directive was introduced by the European Commission (Directorate for
Internal Market headed by Commissioner Bolkenstein and managed by John
Mogg, one of the most prominent supporter of software patents at the
European Commission). 

</dd>

<dt>24 June 2000</dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/statements/view_html?key=967728526.722">Link</a><br />
René TRÉGOUËT - Sénateur du Rhône
<p />
Speaks against software patents.
</dd>

<dt>15 June 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, Citizens</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/pr/pr1.html">Link</a><br />
The Eurolinux Alliance of European software companies and Open Source
associations launches a pan-European petition to keep Europe free from
software patents.
</dd>

<dt>18 May 2000</dt>
<dd><i>DE, Citizens</i><br />

<a href="http://swpat.ffii.org/penmi/bmwi-20000518/indexen.html">Link</a><br />
About 40 representatives of german software companies, government departments, patent offices, universities and associations met today at the German Federal Ministry of Economy in Berlin in order to discuss the effects of software patents on the economy and on the information society.
</dd>

<dt>24 Februrary 2000</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Patent Office</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/ca/e/24_02_00_e.htm">Link</a> <br />

A conference of the contracting states shall be convened to revise the
European Patent Convention. The conference shall be held from 20 to 29
November 2000 at the seat of the European Patent Organisation in
Munich.
</dd>

<dt>1 December 1999</dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/statements/view_html?key=967730901.176">Link</a><br />
Marylise Lebranchu - ecrétaire d'Etat aux petites et moyennes entreprises, au commerce et à l'artisanat
<p />
Explains the not so clear to understand position of the french government.

</dd>

<dt>1 December 1999</dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government </i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/statements/view_html?key=967730827.086">Link</a><br />
Yves Cochet - Député
<p />
Sends a question to the french government asking what position it
will hold regarding software patents.
</dd>

<dt>November 1999</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Commission</i><br />

<a href="http://europa.eu.int/comm/internal_market/en/intprop/indprop/utility.htm">Link</a><br />
Amended proposal for a Directive on the protection of inventions by
utility model.
<p />
This directive on utility models (i.e. short time patents) does not
include any exception for computer programmes, thus allowing them. It
has not been voted yet.

</dd>

<dt>18 November 1999</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Committe of Regions</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/statements/view_html?key=967731125.396">Link</a><br />
222 members of the European Committe of Region
<p />
Speak against software patents.

</dd>

<dt>24 June 1999</dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://www.freepatents.org/law/summary24.html">Link</a><br />
Conférence intergouvernementale (France)
<p />
On June 24 and 25 1999 in Paris, France, the European member states of
the Munchen convention met and discussed the software patent
issue. They have decided to wait for one more year before taking any
final decision regarding article 52.2, which says that computer
programmes as such are not patentable. And French State Secretary
Christian Pierret has stressed the necessity to study the economic
impact of software patents on the software industry.
</dd>

<dt>8 July 1999</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Patent Office</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/pubs/oj99/8_99/8_5729.pdf">Link</a><br />
Notice of the President of the European Patent Office dated 8 July 1999 concerning the
closing of the European Patent Office on 3 and 4 January 2000

</dd>

<dt>1 July 1999</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Patent Office</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/pubs/oj99/8_99/8_5739.pdf">Link</a><br />
Notice concerning the amendment of the Implementing
Regulations to the European Patent Convention

</dd>

<dt>18 Mars 1999</dt>
<dd><i>FR, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://petition.eurolinux.org/statements/view_html?key=968515758.659">Link</a><br />
Pierre Laffitte - Sénateur
<p />
 Pérennité des données administratives et libre accès des citoyens
impliquent que les normes de communication utilisées par
l'administration ne fassent pas l'objet de brevet et que pour l'accès
à ces normes elles ne fassent ni l'objet de droit d'auteur, c'est à
dire que les logiciels correspondants soient libres.
</dd>

<dt>12 February 1999</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Commission</i><br />

<a href="http://europa.eu.int/comm/internal_market/en/intprop/indprop/99.htm">Link</a><br />
Patents: Commission outlines ambitious series of measures
<p />
In this document, the European Commission confirms that there will be
software patents. We also recommend the original French version which
includes a sentence explaining that "software patents had a great
effect on innovation" and that Microsoft is a good example of software
patent holder.
</dd>

<dt>December 1997</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Commission</i><br />

<a href="http://europa.eu.int/comm/internal_market/en/intprop/indprop/1127.htm">Link</a><br />
Commission presents a proposal for a Directive on the protection of
technical inventions (utility models)
<p />
This directive on utility models (i.e. short time patents) does not
include any exception for computer programmes, thus allowing them. It
has not been voted yet.

</dd>

<dt>25 June 1997</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Commission</i><br />

<a href="http://europa.eu.int/comm/internal_market/en/intprop/indprop/558.htm">Link</a><br />
Patents - Commission approves Green Paper
<p />
This is the document which started it all. It was released in 1997.
</dd>

<dt>1996</dt>
<dd><i>US, Government</i><br />

<a href="http://www.iitf.doc.gov/eleccomm/ecomm.htm">Link</a><br />
A Framework For Global Electronic Commerce
<p />
In this article (1996), Al Gore explains that all countries in the
World should adopt the US patent law in order to benefit from the
growth of electronic commerce.
</dd>

<dt>17 December 1991</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Commission</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/legal/epc/e/ma1.html">Link</a><br />
<pre>
CONVENTION ON THE GRANT OF EUROPEAN PATENTS (EUROPEAN PATENT CONVENTION)

of 5 October 1973

text as amended by the act revising Article 63 EPC of 17 December 1991

and by decisions of the Administrative Council of the European Patent
Organisation of 21 December 1978, 13 December 1994, 20 October 1995, 5
December 1996 and 10 December 1998
</pre>
</dd>

<dt>5 October 1973</dt>
<dd><i>EU, European Commission</i><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/legal/epc/e/ma3.html">
EPC - PROTOCOL ON THE CENTRALISATION OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT SYSTEM AND ON ITS INTRODUCTION (PROTOCOL ON CENTRALISATION)</a><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/legal/epc/e/ma4.html">
EPC - PROTOCOL ON JURISDICTION AND THE RECOGNITION OF DECISIONS IN RESPECT OF THE RIGHT TO THE GRANT OF A EUROPEAN PATENT (PROTOCOL ON RECOGNITION)</a><br />

<a href="http://www.european-patent-office.org/legal/epc/e/ma5.html">
EPC - PROTOCOL ON PRIVILEGES AND IMMUNITIES OF THE EUROPEAN PATENT ORGANISATION (PROTOCOL ON PRIVILEGES AND IMMUNITIES)</a><br />

</dd>
</dl>
