<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-12-05">
    <title>5 reasons why your contribution 
is crucial for the promotion of Free Software</title>
    <body>
      <p>
	Your support and contribution for the promotion of Free Software are important for securing our continuous work, ensuring our independence, strengthening our democratic society, promoting and implementing concrete steps towards software freedom, and making it easier to use and develop Free Software. 
	 </p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>
	<h1>5 reasons why your contribution 
is crucial for the promotion of Free Software</h1>

	 <p>
	Your support and contribution for the promotion of Free Software are important for securing our continuous work, ensuring our independence, strengthening our democratic society, promoting and implementing concrete steps towards software freedom, and making it easier to use and develop Free Software. 
	 </p>
	 
  <figure>
	  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/2a/d7/3bd3e511fa6e9b6e1c3a8affa57d.jpg" alt="FSFE booth at one event"/> 
  </figure>

<h2>1. Your engagement is what keeps us going</h2>	
	<p>
	 The backbone of the Free Software Foundation Europe's work is an active 
	 network of Free Software advocates and volunteers who contribute to the 
	 promotion and spreading of the benefits of Free Software within Europe.
  </p>
        <p>
        Your contribution and commitment allow us to continue running our 
        campaigns, lending a hand to our team during our events and helping 
        setting up a booth. These actions all over Europe are creating a 
        stable and strong Free Software movement. Our small actions are really 
        contributing to changing the world!
        </p>
        <p>
        Want to join us but not sure where to start? We are convinced that 
        you will find a way to help us that fits your interests and skills. For 
        example, you can join our community and be an active member of a local 
        group, you can show your affiliation and love for Free Software by 
        wearing our clothes, or you can spread the word at different events
        related to Free Software and give away stickers and leaflets.
        </p>
       <p>
        You can help us by proofreading and translating our messages and 
        documents into the different European languages, helping to improve our 
        website. Or stand up for Free Software in your community, in your 
        regional administration, or in your country. <a href="/contribute/contribute.html">And there's even more you can do!</a>
       </p>

	
	<h2>2. Your support ensures our independence</h2> 
	
	<p>
	The Free Software Foundation Europe is a non-profit organisation. We 
	depend on the financial contributions of individuals who, like you, put 
	their trust in us and support our work. Indeed, over one third of our 
	budget comes from individual donors.
        </p>
        <p>
        This allows us to be independent of governments and companies and only 
        follow what is best for software freedom.
        </p>
        <p>
        Achieving our <a href="https://my.fsfe.org/donate?referrer=/fsfe.org/index.html">fundraising goal</a> of 212.000 € by 12 February 2023 will 
        put us in position to continue our long term approach. This is crucial 
        to abolishing barriers to <a href="/freesoftware/freesoftware.html">Free Software</a> adoption, for example by 
        establishing the right to install any software on any device.
	</p>
	<p>
	In our <a href="/about/transparency-commitment.html">transparency commitment</a>, you can find out more information about 
	the FSFE and where your donations are going.
	</p>
	
	<h2>3. You can contribute to empowering our society</h2>
	<p>
	Your support allow us to run diverse activities and campaigns that are 
	raising awareness about the benefits of Free Software. We promote Free 
	Software programming and tinkering among children and teenagers 
	regardless of their ability or disability, gender identity, sex, race, 
	religion, or sexual orientation. Thereby we provide new generations with 
	the skills to build a more democratic and transparent society, where 
	users have full control of their devices and technologies.
        </p>
        <p>
        Thanks to your contribution, we can provide resources to enable everyone 
        to further promote Free Software in Europe. We are able to attend 
        various conferences, organise activities and workshops, and create 
        content and material to spread the message.
	</p>
	<p>Learn more about our <a href="/activities/awareness.html">Public Awareness activities</a>.
	</p>
	
	<h2>4. You can help promote and implement Free Software</h2>
	<p>
	Our team includes policy experts who are working with policy makers 
	and public bodies in Europe, from local administrators to EU decision 
	makers. Our financial independence allows us to provide in-depth 
	analysis on different topics and issues, getting involved in political 
	processes or campaigning towards the implementation of Free Software, 
	and also to criticise decision makers if necessary.
	</p>
	<p>
	Your support allows us to create campaigns such as <a href="https://publiccode.eu/">‘Public Money, Public Code!’</a>,
	to advocate for the use of Free Software in public administrations, and to promote best practise examples.
	</p>
	
	<h2>5. You can chip in to make Free Software usage and development easier</h2>
	<p>
	We are continuously working to make difficult topics easier to 
	understand, such as usage of Free Software, as well as helping people 
	to run Free Software on their devices.
	</p>
	<p>
	Education is a key pillar in our work, from a “Legal Education Day” to 
	activities targeting the young generation, for instance with a 
	<a href="/activities/ada-zangemann/index.html">children’s book</a> 
	and the <a href="/activities/yh4f/index.html">Youth Hacking 4 Freedom</a> hacking competition. We 
	are also supporting Free Software developers through <a href="/activities/ngi/ngi.html">Next Generation 
	Internet Zero</a>, helping European projects with their technical, legal and 
	licensing needs.
	</p>
	<p>
	If you want to learn more about our activities and campaigns as well as 
	get a deeper understanding of our work during this past year, check our 
	yearly report <a href="/news/2022/news-20220928-01.html">Software Freedom 2022</a>. 
	</p>
	
</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/2a/d7/3bd3e511fa6e9b6e1c3a8affa57d.jpg" alt="FSFE booth at one event"/>
    <link>/news/2022/news-20221205-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
</tags>
    <discussion href="/community.fsfe.org/t/946"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
