<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-10-26">
    <title>If enforced, EU chat control will limit Free Software</title>
    <body>
      <p>
  Surely you have already heard about the controversial EU draft law on 
  mandatory chat control with the supposed aim to effectively tackle 
  child sexual abuse. This law implies the monitoring and scanning of 
  the communications of citizens – even the securely encrypted 
  end-to-end one.
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1 id="if-enforced-eu-chat-control-will-limit-free-software">If enforced, EU chat control will limit Free Software</h1>

<p>
  Surely you have already heard about the controversial EU draft law on 
  mandatory chat control with the supposed aim to effectively tackle 
  child sexual abuse. This law implies the monitoring and scanning of 
  the communications of citizens – even the securely encrypted 
  end-to-end one.
</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/7f/27/c7606f4af28c37eda77b591c8d02.jpg" alt="person watching through hole"/>
</figure>


<p>
  FSFE’s co-founder and programmer Bernhard E. Reiter explains why we 
  as Free Software supporters should join the protest against this 
  legislation that deprives citizens of the privacy of digital 
  correspondence.
</p>

<p>
  As a software developer, if I needed a method to transfer data to a 
  group of people, I would write an application to encode and decode 
  any information/ message I want to send over this channel. Then I 
  would distribute the app to my users, using it to communicate with 
  them, without anybody being able to see what we write along the 
  way.
</p>

<p>
  This is so-called end-to-end cryptography, and any software engineer 
  can write such an application.
</p>

<p>
  Free Software allows everyone to control, write and run their own 
  software. This means that they can tinker with their devices, they 
  can help each other and even earn money by establishing a business 
  based on this software. They are encouraged to use, understand, share 
  and improve it.
</p>

<p>
  By enforcing all service providers to “scan” chat or other messages, 
  the state must also take away the ability - and the right - for you 
  and me to write an own version of software that communicates via the 
  service providers. Otherwise a scan on the server would be 
  useless.
</p>

<p>
  The European Commission’s proposed regulation has not fully taken this 
  into account. It would hinder people to run their own Free Software 
  products on their phones (and other devices) and it would limit 
  innovative companies to provide new services based on Free Software 
  components with strong security and privacy-friendly technology.
</p>

<p>
  Furthermore, the intended regulation would raise the bar for entry 
  into a market which is dominated by a few large corporations. Those 
  providers of software and central service have lower costs per 
  message when installing scanning technology and can take this as an 
  excuse not to offer open standard programming interfaces and prevent 
  people from writing their own clients or not to offer a decentralised 
  service infrastructure which is open for fair competition.
</p>

<p>
  This will further burden those aiming to create software for users 
  that is inspectable by the public, as is the case with Free Software. 
  Additionally, the regulation will also fail to protect children as 
  intended for the same technical reasons outlined above.
</p>

<p>
  A number of groups and experts have explained <a href="https://edri.org/our-work/why-chat-control-is-so-dangerous/">other 
  negative effects of the proposed regulation</a>, and we are joining 
  them from a technical and ethical Free Software perspective: Please 
  join the protests against the proposed EU Chat control.
</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/7f/27/c7606f4af28c37eda77b591c8d02.jpg" alt="person watching through hole"/>
    <link>/news/2022/news-20221026-02.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="policy">European Public Policy</tag>
  <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
  <tag key="encryption">encryption</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/919"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
