<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-02-01">
    <title> ❤ Let's celebrate together the next I Love Free Software Day! </title>
    <body>
      <p> 
	Every 14th of February, people around the world celebrate the 
	“I Love Free Software Day”.  On this day we show our love for Free 
	Software and thank all the people contributing to software freedom. 
	This year, we are organising a whole event dedicated to Free 
	Software games.
	</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>
	<h1> ❤ Let's celebrate together the next I Love Free Software Day!</h1>
	
	<p> 
	Every 14th of February, people around the world celebrate the 
	“I Love Free Software Day”.  On this day we show our love for Free 
	Software and thank all the people contributing to software freedom. 
	This year, we are organising a whole event dedicated to Free 
	Software games.
	</p>
	
	
	<p>
	Although many of us depend on Free Software every day, 
	contributors to those projects usually remain invisible. This is 
	one of the main reasons that drive us to celebrate this day. We 
	want to highlight the valuable work of all the people who 
	contribute to software freedom, and take the time to say thank 
	you!</p> 
	
	<p>There are three different ways you can join us for this 
	celebration. Spoiler alert: all of them are a lot of fun!
	</p> 
	
	<h2 id="let-s-play-together-">Let's play together!</h2> 
	
	<figure class="max-width-85 no-border">
      <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/69395a3acc8cfb98fbb058d0b44a8f04.png" alt="Invitation Free Software Games Online Event: 14th February 18:00 - 20:00CET"/> 
    </figure>
 
	<p>
	For the <a href="/activities/ilovefs/">I Love Free Software Day 
	2022</a>, we have prepared something special and fun for you: an event 
	dedicated to Free Software games. The event takes place online on 
	14 February 2022 at 18:00-20:00 CET. For the first part of our 
	event, our three expert guests in Free Software games, game 
	engines, and Game Jams will share their experiences, and will 
	immerse us in the world of Free Software games. After this, we 
	invite you to play <a href="https://veloren.net/">Veloren</a> with 
	us.
	</p> 
	
	<p>
	For technical reasons, we are asking people who want to 
	take part in the whole event via our BigBlueButton instance to <a href="https://registration.fsfe.org/ilovefs">register</a> in 
	advance (registration is now closed). The number of participants in this instance is limited.
	But, do not worry if you do not want to register or if you are too 
	late to do so. The talks will be <a href="https://stream.fsfe.org">streamed online</a>, and you will be 
	able to watch them without registration.  You just won't be 
	able to join us for the second part of the event in which we will be 
	playing games together.
	</p>
	
	<h2 id="show-your-love-with-a-pic-">Show your love with a pic!</h2> 
	
	<p>
	You can also celebrate the I Love Free Software Day by sending a 
	thank you message to your favourite Free Software project for their 
	valuable work. You can do this, for example, on your preferred 
	social network with the hashtag #ilovefs. If you prefer images over 
	words, please use our brand new <a href="https://sharepic.fsfe.org/">Sharepic Generator</a> to create 
	your very own pictures. It is simple to use and you have a nice 
	graphic to share in two minutes. Let your imagination run free and 
	show your appreciation for Free Software with an #ilovefs image.
	</p>
	
	
	<figure class="max-width-85 no-border">
	    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/5a087946919a989183d1551878a00412.png" alt="Picture made with our sharepic generator"/> 
	</figure>
	
	<h2 id="listen-to-our-special-i-love-free-software-podcast-episode-">Listen to our special I Love Free Software podcast episode!</h2> 
	
	<p>
	Have you heard of 0 A.D: Empires Ascendant? Or even better, have 
	you played it? 
	</p> 
	
	<p>
	For our special podcast episode, Bonnie 
	Mehring - FSFE Junior Project Manager - and Stanislas Dolcini - 
	Project Lead of this well-known Free Software game - talk about the 
	development of the game, its history, the kind of support that is 
	needed, and the highlights of developing a Free Software game. You 
	can listen to the <a href="/news/podcast/episode-13.html">whole 
	episode</a>, and share it with your community. We bet you will want 
	to play 0 A.D after listing to this episode. 
	</p> 
	
	<p> 
	Join us on this special day in the way that you prefer.  Either 
	by learning more about Free Software games from our expert guests, 
	by having fun playing together with our community members, and/or 
	by sharing your love for Free Software. Remember that this is a 
	small gesture that means a lot. 
	</p>  
	
	<figure class="max-width-85 no-border">
      <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/f164c8517e78449fc8844a72347af490.png" alt="HashtagIloveFS"/> 
      <figcaption>
       Don't let this day pass without saying thank you!
      </figcaption>
   </figure>

    <p>
    Happy <strong><span class="text-danger">I Love Free Software</span></strong> Day everyone! ❤
    </p>
	
	    
</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/69395a3acc8cfb98fbb058d0b44a8f04.png" alt="Invitation Free Software Games Online Event: 14th February 18:00 - 20:00CET"/>
    <link>/news/2022/news-20220201-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="ilovefs">I Love Free Software</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href=" https://community.fsfe.org/t/796"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
