<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-05-04">
    <title>EU Declaration of Digital Rights: Free Software included by European Parliament</title>
    <body>
      <p>Early this year, the Commission proposed a draft for an EU 
 Declaration on Digital Rights and Principles that aims to guide the 
 digital transformation in the EU. Now the European Parliament has 
 agreed on a text and Free Software makes part of it.
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>


<h1>EU Declaration of Digital Rights: Free Software included by European Parliament</h1>

 <p>Early this year, the Commission proposed a draft for an EU 
 Declaration on Digital Rights and Principles that aims to guide the 
 digital transformation in the EU. Now the European Parliament has 
 agreed on a text and Free Software makes part of it.
</p> 

 <p><a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/library/declaration-european-digital-rights-and-principles">The 
 European Commission has presented its proposal</a> for the EU 
 Declaration on Digital Rights and Principles which will serve as 
 reference point in the future and as a common vision of our digital 
 rights in Europe. After receiving the contributions to the text from 
 different committees and finding a compromise, the European Parliament 
 has now agreed on a common text. The FSFE welcomes that the text by 
 the European Parliament now includes Free Software as a way to ensure 
 transparency in the use of algorithms and artificial intelligence. It 
 further highlights the importance of promoting "trustworthy 
 standards and, wherever possible, open source standards".</p> 
 
 <figure>
<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/e03669d329cb650b7e36a9a5ba70ae3b.jpg" alt="Building of the European Parliament in Brussels"/> 
 </figure>

 <blockquote><em>"The EU Declaration of Digital Rights and Principles 
 will be an important guideline to our fast pace digitalisation. 
 Therefore, we welcome the agreed text from the European Parliament for 
 acknowledging the role that Free Software has on trustworthy 
 technologies, specially with regard to AI. Now we expect the 
 ongoing-discussed AI regulation to be consistent with these 
 principles" says Lina Ceballos, FSFE Project Manager. 
 </em></blockquote>
 
<p> Furthermore, in Chapter VI of the agreed text named 
"Sustainability", there is the commitment to support the "development 
of sustainable by design digital technologies, that are durable, 
repairable, and interoperable, both on a hardware and a software level, 
and banning practices leading to premature obsolescence".
</p>

 <blockquote><em>"The European Parliament's call for the development of 
 sustainable technologies, that are durable, repairable, and 
 interoperable is in fact a call for the development of Free Software." 
 as Erik Albers, FSFE Digital Sustainability Programme Manager, 
 emphasizes. From here on we expect future legislations aligned to 
 these principles and making use of the crucial role that Free Software 
 plays for an eco-friendly design and the sustainability of our 
 hardware" </em></blockquote>
 
 <p>The FSFE has published an <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/openletter.html">open 
 letter</a> co-signed by meanwhile more than 45 organisations and 
 companies from the environmental, economic, and technological sectors. 
 In the letter, the broad alliance asks EU legislators for the right to 
 install any software on any device, including full access to hardware. 
 These rights support reusability and longevity of our devices.</p>
 
 <p>The FSFE keeps monitoring the ongoing inter-institutional dialogue 
 trying to make sure that the Parliament proposal remains. So that the 
 final text of Declaration of Digital Rights and Principles can become 
 a milestone for software freedom.</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/e03669d329cb650b7e36a9a5ba70ae3b.jpg" alt="Building of the European Parliament in Brussels"/>
    <link>/news/2022/news-20220504-01.html</link>
    <tags>
<tag key="front-page"/>
<tag key="pmpc">Public Money? Public Code!</tag>
<tag key="procurement">Public Procurement</tag>
<tag key="public-administration">Public Administration</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/843"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
