<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-09-28">
    <title>Software Freedom in Europe 2022</title>
    <body>
      <p>
  We continuously work to promote Free Software in Europe. In 2022 
  we addressed technological sustainability, advocated in the DMA and 
  AI act on European level, and defended Router Freedom in 
  Europe – among other activities. To reach younger 
  people, we organised a coding competition for 
  teenagers and published a children's book on software 
  freedom.
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1 id="software-freedom-in-europe-2021">Software Freedom in Europe 2022</h1>

<p>
  We continuously work to promote Free Software in Europe. In 2022 
  we addressed technological sustainability, advocated in the DMA and 
  AI act on European level, and defended Router Freedom in 
  Europe – among other activities. To reach younger 
  people, we organised a coding competition for 
  teenagers and published a children's book on software 
  freedom.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/d4/b6/e565f8b8ae949ded085d085cc3c7.png">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/d4/b6/e565f8b8ae949ded085d085cc3c7.png" alt="A photo of a booth, of a presentation, and of an audience with children"/>
  </a>
</figure>

<div id="introduction">
<p>
  “Software Freedom in Europe” is the yearly report of the Free 
  Software Foundation Europe (FSFE), your charity organisation which 
  empowers people to control technology. Every year we refine our 
  manifold activities to address the current needs of software freedom 
  in Europe. This yearly report covers the FSFE activities from 
  November 2021 to August 2022.
</p>
</div>

<p>
  Global digitization has increased in the pandemic times and 
  developments in the IT sector accelerated rapidly. The climate 
  consequences of such a rapid growth are significant. The longevity of 
  hardware and software is a central element of digital sustainability. 
  With this in mind, we launched the Upcycling Android campaign, 
  demonstrating that Free Software can help overcome software 
  obsolescence. Our open letter to the EU legislators, calling for the 
  right to install any software on any device, received over 100 
  signatures from tech companies and from digital rights and 
  environmental organisations.
</p>

<p>
  Meanwhile, new technologies reintroduce the question of ownership. 
  Artificial intelligence increasingly determines aspects of our 
  everyday life, from picking which content we see online to estimating 
  the length of hospital stays. How are the results generated? As a 
  society, we need to be able to track what input leads to each output 
  and to evaluate the results. Free Software can make AI systems more 
  transparent and trustworthy. The FSFE advocated in favor of Free 
  Software in the Artificial Intelligence Act, with clear results. A 
  European Parliament resolution on AI proclaims that public 
  procurement should require Free Software.
</p>

<p>
  Another critical challenge for our movement is that more and more 
  devices prohibit us from running Free Software on them. As these 
  restrictions often establish monopolistic practices, we were able to 
  give our input to policy makers who created the Digital Markets Act. 
  This was another win for software freedom: the Digital Markets Act 
  enhances interoperability and control over personal data, while 
  limiting monopolistic practices.
</p>

<p>
  We address country-specific cases too. We submitted a position and 
  formed a coalition to defend Router Freedom in Greece, and hosted a 
  debate about Router Freedom in Austria.
</p>

<p>
  We have always advocated for Free Software in public administrations, 
  to allow knowledge sharing and innovation. After all, software 
  created using taxpayers’ money should be released as Free Software. 
  We run electoral activities asking political parties their stance on 
  Free Software, and we share good practices from public entities which 
  already use Free Software. In 2022, we interviewed Free Software 
  developers in Sweden who created a digital school platform. The 
  'Public Money? Public Code!' brochure for public administrations was 
  translated into Spanish and Italian, steps that were marked with 
  dedicated events. We even created an application prototype to make 
  public procurement more transparent. The application made it to the 
  finals of the EU Datathon! 
</p>

<p>
  We acknowledge that developers have to deal with legal matters 
  regarding copyright, patents, and trademarks. The FSFE continued 
  providing legal support to Free Software projects, and published a 
  new version of REUSE.
</p>

<p>
  Looking into the future, it is clear that the software freedom 
  movement can only thrive if younger generations join. Therefore, the 
  FSFE introduced two new activities to appeal to the young people. We 
  organised a hacking competition explicitly for teenagers to spark 
  their interest and enthusiasm about technology and Free Software. 
  Also we published a children's book narrating the adventures of 
  developing Free Software.
</p>

<p>
  We are grateful for all the successes we have had throughout these 
  recent months, yet our real strength lies in our thriving community. 
  Our volunteer translators make our message accessible throughout 
  European language zones. Our local groups and country teams introduce 
  people to Free Software and run local activities across Europe. Our 
  newly formed Women's group empowers women and non-binary people to 
  network on the cause of software freedom. And last but not least we 
  started to be present again in person at events across Europe, 
  letting people know about the benefits of software freedom.
</p>

<p>
  We hope you enjoy reading our yearly report as much as we had the 
  pleasure of writing it.
</p>

<p>
  Your editor in representation of the whole team, Fani Partsafyllidou
</p>

<div class="toc">
  <p>Table of contents</p>
  <ol>
    <li><a href="#software-sustainability">Software <strong>sustainability</strong></a></li>
    <li><a href="#upcycling-android"><strong>Upcycling Android</strong></a></li>
    <li><a href="#pmpc">‘<strong>Public Money? Public Code!</strong>’</a></li>
    <li><a href="#artificial-intelligence"><strong>Artificial Intelligence</strong> and Free Software</a></li>
    <li><a href="#router-freedom"><strong>Router Freedom</strong>: Keeping your gateway to the Internet free</a></li>
    <li><a href="#device-neutrality"><strong>Device Neutrality</strong>: Regaining control over our devices</a></li>
    <li><a href="#legal-support"><strong>Legal support</strong> for Free Software programs</a></li>
    <li><a href="#reuse"><strong>REUSE</strong>: Making licensing easier</a></li>
    <li><a href="#yh4f"><strong>Youth Hacking 4 Freedom</strong>: A coding competition</a></li>
    <li><a href="#childrens-book"><strong>Children’s book</strong>: A tale of software, skateboards, and raspberry ice cream</a></li>
    <li><a href="#education">Free Software in <strong>Education</strong></a></li>
    <li><a href="#public-awareness">What is Free Software? - Our work on <strong>public awareness</strong></a></li>
    <li><a href="#fosdem">The <strong>FOSDEM</strong> 2022 conference</a></li>
    <li><a href="#association">The FSFE e.V. <strong>association</strong></a></li>
    <li><a href="#community">The FSFE <strong>community</strong> across Europe</a></li>
    <li><a href="#technical-infrastructure">Our fully Free Software <strong>technical infrastructure</strong></a></li>
    <li><a href="#movement">Join the <strong>movement</strong></a></li>
   </ol>
</div>

<h2 id="software-sustainability"><span id="anchor"/><span id="anchor-1"/>Software sustainability</h2>

<p>
  In recent years, the FSFE has shed light on Free Software as a 
  central aspect of technological sustainability. Software dictates how 
  long and in what ways we are able to use and reuse hardware. With 
  Free Software, users can replace software and operating systems in 
  order to reuse, repurpose, repair, or upcycle hardware. With 
  interoperable devices and open standards, technical infrastructures 
  can be adapted efficiently and according to local needs. Only with 
  free access to the source code of hardware, drivers, and tools can 
  the right to repair be fully exercised.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/2e/f9/c04c08968d6d889ebde30a93ada4.jpg">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/2e/f9/c04c08968d6d889ebde30a93ada4.jpg" alt="Person pointing to one out of four old phone devices demonstrated in a booth, two people listening."/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    State Secretary Rohleder visited the FSFE booth in the Open House 
    event of the German Federal Ministry of Environment. We 
    demonstrated old phones that can still operate securely with Free 
    Software. CC-BY-SA-4.0 BMUV/Christopher Wehrer. August 2022
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  Right now, the European Union is about to redefine the ecodesign of 
  products in the internal market. Our goal is to <a href="/news/2022/news-20220225-01.html">make sure that the dedicated 
  policies use Free Software to ensure a sustainable European 
  technological sector</a>. To this end in 2022 we provided several 
  policy recommendations:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>Telecommunications sector</strong>: The FSFE <a href="/news/2022/news-20220510-01.html">answered a public 
    consultation</a> about the impact of the telecommunications sector 
    on the environment. The right to install any software on any 
    device, Free Software licensing, and device neutrality serve 
    digital sustainability as well as being consumer protection 
    measures. We contextualized our experience with Router Freedom, 
    explaining that some regulatory approaches taken by policy makers 
    had negative impact on sustainability by limiting freedom of 
    terminal equipment and increasing e-waste.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Sustainable products</strong>: The FSFE <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/law/better-regulation/have-your-say/initiatives/12567-Sustainable-products-initiative/F3316008_en">submitted 
    feedback</a> to the European Commission about the Sustainable 
    Products Initiative, a proposal for a regulation that will revise 
    the Ecodesign Directive. Nowadays, most electronic devices, in 
    particular phones and tablets, can be reused and upgraded by 
    installing a Free Software operating system on them. In order to 
    establish the universal right to install any software on any device 
    we proposed several improvements to the text of the 
    Initiative.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Device Neutrality</strong>: We worked on the upcoming EU 
    legislation targeting redefining the current ecodesign criteria for 
    environmentally friendly products. In preparation, we <a href="/news/2021/news-20211015-01.html">provided an in-depth 
    study</a> on software sustainability and its interplay with device 
    neutrality. More on this concept in its own chapter.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Sustainable consumption:</strong> The FSFE <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/law/better-regulation/have-your-say/initiatives/13150-Sustainable-consumption-of-goods-promoting-repair-and-reuse/F3005275_en">participated 
    in the consultation</a> about the European Commission’s 
    ‘Sustainable consumption of goods’ initiative. Within our feedback 
    we highlighted that in order to extend the usage lifetime of 
    devices, two factors are key: the universal right to install any 
    software on any device and the publication of source code of 
    drivers, tools, and interfaces.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
  <strong>Collaboration</strong>: The FSFE decided to join the 
  organising committee of the upcoming <a href="/news/2022/news-20220905-01.html">Bits &amp; Bäume (‘Bits and 
  Trees’) conference</a>. We congratulated Okular, a Free Software 
  universal document reader that was awarded the Blue Angel ecolabel 
  for being <a href="/news/2022/news-20220316-01.html">an 
  energy-efficient PDF reader</a>.
</p>

<h2 id="upcycling-android"><span id="anchor"/><span id="anchor-2"/>Upcycling Android</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    “There are so many reasons to repurpose a device and to use open 
    technologies: right of ownership, learning, innovation, resource 
    conservation, environmental concerns, providing access to 
    technology, experimentation, system integration... pick 
    yours.”
  </p>
  <cite>
    Pedro Alcántara Martín from Tarsis, signee of the <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/openletter.html">open letter</a> 
    for the right to install any software on any device.
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  In November 2021, the FSFE launched the <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/">Upcycling Android 
  initiative</a>, highlighting phones as a poster-child of software 
  obsolescence and correspondingly unnecessary e-waste. The initiative 
  helps people to flash their phones with Free Software operating 
  systems and promotes the right for every user to install any software 
  on any device.
</p>

<p>
  The initiative offers workshops, develops policy recommendations, and 
  receives a lot of attention. Erik Albers tells <a href="/news/podcast/episode-15.html">the thrilling story of the 
  Upcycling Android campaign</a> in a podcast episode with Bonnie 
  Mehring.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Open letter</strong>: The EU is redefining their ecodesign 
  criteria in effect for environmentally friendly electronics. After 
  several months of internal discussion and external feedback, the FSFE 
  provided input to this process by publishing an <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/openletter.html">open letter about 
  “The right to install any software on any device”</a>. We published 
  the letter in April. Since then, more than <strong>100 entities have 
  signed</strong> the letter, including the Nature And Biodiversity 
  Conservation Union (NABU), EDRi – European Digital Rights, the 
  European Right to Repair Campaign, and Fairphone. It speaks volumes 
  that tech companies, right to repair initiatives, and environmental 
  organisations support the right to install any software on any 
  device. Volunteers translated the letter into <strong>9 
  languages</strong>: Catalan, German, Greek, Spanish, French, Italian, 
  Dutch, Portuguese, and Polish.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Video</strong>: Taking Android phones as example, <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/kGvs3JNADvvQfkC1dR9FGr">we created a 
  video</a> that explains in a nutshell the problem of software 
  obsolescence and relates to it increasing e-waste and resource 
  scarcity. The video continues with showing how Free Software can help 
  overcome artificial obsolescence and help save the climate at the 
  same time.
</p>

<figure>
  <peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/kGvs3JNADvvQfkC1dR9FGr"/>
  <figcaption>
    Watch the Upcycling Android video <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/kGvs3JNADvvQfkC1dR9FGr">with 
    subtitles</a> or <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/uPYZNNpB3ss7xT42474pGB">in 
    German</a> on our Peertube instance.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  <strong>Phones DIY</strong>: How can people get a Free Software 
  phone? To make things easier, we offered a <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Activities/Android/OtherInitiatives">community-led 
  wiki</a> page listing Free Software operating systems and phone 
  devices that come with Free Software operating systems pre-installed. 
  We <a href="/news/2022/news-20220323-01.html">introduced Plasma 
  Mobile</a>, including how it is developed and how to get it, by 
  interviewing Bhushan Shah, a Plasma Mobile developer. We presented 
  the <a href="/news/2022/news-20220712-01.html">software development 
  of the Librem 5 phone and of Phosh</a>, the popular graphical 
  environment for GNU/Linux phones, in an interview with one of Phosh’s 
  main developers, Guido Günther.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Outreach</strong>: The FSFE presented the necessity of Free 
  Software for digital sustainability, at the University of Applied 
  Sciences in Berlin, at the <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/3C7v3X7Enfc7raZesFZKKv">Digital Social 
  Summit (recorded, in German)</a>, and in a panel of experts organised 
  by Fairphone on <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/4WvPgN79fuex3eaSR378yH">Sustainable 
  software for phones that last (recorded)</a>. 
  On November 2021, the FSFE participated in the SFSCon by organising a 
  sustainability track with a phone flashing workshop and five talks 
  (recorded, EN): </p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/3y9SdLpKQvZmmXZhEiZ9QV">4 
    principles for a sustainable digital society</a>, by Erik 
    Albers
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/aHCtjJNBc3RjTdnG5Lizbv">Measuring 
    the Sustainability of AI</a>, by Anne Mollen
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/7AQU8NUSpBDeXJnpNf2ukt">Sustainable 
    Software &amp; Blauer Engel Eco-Certification</a>, by Joseph P. De 
    Veaugh-Geiss
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/ehG8iem2TgnsXuv1v4VicB">Software 
    Heritage</a>, by Stefano Zacchiroli
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/8MUWax3LKQVZUsVJyhTRN4">The role 
    of software for our Right to Repair</a>, by Ugo Vallauri
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="public-money-public-code"><span id="anchor-2"/>‘<span id="anchor-3"/>Public Money? Public Code!’</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    "I wish the FSFE to keep up the good work, keep spreading the word 
    of the advantages of Free Software, and keep pushing for more just 
    regulations on political level such as the Public Money? Public 
    Code! campaign."
  </p>
  <cite>
    Lyudmila Vaseva, software developer at ctrl.alt.coop eG. <a href="/news/2022/news-20220121-01.html">Interview</a> in January 
    2022
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  Software created using taxpayers’ money should be released as Free 
  Software. The FSFE actively campaigns for ‘Public Money? Public 
  Code!’ in the EU and several countries in Europe. We advocate to 
  include Free Software in the EU legislation. We run electoral 
  activities asking political parties their stance on Free Software. We 
  showcase good practices from public entities which already use Free 
  Software. We translate our material into several languages and hold 
  events presenting ‘Public Money? Public Code!’ around Europe. We even 
  created an application prototype to make public procurement more 
  transparent; it attained the finals of the EU Datathon!
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Digital Rights</strong>: The European Union is in the process 
  of discussing the Declaration of Digital Rights and Principles. The 
  European Parliament agreed on a common text recognising Free Software 
  as a way to ensure transparency in algorithms and artificial 
  intelligence. The FSFE keeps monitoring the ongoing 
  inter-institutional dialogue trying to <a href="/news/2022/news-20220503-01.html">make sure that the Parliament 
  proposal remains</a>.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Germany</strong>: In November 2021, the newly formed German 
  government <a href="/news/nl/nl-202112.html">agreed with the FSFE's 
  ‘Public Money? Public Code!’ demand</a> and declared it as one of 
  their aims. The coalition agreement set digitisation as a priority 
  and Free Software as a secure and transparent solution. This decision 
  was an important development for the Free Software movement in 
  Germany.
</p>

<p>
  However, 100 days into the new German government in office, no action 
  had been taken. The FSFE <a href="/news/2022/news-20220315-01.html">called upon the government to 
  follow its own plans</a>.
</p>

<p>
  Consequently, together with other actors, the FSFE demanded that the 
  German government should include <a href="/news/2022/news-20220328-01.html">digital sovereignty in the 
  2022 federal budget</a>. In an <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/policy/letters/20220328-German-Budget-and-Free-Software-2022.de.pdf">open 
  letter (DE)</a>, the signatories urge the government groups in the 
  German Parliament, the “Bundestag”, to start implementing their plans 
  regarding Free Software usage.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>German regional administrations</strong>: An association of 
  nine administrations have jointly modernised their administrations, 
  based on Free Software. <a href="https://readi.de/">Re@di – 
  regional.digital</a> is an inter-communal cooperation of nine 
  southern German cities. Their common needs are met through synergy 
  effects in collaborative development. <a href="/news/2022/news-20220602-01.html">In our interview</a>, 
  Alexander Gabriel and Eduard Itrich highlighted that the 
  administrations could use their resources cost-efficiently thanks to 
  cooperation and sharing Free Software.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Italy</strong>: Our Translators team translated the <a href="/activities/publiccode/brochure">‘Public Money? Public Code!’ 
  brochure into Italian</a>. Friends of the team kindly proofread the 
  brochure. Then, volunteers organised a tour presenting the ‘Public 
  Money? Public code!’ campaign in Italy starting with Bologna and <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/mbjBEd1XRjfLDQAGbTHmuc">Trento 
  (recorded, IT with EN subtitles)</a> and will present it in 
  Caltanissetta.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/mbjBEd1XRjfLDQAGbTHmuc">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/dbb7999251b3c638ec703f577e7cad8a.jpg" alt="Four people answering questions from the audience."/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Volunteers presented ‘Public Money? Public Code!’ in Italy <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/mbjBEd1XRjfLDQAGbTHmuc">(recorded, IT 
    with EN subtitles</a>
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  In Trento the event focused on Free Software in Education. In Bologna 
  the event focused on ‘Public Money? Public Code!’ efforts. Members of 
  the local government attended. Three concrete proposals emerged from 
  this event: Coderdojos in public schools, local Coding Gyms, and a 
  public hearing to bring the topic of ‘Public Money? Public Code!’ to 
  the town council.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Spain</strong>: Volunteers translated the ‘Public Money? 
  Public Code!’ brochure into <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/campaigns/pmpc/ES/FSFE_Policy_Brochure_PMPC_ALL_es.pdf">Spanish</a>. 
  To share this good news we organised an <a href="/news/2022/news-20220112-01.html">event dedicated to our 
  Spanish speaking community</a>. We had the participation of experts 
  from GNUHealth, Lliurex, Pica Pica HackLab, Linkat, and KDE. All the 
  talks are <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/p/bWoJwdNZY9GJPJKFCWBUuD">recorded (ES)</a>.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>France</strong>: The FSFE participated in a workshop on data 
  protection and Free Software organised by the French Data Protection 
  Authority (CNIL) in the context of the Open Government initiative. 
  The development of privacy-respecting technologies was the main 
  topic. For scalability, education on ethics and Free Software in 
  engineering and IT schools was proposed. A potential certification 
  for privacy-respecting technologies would create a gatekeeper 
  position, which is undesirable.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Winning prototype</strong>: The FSFE created an <a href="https://ted.sehn.dev/">application prototype</a> which made it 
  to the EU Datathon finals. The program TEDective aspires to connect 
  publicly available tendering and company data and to allow analysis 
  of this data. The goal is to allow citizens and experts to monitor 
  suspicious market activity of public interest. The project idea has 
  been a success and made it to the <strong>top three</strong> out of 
  26 entries in the ‘transparency in public procurement’ challenge of 
  the EU Datathon 2022. Our team has now been invited to further 
  develop and present the project in Brussels.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Outreach</strong>: Naming a few of our outreach activities, 
  the FSFE gave a ‘Public Money? Public Code!’ workshop at the <a href="https://propuestas.eslib.re/2022/talleres/public-money-public-code">esLibre</a> 
  conference in Vigo, Spain, as well as at the rC3 conference. The goal 
  was to encourage attendees to contact their own administrations to 
  demand public code in the public sector<del>.</del> The FSFE 
  presented the role Free Software played during the corona crisis at 
  the <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/fuE6prJSPvpht2bA7NUXVY">esLibre 
  conference (recorded, EN)</a> in Vigo, Spain, at <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/uwqXb3jJUcgE5exH4mm1AS">SFSCon 
  conference (recorded, EN)</a> in Bolzano, Italy and online in <a href="https://www.gnuhealthcon.org/2021/program.html">GnuHealthCon21</a>. 
  We also explained why innovation needs Free Software at <a href="https://make-it.saarland/">make-it.saarl</a> in Saarbrücken, 
  Germany.
</p>

<h2 id="artificial-intelligence"><span id="anchor-4"/><span id="anchor-5"/>Artificial Intelligence and Free Software</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    "Keep advocating for software freedom especially at EU level and 
    public sector. Institutional changes can and must be achieved."
  </p>
  <cite>
    Matti Lammi, System Specialist at ETLA Economic Research. <a href="/news/2022/news-20220121-01.html">Interview</a> in January 
    2022.
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  Artificial Intelligence (AI) can be more verifiable, trustworthy, and 
  innovative with Free Software. Transparency in AI technologies is 
  necessary to test them, evaluate their results, and improve them. The 
  FSFE involves experts in the field of AI, makes policy 
  recommendations, and advocates in AI-related legislation in the 
  European Union.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Policy recommendations</strong>: The FSFE <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/campaigns/AIandFS/fsfe_AIandFreesoftware.pdf">analysed 
  how AI can be more verifiable, trustworthy, innovative with Free 
  Software</a>, and made policy recommendations. The use of Free 
  Software in AI technologies has the potential to increase their 
  adoption by reducing the level of technical knowledge that is 
  necessary to use AI. An existing algorithm that can be re-used 
  benefits the whole research ecosystem. In this regard, public 
  research and educational institutions inventing, using, or procuring 
  AI systems shall publish those, including a description, version 
  history, and the source code in a public register.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>EU Legislation</strong>: The FSFE is <a href="/news/2022/news-20220330-01.html">following the AI Act to 
  ensure Free Software is included</a>. In the effort of adopting 
  digital policies aligned with people’s fundamental rights, the 
  European Parliament is in the process of finding a position on the 
  legal framework for the development and use of AI technologies. 
</p>

<p>
  The European Parliament passed a resolution on AI with a huge 
  majority. According to the resolution, public procurement should 
  require Free Software, where appropriate, with the goal to encourage 
  cross-border collaboration. The Parliament acknowledges that Free 
  Software can enhance investments and boost innovation in AI 
  technologies in the EU. The FSFE urged the Parliament to transfer its 
  own position into the AI regulation.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Expert interview</strong>: <a href="/news/2021/news-20211209-01.html">Our interview with Vincent 
  Lequertier</a>, researcher of artificial intelligence for healthcare, 
  unravels cutting edge topics such as the possibility of AI obtaining 
  the legal right to claim copyright.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Outreach</strong>: The FSFE presented the status of Free 
  Software and artificial intelligence in the European Union during the <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/w3RnCzhmszqPGWc6y28oJh">OW2 
  (recorded)</a> and <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/eedqVoA34sNSTqGN44CtP9">OSCAL 
  (recorded)</a> conferences, and analysed the challenges of ethical AI 
  in <a href="https://kidd-prozess.de/news/jetzt-anmelden-1-kidd-fachkonferenz-findet-am-19-mai-2022-statt/">KIDD-Fachkonferenz</a>.
</p>

<h2 id="router-freedom"><span id="anchor-6"/><span id="anchor-7"/>Router Freedom: Keeping your gateway to the Internet free<strong> </strong></h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    “Router freedom is essential for end-users to remain autonomous in 
    their capacity to access the Internet, employing devices and Free 
    Software they trust for security, privacy and data protection. 
    Users should not be tied down to any particular router or modem 
    package for internet access. The FSFE should continue to campaign 
    for Router Freedom and to collaborate with national digital rights 
    and Free and Open Source Software organizations in order to achieve 
    a neutral, safe and healthy internet”
  </p>
  <cite>
    Kostas Papadimas, GFOSS. Greece
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  Routers and modems are gateways to the Internet. Being able to 
  control these devices is key not only to software freedom but also to 
  security, privacy, and energy consumption. 2022 has been an active 
  year with several positive developments and new challenges. We saw 
  regulators putting forward laws safeguarding this freedom for 
  end-users, internet service providers (ISPs) being forced to comply 
  with the law, and coalitions of organisations and volunteers working 
  together to demand this right from policy makers. On the other side, 
  fiber connections (FTTx) represent a regulatory challenge for the 
  future.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/88DzWmWw3r5o2XoaWCbzTs">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/400402c99ad11297aee04454a16c8a61.jpg" alt="Person presenting slide with map of Europe."/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Lucas Lasota presenting that Router Freedom is a reality in several European countries. Full talk available (EN). SFSCon, 2021.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  We work, with growing success, with regulators to make them 
  understand that Router Freedom should be consolidated in legislation. 
  In 2022 we worked on several issues/challenges, ranging from 
  multi-stakeholder initiatives to bilateral cooperation with 
  regulators and strategic support from partner organisations in 
  Europe.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Freeing fiber connections</strong>: The deployment of fiber 
  networks in Europe has posed regulatory challenges for policy makers. 
  Deciding whether end-users can use their terminal equipment for their 
  internet connection has a direct impact on divergent interests of 
  consumer protection authorities versus large telecom operators. Major 
  ISPs seek to cover their investments in the deployment of 
  new-generation networks at the expense of end-users who suffer from 
  commercial practices that restrict their legitimate rights to 
  exercise digital freedoms.
</p>

<p>
  In 2022, we have been collaborating with regulators to develop better 
  policies that take the interests of end-users into consideration. We 
  shared our concerns with regulators <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/routers/fsfe-eett-ntp1-en.pdf">planning 
  to exclude Fiber to the Home constructions (FTTH)</a> from Router 
  Freedom, as well as with those who still are <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/routers/fsfe-ftth-rf-es.pdf">analysing 
  the fiber market</a>. We also contextualized the <a href="/news/2022/news-20220510-01.html"> regulatory issues of Router 
  Freedom for the Body of European Regulators for Electronic 
  Communications (BEREC)</a> from the perspective of the sustainability 
  of the telecom sector. During all these processes we have been 
  counting on support of several network specialists who have been 
  volunteering to study, research, and share their opinions with us.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Greece</strong>: The FSFE <a href="/news/2022/news-20220628-01.html">assisted a coalition</a> of 
  organisations in Greece to help provide feedback to the Greek 
  regulator on the upcoming legislation that will consolidate Router 
  Freedom in the country. We highlighted in our position the importance 
  of securing this freedom for all kinds of networks, including DSL, 
  coaxial, and FTTH. Our position (<a href="https://download.fsfe.org/routers/fsfe-eett-ntp1-en.pdf">EN</a>), 
  (<a href="https://download.fsfe.org/routers/fsfe-eett-ntp1-el.pdf">EL</a>) 
  was supported by key stakeholders in the field of digital rights, 
  consumer protection, and business representation. The FSFE country 
  team <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Greece">Greece</a> 
  helped in the translation.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Austria</strong>: The FSFE and the Alliance of 
  Telecommunication Terminal Equipment Manufacturers (VTKE), organised 
  an <a href="/news/2022/news-20220516-01.html">online session 
  (recorded, DE) </a>where key stakeholders debated the future 
  perspectives of Router Freedom in Austria. Although industry 
  representatives raised concerns about the integrity of the networks 
  and user experience, the majority of stakeholders agreed on the 
  advantages of having Router Freedom secured in the legislation.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/d77d9c6c1dd67bde4691263433e0448a.png">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/d77d9c6c1dd67bde4691263433e0448a.png" alt="Four benefits of Router Freedom. #1. Choose your own router.      The device given by your internet service provider should not be      the only possibility. #2 Secure your internet connection. Routers      transmit personal data. Some terminal equipment offers greater      privacy than others. Determine for yourself the level of security      you want. #3. Upgrade your router. Increase the speed and coverage      of your router. Make it compatible with your devices. Configure,      improve, and repair your router. Its performance should be up to      you. #4. Avoid a router monopoly. If you can only use the equipment      provided by a single company, your possibilities might be less      secure or less user-friendly. And you will have no alternative. Get      the most out of the innovations in the router market."/>
  </a>
</figure>

<p>
  <strong>Italy</strong>: Italian volunteers and our partner 
  organisation <a href="https://www.modemlibero.it/">Modem Libero</a> 
  have collaborated with us in monitoring the regulatory panorama in 
  the country, especially in regard to FTTx and related antitrust 
  issues.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>The Netherlands</strong>: The FSFE country team Netherlands 
  held <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Events/Netherlands/2022-03-16">preparatory 
  meetings</a> for the upcoming reform of the telecommunications law in 
  Belgium and started coordinating efforts with partner organisations 
  for potential actions. They also have been following the <a href="https://www.acm.nl/nl/publicaties/acm-dagelijkse-dwangsommen-als-ziggo-juli-regels-voor-vrije-modemkeuze-nog-overtreedt">enforcement</a> 
  of Router Freedom rules in the Netherlands.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Survey</strong>: Internet users from all over Europe have 
  been participating in our <a href="https://survey.fsfe.org/index.php/628449">Router Freedom 
  survey</a>, sharing their experience with ISPs, reporting problems 
  and issues, and providing their opinion on relevant issues for 
  freedom of terminal equipment. The results of the survey will be 
  published at the beginning of 2023.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Infographics</strong>: Volunteers have translated our new 
  Router Freedom infographics into Dutch (<a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/9b227849b1f272b7a492bc882ab55440.png">1</a>,<a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/9efd10337be580471abff2d7e2a5dfdc.png">2</a>), 
  Italian (<a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/b880a54d823fe0eb5126409562901d4e.png">1</a>,<a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/da1f66ed6e69492727a3102583fe84f4.png">2</a>), 
  French (<a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/6c298bd909e4b3b570b7665c057b155c.png">1</a>,<a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/f7345e166500487ed0ac672919bb4c1b.png">2</a>), 
  and Greek (<a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/51c9a501ff62da3ccf89c7310455b52d.png">1</a>,<a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/1cf14dc6c11a1eed8b14f51ba979a8e0.png">2</a>). 
  Groups of volunteers were active in Italy, the Netherlands, and 
  Portugal.
</p>

<h2 id="device-neutrality"><span id="anchor-8"/><span id="anchor-9"/>Device Neutrality: Regaining control over our devices<span id="anchor-10"/></h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    Code is law, as Lawrence Lessig put it. Therefore Free Software and 
    open standards are necessary for human freedom. Our freedom is 
    threatened by patents, copy-prevention schemes, locked-down devices 
    and spying. To counter these threats I support the FSFE's 
    campaigning for open standards, information security and device 
    sovereignty, and against ever more onerous copyright laws.
  </p>
  <cite>
    Björn Persson (Software Engineer)
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  Have you ever noticed that the number of devices you are using daily 
  is continuously growing, but it is ever harder to run Free Software 
  on them? This is not only your personal impression, but a fact: large 
  device manufacturers, vendors and system providers are increasingly 
  locking devices down, restricting end-users’ freedoms.
</p>

<p>
  The FSFE kicked off the <a href="/activities/deviceneutrality/index">Device Neutrality</a> 
  initiative to promote strategies for regaining control over devices. 
  In 2022 we dedicated efforts to get Device Neutrality in the EU 
  legislation.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/41853f80b7b2b1eea6491c84ef2f574a.png" alt="DN logo."/>
</figure>

<p>
  <strong>Digital Markets Act</strong>: Since 2021, the EU has been 
  elaborating a comprehensive piece of legislation to regulate large 
  digital platforms. We have dedicated efforts to include Device 
  Neutrality in the new law<a href="/news/2021/news-20211122-01.html"> 
  and collaborated</a> with policy makers in the European Parliament. 
  The Digital Markets Act is an important advance for setting several 
  anti-monopoly obligations that impact software freedom, 
  interoperability, and control over personal data.
</p>

<p>
  After many iterations and amendments, the European Parliament adopted 
  the Digital Markets Act by 642 votes in favour, 8 votes against, and 
  46 abstentions. With this vote, <a href="/news/2021/news-20211215-01.html">the principle of Device 
  Neutrality is introduced</a>. At the same time, the Parliament missed 
  the chance to introduce strong requirements for interoperability 
  based on Open Standards. As a summary of our involvement, we have 
  prepared an <a href="/activities/dma/dma.html">analysis on how Free 
  Software is a crucial element for the law’s implementation</a>.
</p>

<p>
  Although Device Neutrality in the legislation is a major first step, 
  the law’s enforcement will be challenging, and will require close 
  monitoring from civil society. Free Software and Open Standards are 
  key factors for proper implementation of Device Neutrality in 
  Europe.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Radio Equipment Directive</strong>: The FSFE is on guard 
  about a <a href="/activities/radiodirective/">Radio 
  Lockdown Directive</a>. The EU Radio Equipment Directive may make it 
  impossible to install a custom piece of software on most radio 
  devices. This affects, for example, WiFi routers, phones, and 
  embedded devices. The regulation requires hardware manufacturers to 
  implement a barrier that disallows users to install any software 
  which has not been certified by them. Unfortunately we cannot report 
  major new developments of the last year. The European Commission, in 
  particular DG GROW (the department responsible for the internal 
  market and industry), does not share information about the current 
  state of the Delegated Act that is to be prepared. Even the results 
  of the last consultation in 2020 are not public yet. We are 
  continuing to monitor the situation and we are ready to act on the 
  next development. The topic is too important to ignore.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Public Awareness</strong>: We shared the concept of Device 
  Neutrality with several communities and venues to get feedback and 
  inputs so we could provide valuable insights for policy makers. We 
  presented the concept at <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/vnCosTd5csWzYP5KYBA6mD">FOSDEM 2022</a>, 
  and debated it at <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/9age6ocReoUxGsU1HQv7q9">OW2 2022 
  (recorded)</a>. We talked with legal folk at <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/presentations/20210623-llas-llw.pdf">LLW 
  2022</a> and shared insights with the <a href="https://cfp.openlabs.cc/oscal2022/talk/8NSYYA/">OSCAL</a> 
  community.
</p>

<h2 id="legal-support"><span id="anchor-11"/><span id="anchor-12"/>Legal support for Free Software programs</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    "NGI0 not only made it possible to pursue our goals by supplying 
    funding. I was approached a number of times by professionals whom I 
    learned to respect for their knowledge. [We received] concrete 
    support, ranging from security to usability, internationalisation, 
    licensing, and copyrighting, and putting what we do in a 
    perspective of inclusiveness and diversity. Their help will go a 
    long way to improve our products and I am sure to seek out other 
    partners to the NGI0 project before we are done.” 
  </p>
  <cite>
    Joop Ringelberg, <a href="https://perspect.it/">Perspectives-core Project</a>
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  Programs often come with legal questions, and the FSFE is here to 
  help Free Software programs. We answer licensing questions, we 
  provide technical support to make licensing easier, we provide legal 
  education materials on Free Software, and we organise an annual 
  conference. Since 2008, the FSFE has organised the annual Free 
  Software Legal and Licensing Workshop (LLW) for the FSFE’s Legal 
  Network. It is a conference for legal experts in the field of Free 
  Software to debate over issues and share best practices surrounding 
  Free Software licenses.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Answering licensing questions</strong>: The FSFE runs a team 
  for <a href="/freesoftware/legal/faq.html#lqteam">License 
  Questions</a>, composed of several volunteer legal experts from 
  around Europe who continuously help projects and individuals with 
  topics concerning Free Software licensing. Anyone who has a question 
  about Free Software licensing can reach out to the group with an to <email>licence-questions@fsfe.org</email>. 
  This year, we helped many members of the public with answering basic 
  license questions, mainly with the help of our <a href="/freesoftware/legal/faq.html">online FAQ 
  resource</a>.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Next Generation Internet Zero (NGI0):</strong> The FSFE 
  continued its activities in the European Commission’s <a href="/activities/ngi/ngi.html">NGI0 initiative</a> this year, and 
  will wrap up its activities when the project comes to a close at the 
  end of 2022. Thus far, we have worked with almost <strong>300 
  participating software projects</strong> to aid them by providing 
  recommendations to achieve REUSE compliance, as well as assisting 
  with any legal and licensing questions that they may have.
</p>

<p>
  The goal of this NGI0 initiative is to provide support to developing 
  software technologies that can help to improve the internet into a 
  platform that facilitates and supports transparency, human rights, 
  and democracy. The FSFE is involved specifically in two NGI0 actions: 
  NGI0 PET, which supports software projects that support privacy and 
  enhancing trust online, and NGI0 Discovery, which supports software 
  projects that improve user ability to search and discover information 
  online.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Legal and Licensing Workshop</strong>:<a href="/freesoftware/legal/faq.html"> </a>The 2022 edition of the LLW 
  was originally planned to take place in Gothenburg, Sweden. But 
  during the planning process the decision was made to take the 
  conference online once again, due to uncertainties about COVID-19. 
  Although holding the LLW online again was not ideal, we nevertheless 
  were pleased to organize a successful event over the course of 5 
  weeks in April and May with the help of many of our Legal Network 
  volunteers. All talks organized were held by default under the 
  Chatham House Rule, and included discussions on topics such as the 
  Netfilter v. McHardy settlement in Germany, the ongoing Software 
  Freedom Conservancy v. Vizio lawsuit in the USA, emerging trends in 
  the use of Free Software in Open Science, and other timely and 
  relevant subjects.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Legal Education Day</strong>: Understanding the legal matters 
  and complying with legal obligations can become a burden sometimes. 
  That is the reason why we were happy to organize the first <a href="/freesoftware/legal/led.html">Legal Education Day</a> (LED). We 
  provided basic legal education on the legal context of Free Software: 
  copyright law and the concept of copyleft. Useful topics for software 
  developers followed, such as license compatibility, trademarks, and 
  containers. We plan to repeat LED next year.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>New European Commission Projects:</strong> This year, we also 
  participated in the drafting and submission of three additional 
  European Commission projects that were planned to start by the end of 
  2022: NGI0 Zooom, NGI0 Entrust, and NGI0 Review. Despite a long 
  submission process and waiting period, we were pleased that all three 
  projects were approved, and that we will be participating in them in 
  a similar capacity to our work in NGI0. This means that we will 
  continue to provide legal support for a wide range of software from 
  all over Europe, when work for these approved projects begins at the 
  end of the year.
</p>

<p>
  Similar to our existing activities with the NGI0 initiative, the FSFE 
  will be a member of a joint consortium of organizations that provide 
  support to software developments that participate in these European 
  Commission projects. Our primary role would be to provide assistance 
  with their legal and licensing needs, primarily through our <a href="https://reuse.software/">REUSE</a> specifications.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Public Awareness</strong>: The FSFE gave an online lecture on 
  Software Law and Free Software licences at the <a href="https://www.projekte.hu-berlin.de/de/gnuHU/projekte/floss-werkstatt/veranstaltungen/wise-21-22/introduction-to-software-law-and-floss-licences-10-01-22">Humboldt 
  University </a>of Berlin focusing on conceptual introductions to 
  licensing and copyleft.
</p>

<h2 id="reuse"><span id="anchor-13"/><span id="anchor-14"/>REUSE: Making licensing easier</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p> 
    "Regarding REUSE, we have learnt a lot. We realise that the idea 
    behind REUSE is simple, clear, and powerful… Nowadays, Free 
    Software projects become more and more complicated, and many 
    components/files of a single project have different 
    license/copyright information. REUSE helps a lot on tracking the 
    status of this information in our project.” 
  </p>
  <cite>
    Xianjun Jiao, <a href="https://github.com/JiaoXianjun/openwifi">OpenWifi Project</a>
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  Free Software is created by developers, and comes as everything 
  between small projects and huge corporate suites. Releasing code 
  while granting its users the four freedoms should be simple, but 
  third-party components might come with a variety of available Free 
  Software licenses and thus create some burden.
</p>

<p>
  With REUSE we try to make all of this easier for everyone: individual 
  developers, users, businesses, and re-users. REUSE is a set of best 
  practices and tools with the goal to describe the copyright and 
  licensing information of all files in a repository in a pragmatic and 
  sustainable way. On a large scale, this makes Free Software more 
  transparent and safer to re-use.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>New REUSE version</strong>: We <a href="https://lists.fsfe.org/pipermail/reuse/2022q2/000143.html">released 
  version 1.0.0</a><a href="https://lists.fsfe.org/pipermail/reuse/2022q2/000143.html"> of 
  the REUSE helper tool</a> that makes the initial adoption of the best 
  practices in a repository more comfortable. Thanks to our awesome 
  volunteers and external contributors to the project, we aim for even 
  more features and simplifications for developers.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Implementations</strong>: Obviously, the best standard is 
  irrelevant if it remains unused. This is why we assist projects with 
  understanding their current licensing and copyright situation and 
  making it transparent via REUSE. A prominent example is <a href="https://github.com/curl/curl">cURL</a>, an universally-known 
  tool for transferring network data, which became officially REUSE 
  compliant in July 2022. We are continuing this effort, e.g. with the 
  <a href="https://savannah.gnu.org/forum/forum.php?forum_id=10208">GNUHealth 
  project </a>whose team decided to adopt REUSE for all their 
  components. Please feel free to reach out to projects you would like 
  to be REUSE compliant, and spread the word!
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Outreach</strong>: The FSFE presented the REUSE activity and 
  the importance of licensing metadata in Free Software on several 
  occasions. We gave presentations at the <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/kyJ2WThjdmgmECszKosppt">Upstream 
  (recorded)</a> event, at the <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/cF54Fj99xAUyDVwQ6Q8MoZ">esLibre 
  conference (recorded, in Spanish)</a> in Vigo, Spain, and at the <a href="https://openexpoeurope.com/es/oe2022/">OpenExpoEurope2022</a> 
  conference in Madrid, Spain. We also presented REUSE at the <a href="https://www.weizenbaum-conference.de/day-1/">Weizenbaum 
  conference</a> in Berlin, a venue dedicated to interventions for open 
  digital futures, at <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/1CEroi8ph8oej5eFofQECJ">FrOSCon 
  (recorded, EN)</a> in St. August, Germany, and at <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/9ut2RZYbF99ArSMe8eSsjp">SFSCon 
  (recorded, EN)</a> in Bolzano, Italy.
</p>

<h2 id="yh4f"><span id="anchor-15"/><span id="anchor-16"/>Youth Hacking 4 Freedom: A coding competition </h2>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/9594f30fb15a8edf5082d60baac594bd.png">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/9594f30fb15a8edf5082d60baac594bd.png" alt="Illustration with three students in a hacker space with posters"/>
  </a>
</figure>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    “Taking part in this competition was personally a big step as 
    before it I have never ever programmed something and I did not have 
    knowledge to do so. During the project I learned a lot more about 
    programming concepts, how can I implement the modules and generally 
    the programming language Python.”
  </p>
  <cite>
    Ekaterina, one of the winners of the competition
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  The coding competition <a href="/activities/yh4f/">Youth Hacking 4 
  Freedom</a> is a new initiative of the FSFE. Our goal is to make more 
  young people aware of Free Software by encouraging them to tinker and 
  experiment with technology. It is a chance for young people to 
  discuss and network with important people in the fields of computer 
  science and Free Software. The winners are rewarded with a trip to 
  Brussels and a cash prize, which might turn into an investment for 
  their own project. The first year of the competition was a success 
  with wide participation and well-made winning projects.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Participation</strong>: We had the pleasure to receive many 
  interesting and inspiring projects from all around Europe. 
  <strong>Over a hundred people </strong>aged 13 to 19 <strong>from 25 
  countries </strong>registered for the competition, making it a truly 
  pan-European event.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Coding period</strong>: The participants had five months to 
  come up with a Free Software project. 35 of them submitted a project 
  to the jury.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Jury</strong>: An <a href="/activities/yh4f/jury.html">independent jury</a> evaluated the 
  submitted projects. The jury members excel in software development 
  and are deeply involved in the Free Software movement.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Six Winners</strong>: The winning programs offer sign 
  language transcription, a smart table robot, a personal assistant, a 
  music tutorial, file sharing, and a homework manager. Of course, all 
  Free Software.
</p>

<h2 id="childrens-book"><span id="anchor-17"/><span id="anchor-18"/>Children’s book: A tale of software, skateboards, and raspberry ice cream</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    "A rousing tale of self-reliance, community, and standing up to 
    bullies...software freedom is human freedom!"
  </p>
  <cite>
    Cory Doctorow, Sci-Fi Author
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  In November 2021 O’Reilly published our book “Ada &amp; Zangemann – A 
  Tale of Software, Skateboards, and Raspberry Ice Cream” (in German) 
  under a Creative Commons license. A children’s book for young and old 
  readers, ‘<a href="/activities/ada-zangemann/">Ada 
  &amp; Zangemann</a>’ is a fun and educational tale.
</p>
<p>
  The author, Matthias Kirschner, President of the FSFE, conveys to 
  readers, young and old, the importance of common ownership of 
  software, and even the basics of more complex topics around it. 
  Sandra Brandstätter brings the characters to life with her beautiful 
  illustrations. It quickly sold out at the publisher O'Reilly, right 
  before the holiday season, and received good reviews. In June 2022 we 
  distributed a non-profit Ukrainian translation of the book.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="/activities/ada-zangemann/">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/b2b23d22357bfc0c568a472b45a56dd3.png" alt="Illustration of three pieces. On the left side, an      illustration showing a girl typing on a keyboard connected to her      phone among tools and open books. On the right side, an old grumpy      man types in front of ultra luxurious screens in the middle of      furnitures with golden details. At the bottom, the text Ada and      Zangemann is accompanied with the book cover."/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Ada unravels the mysteries of software in an adventure with her friends, after an unfortunate encounter with the rich and famous inventor Zangemann.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  <strong>Book Donations</strong>: After the publication of Ada &amp; 
  Zangemann, we asked our German-speaking community to bring copies of 
  the book to public libraries for children who cannot afford it or 
  have not heard of it. The response was overwhelming: over <strong>60 
  books</strong> were donated to libraries in Austria, Germany, and 
  Switzerland.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Reviews</strong>: ‘Ada &amp; Zangemann’ received a good 
  rating by EKZ-group, the organisation reviewing new publications for 
  public libraries in Germany and Austria. Therefore the book was 
  recommended to be added to public libraries. The review characterised 
  Ada &amp; Zangemann as “attractively illustrated by S. Brandstätter, 
  […] didactically well structured and very suitable as a basis for 
  discussion”. Among other magazines, the book received positive 
  reviews in the technological magazines <a href="https://www.linux-magazin.de/news/kinderbuch-ada-zangemann-bezauberndes-open-source-maerchen/">Linux 
  Magazine</a> and <a href="https://www.golem.de/sonstiges/zustimmung/auswahl.html?from=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.golem.de%2Fnews%2Fada-zangemann-das-it-maerchen-das-wir-brauchen-2112-161416.html">Golem</a>.
</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    Kirschner’s book introduces readers young and old to the power and 
    peril of software. It also highlights the accelerating effects of 
    <strong>sharing software freely </strong>– creating conditions for 
    direct and indirect collaboration which can be a metaphor for the 
    conduct of science. Behind it all is a backdrop of <strong>ethics 
    of knowledge sharing</strong> upon which the arc of human history 
    rides. 
  </p>
  <cite>
    Vint Cerf, Computer Scientist, one of the inventors of the Internet
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  <strong>Ukrainian version</strong>:<strong> </strong>The FSFE 
  translated ‘Ada &amp; Zangemann’ into Ukrainian, giving a freely 
  available <a href="https://share.fsfe.org/s/2LToF6ZWRAMQZ8X">e-book</a> and 
  donating <strong>2,750 copies </strong>of the book to public 
  institutions and non-governmental organisations all around Europe 
  which further distributed them to refugee children from Ukraine and 
  to public libraries.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/7c246fa1fd8232ad2f982fc60d7e47f1.jpg" alt="Photograph with children"/>
  <figcaption>
    Author reading of "Ada&amp;Zangemann" to over 150 3rd graders from Offenburg schools. © CC-BY-SA Stadt Offenburg / herrfichtner
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  <strong>Outreach</strong>:<strong> </strong>The FSFE reached out to 
  the younger generation with author readings of the book: <a href="https://k7r.eu/recent-readings-of-ada-zangemann/">in a 
  hackerspace bus</a> at re:publica in Berlin, in a <a href="https://k7r.eu/recent-readings-of-ada-zangemann/">large cinema 
  room</a> filled with over 150 third-graders in Offenburg, <a href="https://www.stadt-koeln.de/leben-in-koeln/freizeit-natur-sport/veranstaltungskalender/ada-und-zangemann-autorenlesung">in 
  a public library in Cologne</a>, online at Chemnitzer Linux-Tage, 
  online at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2bHLxFqTnRo">Wintercongress 
  (recorded, DE)</a>, and three readings in school classes in Berlin 
  and two in South Germany. The author participated in podcast episodes 
  at <a href="https://anchor.fm/opensourcecouch/episodes/Jubilumsfolge-Interview-mit-FSFE-Prsident-und-Kinderbuchautor-Matthias-Kirschner-e1dp5mv/a-a7b461l">Open 
  source couch (DE)</a> and <a href="https://gnulinux.ch/gln017-podcast">GNU/Linux (DE)</a>.
</p>

<h2 id="education"><span id="anchor-19"/><span id="anchor-20"/>Free Software in Education</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    Free Software has many practical advantages for businesses, 
    education and the public sector, but most importantly it should be 
    considered as a human right. I became a supporter of the FSFE to 
    help make that point - why Free Software is so important for a 
    lively democratic society and for every one of us.
  </p>
  <cite>
    Erik Grun
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  Students should learn information technology concepts instead of just 
  learning how to use products of proprietary software companies. Free 
  Software helps students understand technology and specifically 
  coding. Also, with Free Software development students can learn the 
  value of collaboratively working together for a common good. These 
  are just some of the reasons why <a href="/freesoftware/education/"> 
  students should learn using Free Software and educational institutes 
  should use Free Software</a> too. This year we had several activities 
  showing the importance of Free Software in education in several 
  countries.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Stockholm</strong>: We <a href="/news/2021/news-20211216-01.html">interviewed two major 
  contributors behind Öppna skolplattformen</a> (‘Open school 
  platform’), the functional and secure Free Software alternative to 
  the proprietary school platform (‘Skolplattformen’). Parents spotted 
  irregularities and security issues in the €100 million publicly 
  funded proprietary platform. When they proceeded to fix the flaws 
  themselves, the city of Stockholm took legal measures against the 
  developers.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Netherlands</strong>: Students should not have to use 
  proprietary software to participate in the educational process. The 
  FSFE <a href="/news/2022/news-20220520-01.html">joined the Dutch 
  coalition ‘Fair Digital Education’</a> supporting privacy-respecting 
  solutions involving Free Software in schools.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Barcelona</strong>: The FSFE joined the <a href="https://congress.democratic-digitalisation.xnet-x.net/">Democratic 
  Digitalisation conference</a> and gave input in a panel about the 
  importance of Free Software. The FSFE noted that public funds should 
  not be allocated to make education dependent on Big Tech.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Berlin</strong>: The <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Berlin">local group 
  Berlin</a> has monthly online meetings dedicated to Free Software in 
  Education.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Zurich</strong>: The FSFE <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Zurich">local group 
  Zurich</a> works on ‘<a href="http://lernenwiedieprofis.ch/">Lernen 
  wie die profis</a>’, a campaign presenting the available Free 
  Software tools that are suitable for classrooms. This year the group 
  focused on the outreach of the campaign.
</p>

<h2 id="public-awareness"><span id="anchor-20"/><span id="anchor-21"/>What is Free Software? - Our work on public awareness</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    “The FSFE does great work to further software freedom locally, 
    nationally and in the EU and I enjoy the podcast and the News RSS 
    so it felt natural to become a supporter. I also want to be more 
    involved with the free software community.”
  </p>
  <cite>
    Einar Mostad, English teacher, musician, IT student.
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  To make software freedom a widespread reality, people need to know 
  what Free Software is. We constantly work on public awareness, 
  explaining Free Software to new audiences.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Videos</strong>: We published a short <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/xs29yhLxSP1uKLYkSeoKKp">video in 
  English</a> and <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/ndxFckPP8yWhMfnPcsvEkM">in German</a>: 
  ‘What is Free Software (Open Source)?’. We explained the complex 
  topic of software freedom in under three minutes. This can help a new 
  audience grasp the importance of Free Software.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>I Love Free Software Day</strong>: One more time, on 14 
  February, <a href="/news/2022/news-20220310-01.html">people around 
  the world celebrated the “I Love Free Software Day”</a> by thanking 
  all the people who contribute to software freedom throughout the 
  year. On that day, as in previous years, <em>#ilovefs</em> has been 
  number one in the Fediverse network with over <strong>47.000 mentions 
  </strong>and over 20 thousand users talking about their love for Free 
  Software. Numerous Free Software organisations, and, among others, 
  DINUM, the Interministerial Digital Directorate of France, spread the 
  thank you message.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/9bf392a8fe0b6b7ee5731a2f9e97efbe.png" alt="Pxelised heart and joystick"/>
</figure>

<p>
  This year’s I Love Free Software Day was gaming-themed. For the first 
  time, we held a <a href="/news/2022/news-20220310-01.html">dedicated 
  event for IloveFS</a>: in our two-hour event the FSFE hosted four 
  speakers who took us into the world of Free Software games. 
  (recorded: <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/fHAMRDb88yJJEkFu7g24jY">Veloren</a>, 
  <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/kFxwEUg12T5xhNG4rVBkXH">Flare</a>, 
  <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/4pD2gBf85R2TWaszGPVWXJ">Vassal</a>, 
  <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/eThiqVS7hDYpGdhyCCmv5y">Wild 
  Jams</a>). Roughly <strong>60 people </strong>joined the event. 
  Afterwards, participants were invited to play Veloren together, 
  making the afternoon a ton of fun.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="/news/podcast/episode-14.html">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/0bf10017e47d8510d09d6058db413290.png" alt="Woman smiling in a park."/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Want to learn more about Mesh networks? Elektra Wagenrad explained 
    the concept in the 14th Software Freedom Podcast <a href="/news/podcast/episode-14.html">episode</a>
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  <strong>Podcasts</strong>: The FSFE continued the Software Freedom 
  Podcasts throughout the year. We interviewed <a href="/news/podcast/episode-13.html">Stanislas Dolcini, a developer 
  of 0 A.D. Empires Ascendant</a>, a Free Software real-time strategy 
  game of ancient warfare. Next was <a href="/news/podcast/episode-14.html">Elektra Wagenrad, one of the 
  original developers of the B.A.T.M.A.N. protocol and of the Mesh 
  Potato project</a>, who presented these initiatives in a podcast 
  episode. And, as mentioned earlier, Erik Albers presented the <a href="/news/podcast/episode-15.html">Upcycling Android campaign</a>.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="/contribute/spreadtheword#childrensbook">
    <img src="/contribute/promopics/childrensbook-sticker-ada-2022-thumb.png" alt="Illustration of a young girl on skateboard."/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Ada and Zangemann stickers
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  <strong>Promotional material</strong>: The FSFE offers <a href="/contribute/spreadtheword">promotional material</a> at no cost 
  to people who want to spread the message of software freedom. This 
  year we enriched our collection with stickers for <a href="/contribute/spreadtheword.html#upcyclingandroid">Upcycling 
  Android</a>, <a href="/contribute/spreadtheword.html#device-neutrality">Router 
  Freedom</a>, and <a href="/contribute/spreadtheword.html#childrensbook">Ada and 
  Zangemann</a>. We sent out <strong>324 promotional packages 
  </strong>for free to <strong>23 countries, </strong>so that those who 
  are interested could use the promotional materials and distribute 
  them. We also offer a collection of merchandise so that people can 
  show their affiliation to the FSFE. <a href="/order/">Try them 
  out</a>!
</p>



<h2 id="fosdem"><span id="anchor-22"/>The FOSDEM 2022 conference</h2>

<p>
  Europe's most prominent annual Free Software conference, FOSDEM, once 
  more happened as an online event. <a href="/news/2022/news-20220224-01.html">We used the event to exchange 
  opinions and chat with people from the Free Software community.</a> 
  We raised awareness on wider issues that impact our movement in the 
  Legal and Policy Devroom.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Policy Devroom</strong>: The FSFE co-hosted the Legal and 
  Policy Issues Devroom in FOSDEM, together with Karen Sandler and 
  Bradley M. Kuhn from Software Freedom Conservancy and Richard Fontana 
  from Red Hat. The talks, which are all recorded, covered:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/jcEG9zpj2cG7gpHdUbEyBa">How to 
    teach OSS licenses and compliances at a university</a>, by Masafumi 
    Ohta;
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/ud3ERe9C9Zdz5Lbm2bcfsD">A 
    globally unified governance framework for Open Source</a>, by 
    Christopher Klooz;
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/2Nt8Auippqob2kSxErQ9p9">Open 
    Source, Interoperability and the Digital Markets Act</a>, by 
    Vittorio Bertola;
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/vnCosTd5csWzYP5KYBA6mD">Why 
    Device Neutrality is important for Free Software</a>, by Lucas 
    Lasota;
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/sf3TPJfTNQ66gDwhSZfWN8">Why the 
    pandemic could help FOSS, but was a win for proprietary 
    software</a>, by Italo Vignoli; and </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/kmWiEp5H7CKuU19yYEuGaU">closing 
    remarks</a> by the organisers: Bradley M. Kuhn, Karen Sandler, 
    Richard Fontana, Max Mehl, and Alexander Sander.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
  <strong>Booth</strong>: For first-time visitors, we provided a shiny 
  <a href="https://stands.fosdem.org/stands/free_software_foundation_europe/">virtual 
  booth presence on the FOSDEM website</a>, showcasing the FSFE and our 
  most notable developments in recent months.
</p>

<h2 id="association"><span id="anchor-23"/><span id="anchor-24"/>The FSFE e.V. association</h2>

<p>
  <a href="/about/legal/minutes/minutes-2021-11-27.en.pdf"><strong>General 
  Assembly</strong></a>: The General Assembly of the FSFE met for its 
  annual meeting on 26 November 2021. During the meeting the attendees 
  discussed long term strategies and challenges for promoting software 
  freedom and held elections for the FSFE Council. Matthias Kirschner, 
  Heiki Lõhmus, and Patrick Ohnewein were re-elected for two years to 
  the positions of President, Vice-President, and Financial Officer 
  respectively.
</p>

<h2 id="community"><span id="anchor-25"/>The FSFE <span id="anchor-26"/>community across Europe</h2>


<p>
  Many people all over Europe support the use of Free Software and act 
  to promote it. The FSFE helps the Free Software community around 
  Europe to take action and stay up to date. Our community is organised 
  in local groups, country teams, and thematic groups. The local groups 
  and country teams discuss local issues and often create local 
  initiatives. Every action undertaken by the FSFE becomes stronger 
  thanks to our volunteers who spread our message across Europe.
</p>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Aarhus"><strong>Aarhus</strong></a>: 
  The Aarhus local group was relaunched after seven years with the aim 
  to raise awareness of Free Software in Denmark. The group decided to 
  focus on outreach and ‘Public Money? Public Code!’ topics.
</p>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Berlin"><strong>Berlin</strong></a>: 
  The local group Berlin has monthly in-person meetings. The group 
  participated in the FSFE booth in the Open House event of the German 
  Federal Ministry of Environment. Volunteers were on the spot during 
  the event, explaining Free Software to the audience. They presented 
  <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/index.html">upcycled Android phones</a> and 
  explained how Free Software can help overcome software obsolescence.
</p>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Barcelona"><strong>Barcelona</strong></a>: 
  The Free Software Barcelona group had the first in-person event since 
  2020.
</p>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/France"><strong>France</strong></a>: 
  The FSFE country team France revamped its <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/France">wiki</a> page, had two 
  internal meetings, and is planning to participate in large Free 
  Software events in the next months.
</p>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Greece"><strong>Greece</strong></a>: 
  The FSFE country team Greece opened its own <a href="https://matrix.to/#/%23greece:fsfe.org">Matrix room</a> to 
  discuss challenging translations of technical terms and software 
  freedom topics.
</p>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Hamburg"><strong>Hamburg</strong></a>: 
  The local group Hamburg has monthly in-person meetings.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/BNL#FSFE_Nederland_.2F_Niederlande_.2F_Pays-Bas_.2F_Netherlands">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/e57f1ea6a43c5a6b6f3cd33aea34fd42.jpg" alt="two people at a booth"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    André Ockers and Nico Rikken at the FSFE booth in the NLLGG in 
    Utrecht, The Netherlands, May 2022
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/BNL#FSFE_Nederland_.2F_Niederlande_.2F_Pays-Bas_.2F_Netherlands"><strong>Netherlands</strong></a>: 
  The FSFE country team the Netherlands influenced policy on the 
  digital identity system in the Netherlands, offered advice to the 
  Dutch Ministry of Internal Affairs, and provided a great number of 
  translations from English to Dutch.
</p>

<p>
  An important topic for the country team is the Dutch government’s 
  Free Software strategy. The team finds the <a href="https://blogs.fsfe.org/nico.rikken/2022/03/16/dutch-digital-identity-system-crisis/">increased 
  dependency on DigID</a>, the Dutch digital identity app, worrying. 
  The team members managed to achieve some political gains through 
  joint community efforts. They called upon parliament to prevent 
  big-tech lock-in through authentication services for governmental 
  usage. The Dutch community sent letters and emails together with 
  other organisations. In the end it resulted in <a href="https://www.security.nl/posting/755793/Van+Huffelen+wil+dat+DigiD+in+toekomst+volledig+open+source+wordt">concrete 
  motions by parliament for analogue alternatives and basing the 
  solutions on Free Software</a>. Although the motions did not correct 
  the authentication process, they were a concrete action as a response 
  to volunteer efforts. Also the FSFE Netherlands country team advised 
  the Dutch Ministry of Internal Affairs (Binnenlandse Zaken, BZK) 
  about adopting and publishing Free Software.
</p>

<p>
  Finally, as always, the group was very active in translating this 
  year: Dutch has the greatest number of new translated pages in 2022 
  (59), not counting the updated ones. Dutch is reaching German in the 
  total number of translated pages in the FSFE website: Dutch 1351, 
  German 1482. Quite a race.
</p>

<p>
  For everybody interested, the FSFE country team the Netherlands runs 
  monthly online meetings. The team met in person in the Netherlands 
  Linux Users meeting, organised an FSFE booth in the NLLGG meeting in 
  Utrecht, and was present at the <a href="https://conference.publicspaces.net/session/open">Public Spaces 
  conference</a>. Overall, it is worth noting that <a href="/news/2021/news-20211123-01.html">the growth of the Dutch 
  community</a> was an iterative process based on learning and 
  feedback, according to one of the coordinators, Nico Rikken.
</p>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/Translators"><strong>Translators</strong></a>: 
  We want to abolish every barrier to software freedom, including the 
  linguistic one. Many volunteers in the FSFE translators team make our 
  message accessible to people across Europe. In August we published 
  the first pages translated into Turkish: our general page about <a href="/freesoftware/freesoftware.html">Free Software</a> and why <a href="/freesoftware/democracy.html">Democracy requires Free 
  Software</a>. The FSFE Translators team met to share advice on how to 
  translate the FSFE pages. The meeting offered instructions for using 
  Git and webpreview. At the end the participants played charades. 
  Overall in the last year we published 363 reports of news and events 
  in English and hundreds of translations. Among the most prominent 
  languages were Italian (306 pages), Dutch (160 pages), Spanish (92 
  pages), German (85 pages) and French (37 pages).
</p>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Vienna"><strong>Vienna</strong></a>: 
  The FSFE local group Vienna had an information booth at the 
  Veganmania street festival.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/Women">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/e76d2d56a7c9142524d227b9cf30c5ad.jpg" alt="Four women around a table with posters and stickers"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    First in-person meeting of FSFE Women. From left to right: 
    Francesca Indorado, Loria, Fani Partsafyllidou, Antje Kazimiers
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/Women"><strong>Women</strong></a>: 
  The FSFE Women team runs monthly online <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/Women/Notes">meetings</a>. This 
  year, the group met for the first time in person in Berlin. During 
  their regular meetings in June the team had an introduction to 
  content management systems, having three guests from CMS Garden. In 
  August, members of the group met at one of Germany’s largest 
  GNU/Linux conferences, FrOSCon in St. Augustin, and participated at 
  the FSFE booth.
</p>

<h2 id="technical-infrastructure"><span id="anchor-27"/>Our fully Free Software <span id="anchor-28"/>technical infrastructure </h2>

<p>
  The FSFE's technical infrastructure is in better shape than 
  ever before. It provides digital sovereignty and 
  privacy to our organisation, the FSFE's employees, and volunteers as 
  well as to other users of our services as we use <strong>fully Free 
  Software </strong>on our own bare metal servers. All services run in 
  some sort of virtualisation: <strong>43 virtual machines </strong>are 
  distributed over different data centres. We recently upgraded our 
  monitoring system, which is now based on Icinga2, using it for 51 
  hosts and 747 services that are continuously checked. This year we 
  enriched our technical infrastructure with three new features:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    We created ‘<a href="https://mehl.mx/blog/2022/docker2caddy-an-automatic-reverse-proxy-for-docker-containers/">Docker2Caddy</a>’ 
    a Python application for the FSFE infrastructure to automate 
    reverse proxies for Docker containers.
  </li>
  <li>
    We created our own <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/">Peertube 
    instance, media.fsfe.org</a>, to share our videos on a Free 
    Software platform.
  </li>
  <li>
    The FSFE officially opened the gates to its <a href="/news/2022/news-20220202-01.html">new Matrix server</a>. All 
    FSFE supporters and volunteers can create their own Matrix 
    accounts.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
  <strong>Knowledge sharing</strong>: We <a href="/news/2021/news-20211203-01.html">presented our technical 
  infrastructure in an article</a>. The article inspired other 
  organisations in the civil society to strive for similar goals as 
  dependencies on proprietary service providers are more and more 
  recognised as the severe problem they are. This is why we are 
  increasingly often asked to share our experiences, best practices, 
  and feedback. However, as for all technology, our infrastructure is 
  neither perfect nor complete. Our system administrators face a number 
  of interesting challenges that will keep them busy aside from the 
  routine tasks. We would like to thank them as well as the numerous 
  Free Software projects we depend on for their contributions to 
  software freedom!
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Accessibility</strong>: Our website consciously avoids 
  practices that hinder accessibility, but there is still room for 
  improvement. This year we improved our consistency in adding 
  alternative text for images, and added a specific reminder in Git 
  flagging each time a contributor fails to add alternative text.
</p>

<h2 id="movement"><span id="anchor-29"/><span id="anchor-30"/>Join the movement</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    “The FSFE is inclusive and puts the learning perspective at the 
    heart of its mission. So I hope it thrives for many years to come, 
    inspiring people like it inspired me. GNUtopia here we come!”
  </p>
  <cite>
    George Brooke-Smith, Risk Management specialist in KPMG. <a href="/news/2022/news-20220121-01.html">Interview</a> in January 
    2022.
  </cite>
</blockquote>

<p>
  The FSFE would be nothing without its contributors. And it would be 
  so much more with you! There are many ways you can <a href="/contribute/contribute.html">contribute</a>: <a href="https://my.fsfe.org/support">support us financially</a>, join a 
  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups">local group</a>, 
  participate in our <a href="/events/events.html">events</a> to meet 
  like-minded people. <a href="/contribute/translators/translators.html">Translate</a> our 
  articles, or offer <a href="/contribute/web/web.html">technical 
  support</a> to the organisation. <a href="/news/newsletter.html">Subscribe</a> to our Newsletter to stay 
  in touch.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Become a supporter:</strong> Advocating for freedom costs 
  money and we depend on people like you to <a href="https://my.fsfe.org/support">support us</a>. We guarantee that 
  all support is used to foster software freedom in Europe a little 
  more each day, step by step, bit by bit for the next decades.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/c0/20/bb69cfe1fef9c555804d27d49f33.png">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/f6/45/c7a2a121586b433090abfc21f859.JPG" alt="group of 14 people in front of modern building"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    FSFE Staff meeting at the SFSCon. From left to right: Matthias 
    Kirschner, Max Mehl, Marlene Kietreiber, Linus Sehn, Francesca 
    Indorato, Erik Albers, Linda Wagener, Alexander Sander, Gabriel Ku, 
    Lucas Lasota, Lina Ceballos, Fani Partsafyllidou, Niharika Singhal, 
    Bonnie Mehring. Bolzano, Italy, November 2021.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  With your help we can keep on defending software freedom. Thank you 
  for your trust, your support, and your ideas.
</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/d4/b6/e565f8b8ae949ded085d085cc3c7.png" alt="A photo of a booth, of a presentation, and of an audience with children"/>
    <link>/news/2022/news-20220928-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="annual-report">Annual report</tag>
  <tag key="sustainability">Sustainability</tag>
  <tag key="upcyclingandroid">Upcycling Android</tag>
  <tag key="pmpc">Public Money? Public Code!</tag>
  <tag key="AI">AI</tag>
  <tag key="routers">Router Freedom</tag>
  <tag key="deviceneutrality">Device Neutrality</tag>
  <tag key="licensing">licensing</tag>
  <tag key="legal">Legal Licensing Workshop</tag>
  <tag key="reuse">REUSE</tag>
  <tag key="yh4f">Youth Hacking 4 Freedom</tag>
  <tag key="ada-zangemann"/>
  <tag key="education">Education</tag>
  <tag key="podcast">Software Freedom Podcast</tag>
  <tag key="fosdem">FOSDEM</tag>
  <tag key="community">Community</tag>
  <tag key="localgroup">Local group</tag>
  <tag key="dk">Denmark</tag>
  <tag key="de">Germany</tag>
  <tag key="berlin">Berlin</tag>
  <tag key="hamburg-group">Hamburg group</tag>
  <tag key="it">Italy</tag>
  <tag key="nl">Netherlands</tag>
  <tag key="es">Spain</tag>
  <tag key="se">Sweden</tag>
  <tag key="ch">Switzerland</tag>
  <tag key="translations">Translators team</tag>
  <tag key="women-group">Women group</tag>
  <tag key="tech-teams">Technical teams</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/904"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
