<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-02-02">
    <title>Welcome to the Matrix: the FSFE now runs its own server</title>
    <body>
      <p>
  The FSFE is eager to support its community with diverse Free Software
  communication channels. We are happy to announce that we have recently added
  Matrix to this list. After successful beta tests, every FSFE supporter and
  volunteer can now create their own Matrix account. We will also use our
  instance for the FSFE’s virtual booth during FOSDEM!
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>Welcome to the Matrix: the FSFE now runs its own server</h1>

<p>
  The FSFE is eager to support its community with diverse Free Software
  communication channels. We are happy to announce that we have recently added
  Matrix to this list. After successful beta tests, every FSFE supporter and
  volunteer can now create their own Matrix account. We will also use our
  instance for the FSFE’s virtual booth during FOSDEM!
</p>

<p>
  For over a decade now, the FSFE has been offering an XMPP (also known as
  Jabber) server as well as a traditional IRC channel for <a href="/about/contact.html#community">our community</a> to quickly exchange messages.
  Today we officially open the gates to our new Matrix server, which has been
  successfully tested for a few months and has a few advantages over XMPP.
</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/ae0b688f41701e0dbf2212609f8565c5.png" alt="A computer screen with Matrix on it in a nice office space"/>
  <figcaption>
    Connect with the FSFE community at FOSDEM – from home!
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2>Federated and encrypted</h2>

<p>
  Matrix is a comparatively new protocol for real-time communication that
  enables federation similar to XMPP. Federation means that users of one
  instance can communicate with users of other instances over the same protocol.
  Matrix has some features directly built in, ranging from automatic encryption
  to sending pictures and the possibility of audio and video chats, or allowing
  responding to messages with emojis. With XMPP, some of these features are also
  available through extensions, but not all servers support all such additional
  features, which means that some users cannot benefit from them.
</p>

<p>
  Matrix is of course not perfect either, but meanwhile many Free Software
  organisations such as KDE and Mozilla as well as a number of public
  administrations use Matrix, for example the French state. And most
  importantly, the feedback from our test users and teams was very positive.
  That is why we now invite our community to make up their own mind about
  Matrix. For the time being, we will keep both Matrix and XMPP running so that
  individual users, groups, and teams can evaluate the technologies for
  themselves.
</p>

<h2>How to enter the Matrix</h2>

<p>
  For those who have an FSFE account - i.e. <fsfe-cd-donate-link>all
  supporters</fsfe-cd-donate-link> and registered volunteers - getting started is
  super easy. We provide a <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/TechDocs/Matrix">wiki
  page</a> where all the necessary information is collected. Due to the
  encryption features of the messenger, the first steps should be taken with
  some caution, but after that everything is quite self-explanatory.
</p>

<p>
  If you already have an account on a homeserver other than the FSFE's, you can
  of course keep it and still join our rooms. There are some recommendations
  listed in the FSFE space (<code>#fsfe:fsfe.org</code>), such as the main
  community room <code>#community:fsfe.org</code>. There is also a <a href="https://ems.element.io/tools/matrix-migration">service by the Matrix
  developers</a> to migrate one's account from one server to another if you'd like
  to make use of the fancy fsfe.org handle.
</p>

<p>
  A great way to experience Matrix on a grand scale is at the virtual FOSDEM
  this coming weekend, where the <a href="/news/2022/news-20220127-01.html">FSFE
  will once again have a devroom and a booth</a>. Participation and visiting is
  possible via distinct Matrix rooms. So get a Matrix account on our homeserver
  beforehand and join us at FOSDEM!
</p>

<p>
  <em>
    Like all FSFE services, this one is part of our <a href="/news/2021/news-20211203-01.html">Free Software infrastructure</a>
    with <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers/synapse/">public
    deployment code</a>. We would like to thank Michael Weimann, one of our
    System Hackers, who maintains the service.
  </em>
</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/ae0b688f41701e0dbf2212609f8565c5.png" alt="A computer screen with Matrix on it in a nice office space"/>
    <link>/news/2022/news-20220202-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="internal">FSFE Internal</tag>
  <tag key="tech-teams">Technical Teams</tag>
  <tag key="tools">Tools</tag>
  <tag key="fosdem">FOSDEM</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/797"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
