<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-01-12">
    <title>Public Money? Public Code! brochure is now available in Spanish</title>
    <body>
      <p>
	 A large part of our work is possible thanks to the contribution of 
	 our volunteers. This was not the exception. Our Public Money? 
	 Public Code! brochure is now translated into Spanish, and we 
	 hosted an event to share this great news with our community. 
	 GNUHealth, Pica Pica HackLab, Lliurex, Linkat, and KDE took 
	 part in our event. 
	 </p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>
	<h1>Public Money? Public Code! brochure is now available in Spanish </h1>

	 <p>
	 A large part of our work is possible thanks to the contribution of 
	 our volunteers. This was not the exception. Our Public Money? 
	 Public Code! brochure is now translated into Spanish, and we 
	 hosted an event to share this great news with our community. 
	 GNUHealth, Pica Pica HackLab, Lliurex, Linkat, and KDE took 
	 part in our event. 
	 </p>
	 
   <figure>
	   <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/696af56c4506ebc114f9cd7df21dac13.png" alt="Picture with panelists"/> 
	   </figure>

	 <p>
	 In the framework of our Public Money? Public Code! initiative, we 
	 have an exhaustive brochure dedicated to public administrations. 
	 It summarises the FSFE's long-term expertise with additional 
	 knowledge from leading experts in various ICT areas. It helps 
	 readers understand Free Software and its benefits for a modern 
	 digital public infrastructure. Hot topics covered include the 
	 avoidance of vendor lock-in, improvement of IT security through 
	 openness, exploring different business models, handling of 
	 procurement issues, and learning from innovative approaches to 
	 smart cities.
	</p>

	 <p>
	 Now, thanks to the work of our volunteers, <strong>this brochure is 
	 also available in <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/campaigns/pmpc/ES/FSFE_Policy_Brochure_PMPC_ALL_es.pdf">Spanish</a></strong>,
	 which means a broader audience that can read about the 
	 benefits of modernising public infrastructure with public code 
	 in their own language, and that is a highlight to us.
	</p>

	 <p>
	 To share this good news, we organised an event dedicated to 
	 our Spanish speaking community. We had the 
	 participation of experts such as Luis Falc칩n, founder of 
	 GNUHealth, Ricardo Mu침oz from Lliurex, Alexis Puente Montiel 
	 from Pica Pica HackLab, Francesc Busquets in representation of 
	 Linkat, and Aleix Pol Gonzalez, president of KDE. Our 
	 speakers and panelist also had the chance to discuss the 
	 challenges that still lie ahead for Free Software in the 
	 public sector with a special focus on Spain. 
	</p>
	
	<p>
	Do not worry if you could not participate; we have recorded our 
	sessions and the videos are now available.
	</p>

	<h2 id="public-money-public-code-initiative-and-translation-process-">Public Money? Public Code! and the importance of a new translation</h2>

	<p>
	FSFE Project Manager Lina Ceballos gave an introduction to 
	our Public Money? Public Code! initiative which requires Free 
	Software as the standard for all publicly financed software. Lina 
	also shared how important is for our community to be able to read 
	this brochure in their own languages, and encouraged others to join 
	us. Video in Spanish.
	</p>
	
	<video preload="none" poster="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/introductiontalk.jpg" controls="controls" width="100%"> <source src="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/introductiontalk.mp4" type="video/mp4; codecs=&quot;avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2&quot;"/> </video>  
	
	<h2 id="gnuhealth-">GNUHealth</h2> 
	
	<p>
	Dr. Luis Falc칩n is a Spanish physician, scientist, and activist. 
	He is the founder of GNU Solidario, a non-profit humanitarian 
	organisation focused on Social Medicine. Luis is the author of 
	GNU Health, the award-winning Free Health and Hospital 
	Information System. In our event, he talked about GNU Health 
	and the importance of Free Software in Public Health regarding 
	data privacy, technological sovereignty, and equity of access to 
	health services. Video in Spanish.
	</p>
	
	<video preload="none" poster="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview1_gnuhealth.jpg" controls="controls" width="100%"> <source src="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview1_gnuhealth.mp4" type="video/mp4; codecs=&quot;avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2&quot;"/> </video>   
	
	<h2 id="lliurex-">Lliurex</h2> 
	
	<p>
	Ricardo Mu침oz, who is the coordinator of the Lliurex project, 
	is a Telecommunications Engineer, a teacher, and now he is part 
	of the team of the Computer Service for Educational Centres of 
	the Regional Ministry (SICE) of Valencia as a Technical 
	Teaching Advisor (ATD). Ricardo told us a bit more about the 
	history, challenges, and the values that Lliurex offers to the 
	education sector but also to the Free Software ecosystem. 
	Video in Spanish.
	</p>
	
	<video preload="none" poster="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview2_lliurex.jpg" controls="controls" width="100%"> <source src="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview2_lliurex.mp4" type="video/mp4; codecs=&quot;avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2&quot;"/> </video>   
	
	<h2 id="linkat-">Linkat</h2> 
	
	<p>
	Francesc Busquets is part of the Unit of infrastructures, Free 
	Software, and online services of the Digital Culture Area of the 
	Department of Education of the Generalitat de Catalunya. He talked 
	about Linkat, a Free Software solution used for over 15 years in 
	some of the schools in the Catalonian community, highlighting the 
	ethical values of Linkat. Video in Spanish.
	</p>
	
	<video preload="none" poster="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview3_linkat.jpg" controls="controls" width="100%"> <source src="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview3_linkat.mp4" type="video/mp4; codecs=&quot;avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2&quot;"/> </video> 
	
	 <h2 id="pica-pica-hacklab-">Pica Pica HackLab</h2> 
	 
	 <p>
	 Alexis Puente Montiel is the founder and coordinator of Pica Pica 
	 HackLab (PicaHack), a HackLab that managed to <a href="/news/2019/news-20190514-01.html">convince 
	 the parliament of Asturias to support our campaign Public Money? 
	 Public Code!</a>, being the first parliament in Spain to do so. He 
	 told us about this experience and what is needed to achieve 
	 such goals. Video in Spanish.
	 </p>
	 
	 <video preload="none" poster="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview4_picapica.jpg" controls="controls" width="100%"> <source src="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview4_picapica.mp4" type="video/mp4; codecs=&quot;avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2&quot;"/> </video> 
	 
	 <h2 id="panel-">Panel</h2> 
	 
	 <p>
	 The already mentioned speakers with the addition of Aleix Pol 
	 Gonzalez - developer and current President of KDE e.V. and founder 
	 of Barcelona Free Software - discussed some of the challenges that 
	 they face in their everyday work for software freedom and what is 
	 needed to overcome them. The panel was moderated by Lina Ceballos 
	 - FSFE Project Manager. Video in Spanish.
	 </p>
	 
	  <video preload="none" poster="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview5_panel.jpg" controls="controls" width="100%"> <source src="https://download.fsfe.org/videos/pmpc/ES%20PMPC%20Brochure%20event/interview5_panel.mp4" type="video/mp4; codecs=&quot;avc1.42E01E, mp4a.40.2&quot;"/> </video>   
	  
	 <p>
	 Remember that you can take action as well by joining our <a href="https://publiccode.eu/">campaign</a>, distributing our <a href="/activities/publiccode/brochure">brochure</a>, 
	 and <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Activities/ContactingAdministrationsForPMPC">convincing 
	 your local administration</a> to use Free Software. 
	 </p>
 
</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/696af56c4506ebc114f9cd7df21dac13.png" alt="Picture with panelists"/>
    <link>/news/2022/news-20220112-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="pmpc">Public Money? Public Code!</tag>
  <tag key="public-administration">Public Administration</tag>
  <tag key="procurement">Public Procurement</tag>
  <tag key="es">Spain</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/790"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
