<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2024-01-22">
    <title>The FSFE partners with the Edulife Foundation to introduce Italian students to Free Software</title>
    <body>
      <p>In the framework of the ITS Academy LAST project, the Free Software Foundation Europe and the Edulife Foundation, the operational partner of ITS Academy LAST, have developed a two-year agreement to deliver educational content to students about Free Software legal aspects, policy and public awareness.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>The FSFE partners with the Edulife Foundation to introduce Italian students to Free Software</h1>

<p>In the framework of the ITS Academy LAST project, the Free Software Foundation Europe and the Edulife Foundation, the operational partner of ITS Academy LAST, have developed a two-year agreement to deliver educational content to students about Free Software legal aspects, policy and public awareness.</p>

<figure>
	<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/d0/7a/a24df523825e9c9c27b181b18554.jpg" alt="Image of the kick off during SFSCON23 showing the students group with the FSFE staffers"/>
</figure>

<p>During <a href="https://sfscon.it">SFSCon 2023</a>, the FSFE and <a href="https://www.fondazioneedulife.org/">Edulife Foundation</a> kicked off a collaboration project to raise awareness about the benefits of Free Software to the next generation of innovators. The educational initiative aims to expose the students to Free Software, so they can positively contribute to how technology is developed. More than 50 students of the ITS Academy LAST were able to attend the kick-off at SFSCon, having the opportunity to listen to talks about Free Software as well as engage in discussions with experts from the FSFE and other speakers and enthusiasts.</p>

<p>For more than 20 years, the Edulife Research Foundation has been working to guide local students and educators in Italy towards the realisation of their professional and personal life goals. One the leading initiative is the <a href="https://www.olos311.org">“Observatory and Laboratory for Free Software”</a>. Antonio Faccioli, the scientific coordinator of the digital courses of the ITS Academy LAST, and a Free Software enthusiast, was the idealizer of this partnership.</p>

<p>This partnership represents an important step for the FSFE to engage with students and	educational communities in Italy. It is important to convey to next generation of professionals the message of Free Software, especially in broader contexts the mean of technology in a democratic society.</p>


<h3>The IT Free Software Knowledge Project</h3>
<p>Known as “IT Free Software Knowledge Project”, this two-year partnership started in November 2023. As part of this studies academic program, the FSFE has delivered educational content about Free Software, with a focus on Free Software legal issues, policy aspects and public awareness in the form of lectures. Besides, the students attended Free Software conferences, such as the <a href="sfscon.it/">SFSCon</a>, where they will be able to have a more practical approach and the opportunity to get in touch with leading experts of the Free Software world.</p>

<p>Should you want to receive further information on the IT Free Software Knowledge Project do not hesitate to get in touch with us at <email>contact@fsfe.org</email>. We are always on the look out for partners who share the same goals to foster a culture of Free Software on the territory. If you want to share a project idea please do not hesitate to contact us.</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/d0/7a/a24df523825e9c9c27b181b18554.jpg" alt="Image of the kick off during SFSCON23 showing the students group with the FSFE staffers"/>
    <link>/news/2024/news-20240122-01.html</link>
    <tags>
	<tag key="front-page"/>
	<tag key="it">Italy</tag>
	<tag key="education">Education</tag>
	<tag key="sfscon">SFSCon</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
