<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2024-03-01">
    <title>FOSDEM 2024 was a blast!</title>
    <body>
      <p>
At the beginning of February, FSFE volunteers and staffers went back to 
Brussels to take part in FOSDEM 2024 with a booth and talks. While for 
some of us this has become an awesome yearly experience, it was the 
first time for others. Thanks to everyone who came to FOSDEM, visited 
our booth for a nice chat, and joined us during our social events!
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>FOSDEM 2024 was a blast!</h1>

<p>
At the beginning of February, FSFE volunteers and staffers went back to 
Brussels to take part in FOSDEM 2024 with a booth and talks. While for 
some of us this has become an awesome yearly experience, it was the 
first time for others. Thanks to everyone who came to FOSDEM, visited 
our booth for a nice chat, and joined us during our social events!
</p>

<figure>
	<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/f4/77/c0dc9a85f12e912c90380098daaa.jpg" alt="Smiling FSFE team members and volunteers in the FSFE booth at FOSDEM 2024"/>
	<figcaption>Our team and volunteers at our FOSDEM 2024 booth!</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
For many members of our community, FOSDEM marks the beginning of the 
annual Free Software conferences. It is also one of the largest 
conferences on Software Freedom, so as a Free Software enthusiast it is 
one of the places to be.
</p>
<p>
While most of our staff and volunteers have marked the first weekend of 
February in their calendars for years, some FSFE members attended for 
the first time. We asked one of them, <a href="https://tommi.space/" title="Tommi’s personal website">Tommi</a>, a Free Software enthusiast 
and FSFE intern, about his first FOSDEM experience.
</p>

<blockquote>
	<p>“When I was asked to go to FOSDEM, my answer was <q>of course!</q> 
	So, a couple of weeks ago, I caught a train to Brussels and took part in 
	the first FOSDEM of my life. It won’t be the last one.</p>
	<p>It is hard to explain how incredible an experience it was to 
	attend the conference. What struck me the most was to finally give a 
	face and an identity to usernames contributing to Free 
	Software. Up to FOSDEM, I personally met only a few people directly 
	involved in the universe of open technologies that I have been 
	following in the past few years. FOSDEM gave me the opportunity to 
	finally have a face-to-face conversation with a lot of developers and 
	members of the Free Software community, and I expressed my gratitude to 
	them.</p>
	<p>Both by standing at our booth and by wandering around, I could 
	not help but feel surrounded by like-minded people who believe in the 
	importance of Software Freedom, and more broadly in technology 
	developed by the people for the people. I chatted face-to-face with 
	developers and maintainers of projects whose existence literally 
	changed my life, and all this happened in a self-organized and 
	volunteer-led environment, making it even more interesting and 
	captivating. Of course, there was also time to attend really 
	interesting talks, and I had the chance to listen to my colleagues in 
	front of an audience. It was also great to have the chance to meet a 
	lot of FSFE volunteers and engage in interesting discussions with them 
	during our social events.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>
For this year, we had a booth at FOSDEM with <a href="/contribute/spreadtheword.html">promotion material</a> and <a href="/order/index.html">merchandising</a>. Thanks to everyone who gave 
us a hand there!
</p>

<p>
If you missed FOSDEM or didn’t have time to attend all of our 
sessions, don’t worry! Have a look at the devrooms we co-organized 
this year and took part in, so that you can learn something new, deepen your 
knowledge, and improve your Free Software skills.
</p>

<figure>
	<peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/aQs7EbEUQGt4DP13SsqAJ7"/>
	<figcaption><a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/aQs7EbEUQGt4DP13SsqAJ7">Legal and Policy issues Devroom</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
	<peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/9anGpCP2t8355qd3aUyQhC"/>
	<figcaption><a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/9anGpCP2t8355qd3aUyQhC">CRA &amp; PLD: Free Software in the European legislative landscape</a>, the first of four parts of the <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/p/xoLLMjgsgDFdcVNBwKyn3m">EU policy devroom</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
	<peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/thWtSBLxNRRAkiiMPamjdg"/>
	<figcaption><a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/thWtSBLxNRRAkiiMPamjdg">Codes Bound by Ethics: The Rising Tide of Non-Free Software Licenses in AI ecosystems</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
<peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/8GSutX7VcnGtMiqm3Ng96m"/>
<figcaption><a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/8GSutX7VcnGtMiqm3Ng96m">Presenting Youth Hacking 4 Freedom, FSFE programming competition for European teenagers</a></figcaption>
</figure>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/f4/77/c0dc9a85f12e912c90380098daaa.jpg" alt="Smiling FSFE team members and volunteers at the FSFE booth at FOSDEM 2024"/>
    <link>/news/2024/news-20240301-01.html</link>
    <tags>
	<tag key="front-page"/>
	<tag key="fosdem">FOSDEM</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1134"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
