<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2025-02-14T16:00:00Z" end="2025-02-14T22:00:00Z">
        <title>I love Free Software Day - Carinthia in Villach, Austria</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url/>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>We often underestimate the power of a simple thank you. Everyone who contributes to or supports free software does valuable work for our society and deserves to be recognised.
      ‘I Love Free Software Day’ on 14 February is an opportunity to show your gratitude with a “Thank you for being part of free software!”. On ‘I Love Free Software Day’, we create 
      a day that recognises and appreciates all this volunteer work by saying ‘Thank you ♥’ to all the people behind the free software projects and those who are committed to it. With a 
      simple thank you on 14 February, we show that we appreciate the efforts of the contributors to free software.</p>
      <p>We will celebrate together with you at <a href="https://www.carinthianlinuxday.at/">HTBLuVA Villach</a>, Tschinowitscher Weg 5, 9500 Villach, Austria, from 16:00 (CET) till 22:00 (CET).<br/>
            Free Software is not just any kind of software: it represents a community. Free Software empowers us to use, understand, share, and improve the software. 
            Let’s build a community for Free Software together — a community that values and welcomes each other — by celebrating the software that empowers us. That is why you’re invited 
            to join our event the “I ♥ Free Software Day - Carinthia”. We’ll host a small installation party featuring F-Droid, Linux, and more, we express our thanks to maintainers, and 
            enjoy good coffee and cake together. It’s the perfect setting to chat about Free Software topics and also to install some! :)</p>
    </body>

    <link>https://www.carinthianlinuxday.at/</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="at">Austria</tag>
            <tag key="meeting"/>
            <tag key="ilovefs">I Love Free Software Day</tag>
            <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
