<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2025-11-15T14:00:00Z" end="2025-11-15T16:00:00Z">
        <title>Lettura e creatività con Ada &amp; Zangemann in Nembro, Italia</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>📖 A new educational activity with Ada &amp; Zangemann is coming to Nembro (Bergamo - Italy). Join us for an afternoon of reading followed by a workshop on making and technology! The event will be held at the “Tullio Carrara” Cultural Center in Nembro* on November 15, 2025, starting at 3:00 p.m.</p>
     <p>The activity is aimed at children aged 6 to 10 accompanied by an adult and it is part of a wider range of initiatives promoted by BgLUG and the FSFE to disseminate and promote Free Software.</p>
     <p>Admission is free, reservations required (at the library or online).</p>
     <p>📖 About the book: The famous inventor Zangemann lives in a large villa above the city. Both adults and children love his inventions and desperately want to have them. But then something happens: Zangemann wants to see his inventions up close once again and so he goes for a walk in the city when, with a loud thud, a child hits him on the shins with his skateboard. Ouch! Enraged, the inventor makes a drastic decision... But Ada, a bright girl, understands what is happening. Together with her friends, she devises a plan. This illustrated children&#039;s book tells the story of the famous inventor Zangemann and Ada, a curious and enterprising girl. Ada begins experimenting with hardware and software and, in the process, realizes how important it is to control technology, for herself and for others. A book that stimulates children&#039;s interest in experimentation and encourages them to shape technology. For ages 6 to 106.</p>
     </body>

    <link>https://bglug.it/it/eventi/2025/11/ada-zangemann-nembro-novembre-2025/</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="it">
          Italia      </tag>
            <tag key="meeting"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
