<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2025-12-27T09:00:00Z" end="2025-12-30T15:30:00Z">
        <title>FSFE at the 39C3 in Hamburg, Germany</title>
    <group>
     <name></name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>It is this time of the year already, the FSFE will be at the 39C3 Together with over 10.000 people and many civil organisations will we be at the 39C3. We have a booth in hall H at the <a href="https://events.ccc.de/congress/2025/hub/en/assembly/detail/bitsundbaeume_aboutfreedom">Bits and Bäume Assembly</a>. But of course we will also be there with talks, workshops and meet-ups! Come and join us:</p>
<p>
<ul>
<li> <strong>27.12.2025, 16:00 - 16:45</strong>: We will also be part of a <a href="https://pretalx.c3voc.de/39c3-sendezentrum/talk/Y99YJ7/">podcast by c&#039;t uplink</a> about digital sovereignty on the first day in the Sendezentrum, with Bonnie Mehring.</li>
<li> <strong> 28.12.2025, 11:00 - 11:50</strong>: REUSE Workshop on the reuse licensing tool with Tobias Diekershoff</li>
<li> <strong>29.12.2025, 13:00 - 13:40</strong>: FSFE Insights with Ana Galán</li>
<li> <strong> 29.12.2025, 14:00 - 14:50</strong>: Digital Markets Act (DMA) - Q &amp; A. Come over, sit down and talk about the Digital Markets Act with our expert Dario Persutti</li>
<li> <strong>29.12.2025, 15:00 - 15:55</strong>: Was hat das Fediverse eigentlich zu bieten wenn Datenschutz und Digitale Souveränität egal sind? with Tobias Diekershoff</li>
<li> <strong>30.12.2025, 10:00 - 11:30</strong>: <a href="https://events.ccc.de/congress/2025/hub/en/event/detail/ada-und-zangemann">Ada und Zangemann</a> reading (DE) with an additional workshop after the reading. In the workshop the participants will write a letter to Ada or Zangemann and reflect on the story they just heard, with Bonnie Mehring</li>
<li> <strong>30.12.2025, 12:00 - 12:50 </strong>: <a href="https://events.ccc.de/congress/2025/hub/en/event/detail/fsfe-meetup-at-bits-baume-habitat">FSFE meetup at Bits &amp; Bäume Habitat</a>, for all FSFE volunteers and those who would like to become one, with Ana Galan and Tobias Diekershoff</li>
<li> <strong> 30.12.2025, 13:00 - 13:40</strong>: Running a NGO on FLOSS with Tobias Diekershoff</li>
</ul>
</p>
    <p>The FSFE will be there from 27 to 30 December and we are more than happy to say hi to you. So, come and visit us in the hall H with the Bits &amp; Bäume assembly.</p>
     <p></p>
    </body>

    <link>https://events.ccc.de/congress/2025/hub/en/assembly/detail/fsfe</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="de">
          Germany      </tag>
            <tag key="talk"/>
<tag key="infobooth"/>
<tag key="localgroup"/>
<tag key="meeting"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
