<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2025-05-22T08:00:00Z" end="2025-05-23T19:00:00Z">
        <title>DORS/CLUC : Keynote from Matthias Kirchsner  and FSFE booth in Zagreb, Croatia</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>Matthias Kirschner, President of the FSFE, will deliver a keynote at DORS/CLUC titled 'A Vision for Software Freedom in 2048'.</p>
     <p>Our litigation against Apple in front of the European Court of Justice, fighting for sustainable long term funding in the EU and member states, “Public Money? Public Code!”, Device Neutrality, Router Freedom, Free Your Android, assistance with licensing questions, Youth Hacking 4 Freedom, and a tale of software, skateboards, and raspberry ice cream. These are some of the activities by the Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE), which has been working since 2001 to empower users to control technology.</p>
     <p>Recently we discussed how the world would look like in our area in 2048, if the FSFE has been successful. In this talk Matthias would like to share those thoughts with you and during the conference get your feedback on the next decades of our work for software freedom.</p>  
     <p>There will also be an FSFE booth with information materials and merchandise. Come by to say hi and join us for engaging discussions about software freedom!</p>
     <p>TBC- we are also trying to help to organize a small FSF40 get-together during DORS/CLUC. If you are interested to join, reach out!</p>
     <p>--------<br />
DORS/CLUC is a conference in Croatia that covers Free Software topics. DORS/CLUC has brought together individuals and companies from the Free Software community.  This year, celebrating its 30 anniversary, the conference will take place on 22 and 23 May at the University Algebra, Zagreb.</p>
    </body>

    <link>https://www.dorscluc.org/person/matthias-kirschner/</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="hr">
          Croatia      </tag>
            <tag key="talk"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
