<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2025-02-12T17:00:00Z" end="2025-02-12T19:00:00Z">
        <title>&quot;Free/Libre software and freedom in the digital society&quot; (online)</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>The seminar, organized by the Nexa Center for Internet &amp; Society of the DAUIN - Polytechnic of Turin, will be held by Dr. RICHARD STALLMAN (Founder of the Free Software Foundation and Founder and development leader of the GNU operating system), with formal greetings from the Vice-Rector of the Polytechnic of Turin, Prof. Stefano Sacchi.</p>
     <p>The event will take place on Wednesday 12 February at 5 pm, at the Aula 27 of the Polytechnic of Turin (Corso Castelfidardo 39, TO, Italy).</p>
     <p>Here is the abstract for the talk:<br />
&quot;There are many threats to freedom in the digital society. They include nonfree software, massive surveillance, and censorship.</p>
     <p>Nonfree programs are often designed to restrict users, control users or manipulate uesers. The War on Sharing aims to stop users from sharing copies of published works.  Computers for voting make election results untrustworthy.</p>
     <p>Other threats come from use of web services, implemented by companies that can impose any conditions whatsoever.</p>
     <p>Finally, most internet activities (aside from those which existed before 2000) are precarious, dependent on permission from one company.</p>
     <p>All of these threats originate more or less in the use of nonfree software. That is why free software is the first battle in the liberation of the digital society.&quot;</p>
     <p>The seminar is open to anyone, free of charge, and will be held in english. It will be possible to attend in-person or online, connecting to the University&#039;s Virtual Classroom (no registration needed): https://didattica.polito.it/VClass/NexaEvent</p>
     <p>Further details are available at the following link: https://nexa.polito.it/mercoledi-180</p>
    </body>

    
    <tags>
            <tag key="workshop"/>
<tag key="meeting"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
