<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2025-11-05T18:00:00Z" end="2025-11-05T19:30:00Z">
        <title>End of life for Windows 10? It&#039;s time to try Linux! in Milan, Italia</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>Invitation to Milano, Thursday, 23 October, 2025</p>
     <p>With the end of support for Windows 10 (October 2025), many users and businesses are faced with the decision to discard good PCs or migrate to Windows 11, but not all PCs are compatible.</p>
     <p>Introduction:</p>
     <p>- Marta Andreoli of FSFE Free Software Foundation Europe</p>
     <p>Two professionals working with Linux:</p>
     <p>- Marco Crotta, info@blockchaincaffe.it<br />
- Valentino Spataro, info@caffe20.it</p>
     <p>Together:</p>
     <p>We will discuss it.refund4freedom.org for refunding the cost of Windows from new PCs.</p>
     <p>We will show yout:<br />
- how a PC with Linux works,<br />
- start Linux on your PCs (live or dual boot)</p>
     <p>The relators, Linux experts, organize a practical event on Thursday, October 23, 2025 (18:00-20:00) at the Biblioteca Lambrate in Milano.</p>
     <p>&quot;Working with an old PC? Normal with Linux!&quot;</p>
     <p>During the meeting, the experts will show Linux and how to use it on your laptops.</p>
     <p>Participants must bring:</p>
     <p>- Their own laptop loaded<br />
- A USB flash drive.<br />
- With this, they will transform outdated hardware into a fast PC. The experts will show how Linux offers stability, security, and efficiency, even on outdated PCs.</p>
     <p>IMPORTANT: Make a backup of all your data on an external disk (leave it at home), and also of emails, configurations, passwords, and software licenses on your PC. We will show you how to start live without modifying the PC, but if you want to install it, you must have all the data copied.</p>
     <p>The event is free but requires registration (few places available). Transportation is facilitated by the M2 Metro Lambrate station and the tram lines 19, 33, and bus 54.</p>
     <p>&quot;Let&#039;s Get Together with Linux&quot; is an invitation to discover the potential of open source to reduce costs, extend the life of hardware, and ensure operational continuity.</p>
     <p>What to Bring:</p>
     <p>- Your old laptop (loaded)<br />
- A USB drive (minimum 8GB)</p>
     <p>Why to participate:</p>
     <p>- Learn why the internet works on Linux servers more than Windows<br />
- Learn to extend the life of your computer<br />
- Discover how similar it is to Windows, but better in every detail<br />
- Reduce costs using free and open-source software<br />
- Connect with a passionate and available community</p>
     <p>Summary:</p>
     <p>Finished Windows 10? Let&#039;s Get Together with Linux!</p>
     <p>Marco Crotta - info@blockchaincaffe.it<br />
Valentino Spataro - info@caffe20.it</p>
     <p>Event Information:</p>
     <p>Date: Thursday, October 23, 2025<br />
Time: 18:00-20:00</p>
     <p>Location: Biblioteca Lambrate, Via C. Valvassori Peroni 56, Milano<br />
Metro: M2 Lambrate - Tram: 19, 33 - Bus: 54<br />
Admission: Free, mandatory registration (limited spots)<br />
</p>
    </body>

    <link>https://caffe20.it/linux</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="it">
          Italia      </tag>
            <tag key="workshop"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
