<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2025-01-17T00:00:00Z" end="2024-12-21T00:00:00Z">
        <title>https://www.pistoiaalliance.org/events/submit-an-event/ in UAE, United Arab Emirates</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>With this message and on behalf of the Organizing Committee, I invite you to attend and actively participate in this important international gathering. 12 World Digital Pathology &amp; AI UCGCongress from December 17-19, 2024 in Dubai, UAE.<br />
The purpose of the UCGConference is to encourage the national and international exchange of ideas between academic, corporate, industrial and government researchers. In addition to sharing knowledge, this conference provides a chance for professional networking, particularly for recent graduates, postdoctoral researchers, and individuals in the early stages of their careers.<br />
Since the previous year's conference was a great success, people from all over the world are expected to attend this year's event. The esteemed speakers come from both the world's most prestigious academic institutions and the most successful Diagnostics companies. This conference will offer the chance to discuss difficult problems in the Digital Pathology domains, including Digital Pathology, Artificial Intelligence in Digital Pathology, Machine Learning and AI, Computational Pathology, and others, as well as the practical aspects of the subject. The conference this year will take place in Dubai, UAE, a city with significant historical significance UAE and the world.<br />
There will be well-known, renowned speakers from around the world who will share, debate, and analyze important new discoveries and scientific advancements that will affect clinical trials and related fields in the future.<br />
Why Dubai, UAE. <br />
The United Arab Emirates' Dubai is a city and emirate that is well-known for its upscale shopping malls, avant-garde architecture, and vibrant nightlife. The skyline dotted with skyscrapers is dominated by the 830-meter-tall Burj Khalifa tower. At its base is the Dubai Fountain, with its lights and jets that sync to music. Since the turn of the 20th century<br />
Meet Our Speaker and Organizing Committee Member<br />
Dr. Zev Leifer: US President<br />
Dr. Anil Parwani: Professor and Vice Chair Pathology<br />
Dr. David J. Shulkin: Ninth Secretary, US Department of Veterans Affairs<br />
Dr. Anil Berger: VP Sales &amp; Marketing at Mindpeak GmbH<br />
Mr. Troy Bankhead: Director of European Operations &amp; Vice President of Marketing<br />
Dr. Michael Retsky: Hon Associate Prof at University College London<br />
Dr. Mustafa Yousif: Director of Digital Pathology at Michigan Medicine<br />
Dr. Eric Ibegbu: Medical Director and CEO at Atlantic Medical Group<br />
Ms. Ariadna Maso: Founder &amp; CEO SANNO<br />
Dr. Lewis Hassell: University of Oklahoma<br />
Kindly find the previous editions' speakers and committee member here https://digitalpathology.utilitarianconferences.com/scientific-committee<br />
Call for Paper:<br />
Call for Abstracts is now open for the 12th World Digital Pathology &amp; AI UCGCongress, scheduled from December 17-19, 2024 in Dubai, UAE., We invite researchers, academicians, professionals, and industry experts to contribute and share their knowledge, experiences, and research<br />
Save the dates, December 17-19, 2024. Start preparing your abstracts, and poster and don’t forget to tell your colleagues – this is going to be the best Pathologists’ conference ever! We hope that you will have a productive and fun-filled time at the 12th World Digital Pathology &amp; AI UCGCongress  Our Best Regards<br />
Conference Key Sessions:<br />
Track 1: Digital Pathology<br />
Track 2: Medical Imaging Digital Pathology<br />
Track 3: Artificial Intelligence in Digital Pathology<br />
Track 4: Computational Pathology<br />
Track 5: Pathology with Technology<br />
Track 6: Digital Pathology in COVID-19<br />
Track 7: Machine Learning and AI<br />
Track 8: Diagnostics Digital Pathology<br />
Track 9: Digital Surgical Pathology<br />
Track 10: Digital Pathology Solutions<br />
Track 11: Pathology Informatics<br />
Track 12: Digital Histopathology<br />
For more tracks/sessions please visit here: https://digitalpathology.utilitarianconferences.com/submit-abstract<br />
Target Audience: <br />
Digital Pathologists, pathologist, Neurologist, Surgeons, Cytopathologists, Clinical and academic, dermatologists, residents, Dermatopathologists, Gynecologists, Lecturers. CTOs, VPs, Directors, Senior Managers, Scientists, Doctors, Chief officers, Professors, Anatomic Pathologist, Product Managers. Digital Pathologists, Neurologist, Surgeons, Cytopathologists, Clinical and academic, residents, fellows, Anatomic Pathologist, Biomedical Researchers, Healthcare Providers, Medical Technologists, IT Professionals, Industry Experts and Vendors, Regulators and Policy Makers, Academics and Educators, Surgeons, Hospital Administrators, Telemedicine Professionals, Educators, Software Developers, Pharmaceutical Companies, Health Policy Experts, Legal Professionals, Venture Capitalists and Investors, Market Analysts, Educational Institutions, Patient Advocacy Groups, Medical Device Manufacturers.</p>
     <p>Conference Benefits:</p>
     <p>21 CME Hours<br />
21 CPD Hours<br />
Live Sessions<br />
One on one meet with Experts and Investors on Demand<br />
A showcase of new Products<br />
Certification of Recognition<br />
Industrial Exhibitions<br />
Meet your Academic idols<br />
Hear about the latest research<br />
Engage in High-level debates &amp; Q/A<br />
Networking for future collaboration<br />
Publication of abstracts on our Website<br />
Add Research Value<br />
Employment Bureau<br />
Networking Sessions</p>
     <p>What is CME/CPD?<br />
CME stands for Continuing Medical Education. It refers to the educational activities that help medical professionals maintain competence and learn about new and developing areas of their field. These activities are often required for doctors, nurses, and other healthcare providers to renew their licenses and certifications. CME activities can include conferences, workshops, online courses, and other forms of professional development.</p>
     <p>CPD stands for Continuing Professional Development. It is a broader concept than CME and refers to the ongoing process of learning, developing, and maintaining skills and knowledge throughout one's professional career, regardless of the industry. CPD activities can include formal education like courses and workshops, as well as informal learning like self-study, mentoring, and attending conferences.</p>
     <p>In healthcare, CPD encompasses CME but also includes other areas of professional growth, such as leadership skills, communication, and ethics. It is designed to ensure that professionals continue to develop their expertise and stay updated with the latest advancements in their field.<br />
Book Now: https://digitalpathology.utilitarianconferences.com/accreditation-registration</p>
     <p>EPUCG- SUPPORTING JOURNALS<br />
Unified Citation Journals is a platform for the latest discoveries in Technology, Science, engineering, medicine, medical clinical, and advancing discoveries and health. We at Unified Citation Journals ensure the advancement of healthcare and improve performance for the benefit of humanity.<br />
Learn More: https://ucjournals.com/</p>
     <p>Important Information:<br />
Conference Name: 12th World Digital Pathology &amp; AI UCGCongress<br />
Short Name: 12DIGIPATH2024<br />
Dates: December 17-19, 2024<br />
Venue: Dubai, UAE<br />
Scientific Program: It will only include plenary speakers, keynote speakers, panel discussions and presentations in parallel sessions.<br />
Audience: Global Leaders, Industrialists, Business Delegates, Students, Entrepreneurs, Executives<br />
Email:  info@utilitarianconferences.com i <br />
Visit: https://digitalpathology.utilitarianconferences.com<br />
Call for Papers: https://digitalpathology.utilitarianconferences.com/submit-abstract <br />
Register here: https://digitalpathology.utilitarianconferences.com/registration<br />
Call Us: +442033222718<br />
WhatsApp Us: +442033222718 info-ucg@utilitarianconferences.com<br />
Connect With Us: <br />
Url: https://digitalpathology.utilitarianconferences.com/<br />
Email:  info@utilitarianconferences.com i <br />
Twitter: https://twitter.com/DrKhadijaAlAmi1<br />
Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=100081763194551<br />
Pinterest:https://in.pinterest.com/DigitalpathologyUCGConferences/<br />
Tumbler: :https://www.tumblr.com/blog/digitalpathlogyucgconferences<br />
YouTube: https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCS1TFe3nzRlREovQIjYMPkg</p>
     <p>Community: Utilitarian Conferences Gathering<br />
Utilitarian Conferences Gathering offers a wide range of events, Meetings, Conferences, Workshops, symposiums. We have a dedicated team who are aimed at acquiring the technologies, adopting the knowledge of business needs, and accelerate with the best ideas and strategies. Utilitarian Conferences Gathering is a pioneer in the area of Event Management, Collaboration. We are a full-service event provider specializing in the field of Medical, Clinical, Healthcare, Life Sciences, Engineering, Pharma, Environmental Science, Engineering, Business, Agricultural, and Food event services for Academic and Industrial Sectors. We stand out distinctively from our competitors for our commitment to quality, round-the-clock service, and unmatched price. We are able to provide you with the best event, Meeting experience under one roof. We at Utilitarian Conferences Gathering make sure that you as a client choose the most appropriate event.<br />
More Information: https://utilitarianconferences.com/<br />
LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/company/ucg-utilitarian-conferences-gathering/<br />
Email: info@utilitarianconferences.com<br />
Twitter:  https://twitter.com/UCGConferences<br />
Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/Utilitarian-Conferences-Gathering-102364354933420</p>
     <p></p>
    </body>

    <link>https://digitalpathology.utilitarianconferences.com/dr--homagni-sikha-roy</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="ae">
          United Arab Emirates      </tag>
            <tag key="localgroup"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
