<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2025-10-25T13:00:00Z" end="2025-10-09T18:00:00Z">
        <title>Linux Day 2025 @Fermo in Fermo, Italia</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>Anche quest&#039;anno torna il Linux Day a Fermo, il 25 ottobre, organizzato da FermoLUG.</p>
     <p>Parleremo di open software, software libero, IA, ambiente e tecnologia.<br />
E di Linux, ovviamente.</p>
     <p>Gli appuntamenti fissati per il pomeriggio del 25 ottobre sono:</p>
     <p>15:00 Openwashing nelle AI  @Aldo Giambuzzi</p>
     <p>16:00 Surprise speech  @Alessandro Iena</p>
     <p>17:00 Non solo blink: MicroPython e Bluetooth LE @Giacomo Vallorani</p>
     <p>18:00 Ambiente &amp; IA @Federico Massi</p>
     <p>19:00 OpenPGP e Crittografia @Francesco Valentini</p>
     <p>Sarà possibile approfondire con i relatori al termine del talk. Inoltre saranno presenti laboratori, un&#039;area per toccare con mano Linux e per chiedere e confrontarsi sull&#039;open source a casa e in azienda.</p>
     <p>In parallelo, saranno presenti anche:</p>
     <p>- una presentazione di  Ufficio Zero , la distro Linux italiana per professionisti, PMI e istituzioni;</p>
     <p>- la visione asincrona di  &quot;Python: The Documentary | An Origin Story&quot;  di Cult.Repo  in un’area specifica, per scoprire la storia di uno dei più interessanti linguaggi di programmazione del nostro tempo (inglese con sottotitoli);</p>
     <p>- una zona di Internet in a Box   per accedere a risorse e file senza avere una connettività esterna (demo di quello che possa essere fatto per portare dati e conoscenza alle comunità isolate e le aree in emergenza);</p>
     <p>- il nostro angolo  Raspberry  per scoprire mille progetti che possono portare i vantaggi del software libero nelle nostre case;</p>
     <p>- la presentazione del progetto  Semantica , tool per l&#039;analisi semantica foss;</p>
     <p>- il  punto FermoLUG , per scoprire cosa fa FermoLUG, partecipare e iscriversi (adesivi, tessere, magliette saranno disponibili al banchetto);</p>
     <p>- il Community Corner, per dare un supporto dal vivo su Linux e i software più comuni.</p>
     <p>L&#039;evento si terrà in italiano ma avremo la possibilità di dare supporto anche in inglese e francese.</p>
     <p>Come tutti i Linux Day, la partecipazione è gratuita.</p>
     <p>Dopo cena procederemo con l’Assemblea dei Soci.</p>
     <p>---<br />
EN</p>
     <p>Once again this year, Linux Day returns to Fermo on October 25th, organized by FermoLUG.</p>
     <p>We’ll talk about open software, free software, AI, environment, and technology -<br />
and of Linux, of course.</p>
     <p>The scheduled talks for the afternoon of October 25th are:</p>
     <p>15:00 — Openwashing in AI @Aldo Giambuzzi</p>
     <p>16:00 — Surprise Speech @Alessandro Iena</p>
     <p>17:00 — Not Just Blink: MicroPython and Bluetooth LE @Giacomo Vallorani</p>
     <p>18:00 — Environment &amp; AI @Federico Massi</p>
     <p>19:00 — OpenPGP and Cryptography @Francesco Valentini</p>
     <p>It will be possible to further discuss and exchange ideas with the speakers after each talk.<br />
In addition, there will be hands-on labs, an area to explore Linux with in person assistance, and spaces to ask questions and share experiences about open source at home and in business environments.</p>
     <p>In parallel, there will also be:</p>
     <p>a presentation of Ufficio Zero, the Italian Linux distribution for professionals, SMEs, and institutions;</p>
     <p>an asynchronous screening of “Python: The Documentary | An Origin Story” by Cult.Repo, in a dedicated area — discover the story of one of the most fascinating programming languages of our time (English with subtitles);</p>
     <p>an Internet in a Box area, allowing access to resources and files without external connectivity — a demo of what can be done to bring data and knowledge to isolated communities or emergency areas;</p>
     <p>our Raspberry corner, showcasing countless projects that bring the benefits of free software into our homes;</p>
     <p>a presentation of the Semantica project, a FOSS tool for semantic analysis;</p>
     <p>the FermoLUG point, where you can discover FermoLUG’s activities, join the community, and get stickers, membership cards, and T-shirts at the booth;</p>
     <p>the Community Corner, offering live support for Linux and common open-source software.</p>
     <p>Events and talks will be held in Italian, but we could provide assistance in English and French also. </p>
     <p>As any other Linux Day in Italy, registration is free.</p>
     <p>After dinner, we’ll hold the Members’ Assembly.</p>
    </body>

    
    <tags>
            <tag key="it">
          Italia      </tag>
            <tag key="talk"/>
<tag key="infobooth"/>
<tag key="localgroup"/>
<tag key="workshop"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
