<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2022-06-03" end="2022-06-03">
        <title>Upcycling Android workshop in Cologne, Germany</title>

    <body>
      <p>
        Together with contributors from PostmarketOS, we are offering
        another Upcycling Android workshop on 03 June at Alte
        Feuerwehrwache in Cologne, Germany. The workshop is about
        bringing tech enthusiasts and sustainability enthusiasts
        together and exchanging views on technology and sustainability
        while flashing phones with Free Software operating systems. We
        want to provide a place for all questions you have and we will
        bring different phones for trying out different systems and
        for trying out how to flash them. You can also bring your own
        phones, but in that case, we would ask you to clarify with us
        in advance whether we can support those devices.  In addition
        to the actual phone flashing, there will be a short keynote
        speech on longevity and sustainability on Android and other
        devices.
      </p>
      <p>
	As a unique feature for this workshop, we have two rooms
	available.  One room will focus on installing systems on
	phones to make them more sustainable. In the other room, the
	focus is on exchanging ideas about the development of the
	GNU/Linux mobile operating system PostmarketOS and about
	learning how to get involved.
      </p>
      <p>
        The workshop takes place from 16:00 - 20:00 at Alte Feuerwache
        Köln, Melchiorstraße 3, 50670 Köln. Everyone is welcome to
        join, participation is free, but please register via email to
        <a href="mailto:floriansnow@fsfe.org">floriansnow@fsfe.org</a>
        because space is limited.
      </p>
    </body>

    <link>https://wiki.fsfe.org/Activities/Android/UpcyclingWorkshops#A03._Juni_2022_-_K.2BAPY-ln.2C_Deutschland</link>
    <tags>
      <tag key="de">Germany</tag>      <tag key="workshop"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
