<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<data>
  <version>3</version>
  <module>
  <h2>I ♥ Free Software Day 2023: Meet and Connect</h2>

    <p>For the past years we hardly had the chance to meet each other in 
    person. Now we are bringing back in person 
    meetings for the "I Love Free Software Day". Let's celebrate our 
    love for Free Software - you are invited!
    </p>
    
<p>The "I Love Free Software Day" has been a tradition that 
lasts years. On this day we thank all the people behind Free Software 
projects or programs and let them know that their work does not go 
unnoticed. Let's celebrate together all the wonderful people working for 
Free Software. Therefore you are invited to join "I Love Free Software 
Day" celebrations all across Europe. Connect with your 
<a href="/about/groups.html">local FSFE group</a> and organise 
a fun meetup. 
</p>
      
   <p>
   We are grateful to those who work and contribute to the 
   Free Software universe: developers, designers, 
   translators, advocates, donors, users, and more. 
   There are a lot of different Free Software communities out there, 
   with different values or different focuses in their work. But we all 
   share our love for Free Software and value the freedom
   to use, study, share and improve software. Let's meet and connect! 
   Let's show our appreciation with a simple "Thank 
   you!"
   </p>


    <h2>Join the party</h2>
    
    <p>You want to celebrate with other Free Software enthusiasts? Here are some of the meetings
    happening around Europe</p>
    <ul>
    <li>I ♥ Free Software Day Party in Berlin at C-Base (Rungestraße 20, 10179 Berlin) with pizza, cake and music. They start at 16:30 with an "Upcycling Android Workshop". <a href="https://share.fsfe.org/apps/forms/s/JJ9GZiRzABW4CzSNj5ASixto">Please register for joining</a>.</li>
    <li>Meetup in Hamburg at Quan 19 (Rentzelstr. 6, 20146 Hamburg). For all of you who want to join you can drop by and enjoy "I Love Free Software Day"</li>
    <li>Pizza party in <a href="https://ccc-ffm.de/2023/01/i-free-software-day-am-14-februar-2023/">Frankfurt Chaos Computer Club</a>. Stop by and 
  join them! If you want to join please send an e-mail to<a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#x3a;&#x6d;&#x77;&#101;&#105;&#x6d;&#97;&#110;&#110;&#64;&#x66;&#x73;&#x66;&#101;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#103;">&#x6d;&#x77;&#101;&#105;&#x6d;&#97;&#110;&#110;&#64;&#x66;&#x73;&#x66;&#101;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#103;</a> and keep in mind that an FFP2 mask is required. The party starts at 19:00 (CET).</li>
  <li>For those near Thesaaloniki, Greece, there is an "Free Software and privacy" party happening at 18:30 (CET) in the "Ypsilon" first floor, Edessis 5, 546 25. For this <a href="https://share.fsfe.org/apps/forms/s/p6zSYnZyYKbwZBFe67YS2DP9">please register</a>.</li>
<li>Netherlands team meets in Arnhem, at the <a href="https://momento-arnhem.nl/eten-en-drinken">Momento</a> (Oude Oeverstraat 98, 6811 JZ Arnhem, Nederland) at 19:00 (CET). Please send an mail to the <a href="https://lists.fsfe.org/mailman/listinfo/netherlands">Dutch mailing list</a>.</li>
<li>The Italian community meets online. They start at 17:30 (CET) and you can join them in this <a href="https://edu.meet.garr.it/italiancommunitymeetingxilovefreesoftwareday">virtual room</a></li>
<li>Meetup in Swiss! Three Swiss local groups, Zurich, Basel, and St. Gallen invite you to join them for drinks, food and most importantly the celebation of ‘I Love Free Software Day’. They meet at
the Bitwäscherei at 17:00 (CET) and at 18:00 they take a group picture.</li>
<li> The local group in Potterie (UK) will meet at the Innovation Centre 1 building, Keele University, ST5 5NB, Staffordshire, United Kingdom. The "I Love Free Software" celebration beginn at 18:30 (GMT).</li>
<li>Madrid celebrates "I Love Free Software Day" from 18:30 (CET) at the MakerSpace Madrid, C. de la Arquitectura, 18, 28005 Madrid, Spain </li>
<li>"I Love Free Software Day" celebration in Barcelona will be a bit delyed on the 16th of February at 18:15 (CET) at the Ubicación, ,21 Carrer d'En Bot 08002 Barcelona, Spain. Contact the <a href="https://lists.fsfe.org/mailman/listinfo/barcelona">group</a> to get the location and more information</li> 
</ul>
    
      <div class="icon-grid">
      <ul>
        <li>
          <img src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-use.png" 
          alt="ILoveFS heart with 'use'"/>
          <div>
            <h3>Say thanks<br/></h3>
            <p>
              Thank the people who
              enable you to enjoy software freedom. Organise a local 
              group meeting or spread the word about Free Software. You can use our <a 
              href="https://sharepic.fsfe.org/#ilovefs">sharepics</a>,
              <a href="/contribute/spreadtheword#ilovefs">stickers and
              balloons</a>, or <a href="/activities/ilovefs/artwork/artwork.html">artwork</a>, and
              <a href="/order/order.html">merchandise</a> for <em>#ilovefs</em>.
            </p>

          </div>
        </li>

        <li>
          <img 
          src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-study.png" 
          alt="ILoveFS heart with 'study'"/>
          <div>
            <h3>Remember the good times<br/></h3>
            <p>
              Which Free Software project did you uses
              last year? What felt empowering? What was fun?
              For some inspiration have a look at others' <a 
              href="/activities/ilovefs/whylovefs/gallery.html">love 
              statements</a> and <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/p/u3Ep8hRP5vFdbgUE9LKScW">videos</a>.
            </p>
          </div>
        </li>

        <li>
          <img 
          src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-share.png" 
          alt="ILoveFS heart with 'share'"/>
          <div>
            <h3>Share your love</h3>
            <p>
              That's the fun part! We have created a <a 
              href="https://sharepic.fsfe.org/#ilovefs">sharepic generator</a>, 
              with which you can easily create your very own sharepics 
              and share your appreciation on social media
              (<em>#ilovefs</em>), in blog posts, pictures and <a 
              href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/p/u3Ep8hRP5vFdbgUE9LKScW">video 
              messages</a>,
              or directly to the Free Software developers and contributors.
            </p>
          </div>
        </li>

        <li>
          <img 
          src="/graphics/icons/ilovefs-improve.png" 
          alt="ILoveFS heart with 'improve'"/>
          <div>
            <h3>Improve Free Software</h3>
            <p>
              Talking is silver, contributing is gold! Help a Free Software
              project with code, a translation, or by assisting its users. Or if
              you can, please consider a donation to a Free Software
              organisation <a href="https://my.fsfe.org/donate">like the
              FSFE</a>, or to a Free Software project.
            </p>
          </div>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </div>

    <figure class="no-border">
      <img
        src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/small/f164c8517e78449fc8844a72347af490.png"
        alt="#ilovefs" />
    </figure>

    <p>
      What is your contribution to this special day dedicated to the people who enable
      you to use Free Software? Will you use our stickers and balloons? Or make
      a picture or video with your new ILoveFS shirt? And what about celebrating
      software freedom with your colleagues and friends at a company gathering
      or public event? Whatever you do, show it to the world by using the
      <em>#ilovefs</em> tag. And if you have questions, <a href="/contact/">just
      drop us an email</a>.
  </p>

    <p>
      Happy <strong><span class="text-danger">I Love Free
      Software</span></strong> Day everyone! ❤
    </p>

 </module>
</data>
