<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2023-12-19" end="2023-12-19">
        <title>FSFE Potteries - Flörgåsbord! (A social with 4 free bowling lanes!) in Newcastle-under-Lyme, United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</title>

    <body>
      <p>IMPORTANT!..  You must RSVP to attend this event via the FSFE Potteries mailing list or e-mail the organiser directly... questions are also welcome via either method also.</p>
      <p>Mailing list: https://lists.fsfe.org/mailman/listinfo/potteries<br />
E-mail the organiser: lantizia@fsfe.org</p>
      <p>We've booked a private room in the centre of Newcastle-under-Lyme, that holds up to 40 people (which we're very unlikely to fill anyway) from 6:30pm GMT onwards until closing... it's upstairs from the Vue cinema and we'll provide exact directions when you RSVP.</p>
      <p>There's 4 full sized bowling lanes in this room... all of which are ours for the whole evening for unlimited free play, 6 people at most to a lane.</p>
      <p>It's FREE as we're pickup up the bill, it's an incredibly small bill anyway (we're familiar with the management) and so don't worry about it.</p>
      <p>Like our past socials there will be places to just sit and just chat (no loud music!).  Not everyone will be bowling anyway, so don't feel like you have to.  Should be plenty of free software users about for a catch up!</p>
      <p>The venue has a new kitchen serving hot food (so no need to eat before coming out) as well as offering drinks... we'll send out details of what kind of food and drinks when you RSVP.</p>
      <p>We're holding this event jointly with the local LUG and local Open Rights Group branch, so it's sure to be a great mix of people in one social.  You're welcome to bring friends and family too, but you must let us know exact numbers if possible when you RSVP (as we need to keep the room to under 40 people, which it surely will be anyway... so don't give it a second thought!)</p>
      <p>It's a veritable Flörgåsbord! - We were trying to merge the acronyms FSF/LUG/ORG and got &quot;Florg&quot; which got compared to the word Smörgåsbord (a Swedish buffet) and so we made it Flörgåsbord instead (as a buffet of local technology groups!).</p>
      <p>I've got details of where to park, food, directions, etc... so when you RSVP I can pass all those details to you!</p>
    </body>

    
    <tags>
      <tag key="gb">United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</tag>      <tag key="localgroup"/>
<tag key="meeting"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
