<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-12-13" type="newsletter">
    <title>Weak EU Digital Rights +++ Checkmate! +++ 5 reasons why</title>
    <body>
      <p>
  In this issue we note the shift of the EU Digital Rights Declaration 
  to an unclear, ambiguous text. Free Software chess engine wins its 
  legal battle. Your contribution can help software freedom. YH4F 
  registration. The Greek team meets after a long time.
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>
    
<h1 id="weak-eu-digital-rights-checkmate-5-reasons-why">Weak EU Digital Rights +++ Checkmate! +++ 5 reasons why</h1>

<p>
  In this issue we note the shift of the EU Digital Rights Declaration 
  to an unclear, ambiguous text. Free Software chess engine wins its 
  legal battle. Your contribution can help software freedom. YH4F 
  registration. The Greek team meets after a long time.
</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/90/d5/ff7ad79363421dbf1ac39faca9d9.png" alt="Three illustrations. A dark official building, a community gathering, a chess board."/>
</figure>

<h3 id="eu-declaration-of-digital-rights-falls-short-of-its-ambitions">EU Declaration of Digital Rights falls short of its ambitions</h3>

<p>
  <a href="/news/2022/news-20221206-01.html">Member 
  states, the European Parliament and the Commission have reached a 
  consensus on the Declaration of Digital Rights and Principles</a>. 
  The Declaration aims to serve as a reference point for the digital 
  transformation of Europe. Instead, it descends into murky waters, 
  causing ambiguity. The wording is unclear and the declaration 
  overlooks existing good proposals.
</p>

<p>
  The Declaration is said to be built upon previous initiatives such as 
  the Berlin and <a href="/news/2017/news-20170710-01.html">Tallinn</a> 
  declarations. These frameworks already referred to Free Software 
  concerning digital sovereignty and interoperability, required more 
  use of Free Software, and strengthened the requirement for its use. 
  It is striking that concerning interoperability, Free Software is not 
  explicitly mentioned in the Declaration of Digital Rights and 
  Principles.
</p>

<h3 id="copyleft-licensed-chess-engine-wins-legal-case-against-proprietary-counterpart">Copyleft-licensed chess engine wins legal case against proprietary counterpart</h3>

<p>
  Copyleft protects Free Software from becoming proprietary. Free 
  Software chess engine Stockfish filed a lawsuit when ChessBase 
  distributed parts of Stockfish work under a proprietary license, 
  violating GPL-3.0 obligations. Checkmate! <a href="/news/2022/news-20221212-01.html">Stockfish was 
  victorious</a>. ChessBase must comply fully with GPL-3, hire a Free 
  Software Compliance Officer, and list their Free Software elements 
  online, before they can distribute the Stockfish software or make it 
  publicly available again.
</p>

<figure>
  <a href="/news/2022/news-20221212-01.html">
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/2f/4c/a417a2cf4466f2edcee94bf1e2c1.jpg" alt="Chess board with a white horse pawn in between a black horse and a black tower."/></a>
</figure>

<h3 id="5-reasons-why-your-contribution-matters">5 reasons why your contribution matters</h3>

<p>
  <a href="/news/2022/news-20221205-01.html">Your 
  support and contribution for the promotion of Free Software are 
  important</a> for securing our continuous work, ensuring our 
  independence, strengthening our democratic society, promoting and 
  implementing concrete steps towards software freedom, and making it 
  easier to use and develop Free Software.
</p>

<h3 id="yh4f-registrations-end-in-2022">YH4F registrations end in 2022</h3>

<p>
  <a href="/activities/yh4f/">Registration for Youth 
  Hacking 4 Freedom ends on 31st December</a>. The coding contest 
  welcomes 14-18 year old Europeans who wants to hack a Free Software 
  project of their choice and win cash prizes. As some of the winners 
  from the last edition stated,  participating was a lot of fun and a 
  great opportunity. Check our <a href="/news/2022/news-20221118-01.html">video with 
  the winners presenting their projects in Brussels</a>. Share this 
  opportunity among your friends and community! Moreover, you can send 
  it to schools, teachers, and young people in your region.
</p>

<figure>
  <a href="/news/2022/news-20221212-01.html">
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/40/98/97b47597923d312f9248726411b6.png" alt="Boy with black hoodie that writes 'Hacking for Freedom' says: Do you love coding? Join the YH4F competition until Dec 31."/></a>
</figure>

<h3 id="past-events">Past events</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    On 2 December Alexander Sander, FSFE Senior Policy Consultant, 
    spoke at a <a href="https://swforum.eu/os-standards">workshop 
    hosted by the European Commission</a>. The topic was ‘Open 
    standards and industrial use for Open Source: Leveraging the 
    sustainability of Open Source projects and increasing competition 
    and interoperability between different steps in value-chains’.
  </li>
  <li>
    On 26 November Vincent Lequertier gave a talk 'For an inclusive 
    and ethical artificial intelligence' in the event Campus du 
    Libre in Lyon, France. Also, the FSFE had a booth at the 
    event.
  </li>
</ul>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/26/0f/8a67735ce1db3f230c4e43af9768.jpg" alt="Series of booths with people behind them, person with orange T-shirt looks at the camera."/>
  <figcaption>
    Vincent Lequertier at a booth in Campus du Libre event. November 2022, Lyon, France.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<ul>
  <li>
    On 21 November we flashed phones in Dessau and on 24 November in 
    Frankfurt, Germany. We flashed phone devices the FSFE provided, and 
    also others that people brought.
  </li>
  <li>
    On 17 November Lina Ceballos, REUSE's coordinator, gave a talk 
    about REUSE in the GNU Health Conference (GHCon). Right after, Lina 
    gave the GNUHealth project the well-deserved REUSE compliance award 
    for its Hospital Management System component. <a href="https://gnuhealth.org/">GNUHealth</a> is an outstanding Free 
    Software project that contributes to make a change in various 
    countries in the global South.
  </li>
</ul>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/a9/52/61ffa322a01ce8870c95d6252269.jpeg" alt="Conference room. Projected presentation with REUSE logo, banners with GNU Health logo, woman presenting."/>
  <figcaption>
    Lina Ceballos presents REUSE in the GNU Health Conference. November 2022, Las Palmas, Spain.
  </figcaption>
</figure>


<h3 id="fsfe-groups">FSFE groups</h3>

<p>
  Our groups welcome everyone who is interested in Free Software to 
  join, and abide to the Code of Conduct. Here is what they are up 
  to.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Germany</strong>: A festive meeting marked the end of the year at the FSFE 
  local Berlin group. Nikolai from "cosum" joined as speaker. 
  cosum (from CO-llaborative con-SUM-ption) is a lending platform that 
  allows people to share things like tools, gardening equipment, or 
  gazebos. With this, the group wants to promote more social-ecological 
  consumption models. With cosum, a public lending store can be 
  founded, but also private-to-private lending between friends and 
  lending in communities, e.g. in the house or neighborhood, are 
  possible. Borrowing saves resources, money, and space. Hamburg has 
  monthly meetings in-person.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Greece</strong>: <a href="/events/events.html#event-20221215-01">After 
  a long time without meetings, next  Thursday 15 December the FSFE 
  Greece country team gathers in a first introductory meeting</a>. The 
  topics to be discussed include Mastodon and its current developments, 
  Greek instances, recommendations for content in the Greek language, 
  and usage tips. Nikos Roussos, developer at libreops, will talk about 
  Libretooth. Fani Partsafyllidou, FSFE Project Manager, will share 
  updates about Free Software in Europe. Just drop by!
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Netherlands</strong>: During their last meeting the team discussed a <a href="https://gitea-open-letter.coding.social/">Gitea governance 
  conflict</a>. The Fair Digital Education coalition, in which the FSFE 
  participates through the country team Netherlands, became an <a href="https://isoc.nl/nieuws/new-isoc-nl-working-group-coalition-fair-digital-education-cfde">Internet 
  Society chapter</a>. The group also debated a worrying phenomenon in 
  the Netherlands, where citizens form WhatsApp groups with policing 
  purposes. There is a question if a standalone Belgium group can be 
  formed. The next meeting is on 21 December.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Switzerland</strong>: <strong>Basel</strong>: In their previous meeting, the FSFE local group 
  Basel discussed the dependency of schools upon proprietary software. 
  The experiences of the members were similar; schools have a 
  simplistic approach to software. The best way is to correct this is 
  to demonstrate the benefits of Free Software in a playful and visual 
  way. The group compared Tor, VPN, and Freifunk as privacy options. A 
  member from the Zurich group encouraged the Basel group to adopt a 
  project based strategy. <strong>Zurich</strong>: The FSFE local group Zurich has 
  launched the FediGov campaign and has created a leaflet for the 
  campaign ‘Learn like a pro’.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Women</strong>: In the last online meeting Fani presented the Upcycling 
  Android open letter to the group. Then, the team talked about joining 
  the decentralized and independent alternative events of 37c3. In the 
  previous meeting the group discussed radio technology, an example of 
  a <a href="https://mycroft.ai/">privacy-focused voice assistant</a>, 
  and colour printing.
</p>

<h3 id="get-active">Get active</h3>

<p>
  We need your backing to gain the right to install any software on any 
  device. <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/openletter.html">Sign 
  our open letter and share it with your own message</a>. Explain to 
  your network what this right means for you.
</p>

<h2 id="contribute-to-our-newsletter">Contribute to our Newsletter</h2>

<p>
  If you would like to share any thoughts, pictures, or news, please 
  send them to us. As always, the address is <email>newsletter@fsfe.org</email>. 
  We're looking forward to hearing from you! If you also want to 
  support us and our work, join our community and support us with a <a href="https://my.fsfe.org/donate?referrer=newsletter">donation or a 
  monthly contribution</a>. Thanks to our community and all the 
  volunteers, supporters, and donors who make our work possible. And 
  thanks to our translators, who enable you to read this newsletter in 
  your native languages.
</p>
  
<p>Your editor, Fani Partsafyllidou</p>

  </body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/90/d5/ff7ad79363421dbf1ac39faca9d9.png" alt="Three illustrations. A dark official building, a community gathering, a chess board."/>
    <link>/news/nl/nl-202212.html</link>
    <tags>
    <tag key="front-page"/>
    <tag key="newsletter">Newsletter</tag>
    <tag key="compliance">Compliance</tag>
    <tag key="gpl">GNU GPL</tag>
    <tag key="yh4f">Youth Hacking 4 Freedom</tag>
    <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
    <tag key="localgroup">Local group</tag>
    <tag key="de">Germany</tag>
    <tag key="berlin">Berlin</tag>
    <tag key="hamburg-group">Hamburg group</tag>
    <tag key="gr">Greece</tag>
    <tag key="nl">Netherlands</tag>
    <tag key="ch">Switzerland</tag>
    <tag key="women-group">Women group</tag>
      
  </tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/948"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
