<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2024-01-16" type="newsletter">
    <title>Podcast episodes +++ Router Freedom tech wiki +++ Become our policy intern</title>
    <body>
      <p>
We are starting 2024 with a lot of energy, looking for a policy intern 
and with great news: two new SFP episodes, the Router Freedom tech wiki, 
the ‘Ada &amp; Zangemann’ ebook is free of charge in French, and we are looking 
forward to celebrating ‘I Love Free Software Day’ on 14 February!
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>Podcast episodes +++ Router Freedom tech wiki +++ Become our policy intern</h1>

<p>
We are starting 2024 with a lot of energy, looking for a policy intern 
and with great news: two new SFP episodes, the Router Freedom tech wiki, 
the ‘Ada &amp; Zangemann’ ebook is free of charge in French, and we are looking 
forward to celebrating ‘I Love Free Software Day’ on 14 February!
</p>

<figure>
	<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/f5/12/ffddcc73fe45a2be26905cf75c61.png" alt="Image collage with an illustration of a heart in a screen with 1 and 0; the router freedom sticker and the software freedom podcast logo"/>
</figure>

<div class="toc">
<p>Table of contents</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="#Software-Freedom-Podcast">Software Freedom Podcast: Listen to our episodes about ‘What is Free Software’ and ‘Public Money? Public Code!’</a></li>
<li><a href="#Router-Freedom">Router Freedom: Good news: our tech wiki is now online! Bad news: Austria goes against Router Freedom</a></li>
<li><a href="#job-internship">Spread the Word! We are looking for a policy intern</a></li>
<li><a href="#Unblocking-User-Freedom">Unblocking User Freedom: The right to use adblockers</a></li>
<li><a href="#Ada-&amp;-Zangemann">‘Ada &amp; Zangemann’: What pupils write about proprietary software and why it motivates the author</a></li>
<li><a href="#Italian-Community-Meeting-2023">Italian Community Meeting 2023</a></li>
<li><a href="#Get-involved">Get Involved: I Love Free Software Day</a></li>
<li><a href="#quote-of-the-month">Quote of the Month</a></li>
<li><a href="#contribute-to-our-newsletter">Contribute to our Newsletter</a></li>
</ol>
</div>

<h3 id="Software-Freedom-Podcast">Software Freedom Podcast: Listen to our episodes about ‘What is Free Software’ and ‘Public Money? Public Code!’</h3>
<p>During the past weeks we published two new episodes of our Software Freedom Podcast!</p>

<p>
In our episode number 23,  some FSFE staffers play <a href="/news/podcast/episode-23.html">a guessing game with terms related 
to Free Software</a>. This is the perfect episode for you to learn more 
about it and get a better understanding of some terms that you might 
not use daily.
</p>
 
<p>
Before that, we talked with Johannes Näder, Senior Policy Project 
Manager at the Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE), about <a href="/news/podcast/episode-22.html">"Public Money? Public Code!", in 
our 22nd episode</a>.
</p>

<h3 id="Router-Freedom">Router Freedom: Good news: our tech wiki is 
now online! Bad news: Austria goes against Router Freedom</h3>
<p>
Have you ever thought about installing your own router but never had the 
chance to learn how to do it? Now you can with our <a href="https://docs.fsfe.org/en/teams/router-freedom-tech-wiki">Router 
Freedom tech wiki</a>, which provides information on the necessary steps 
you need to use to connect your own router! With the help of our team 
of volunteers from the Netherlands, you can check all the necessary 
steps to start using your own home router. <br/><br/>Our 
policy and advocacy work continues, notwithstanding some regulatory 
hurdles. <a href="/news/2023/news-20231201-01.html">The Austrian Regulatory 
Authority for Broadcasting and Telecommunications decided not to 
regulate the network operators</a> with regard to Router Freedom, 
allowing Internet Service Providers (ISPs) to impose their equipment on 
consumers. We will continue to seek alternative ways to promote Router Freedom in the country. 
</p>

<p/>

<h3 id="job-internship">Spread the Word! We are looking for a policy intern</h3>
<p>
The FSFE team is looking for <a href="/news/2023/news-20231211-01.html">a motivated intern to support 
the FSFE’s policy activities</a> and contribute to our work to empower 
people to control technology. The person will work 35 hours per week 
with our team in the FSFE Berlin office for a period of six months.
</p>
	
<p>
<cite>“I joined FSFE as an intern in March 2023 because I have always 
been interested in European politics and because the slogan "Public 
Money? Public Code!" resonated deeply with my beliefs. The experience at 
FSFE has been great: I learned how to make our voice heard and I am 
proud of being part of a community of  many amazing people working and volunteering for 
software freedom.”</cite> - Dario Presutti, former policy intern
</p>


<h3 id="#Unblocking-User-Freedom">Unblocking User Freedom: The right to use adblockers</h3>
<p>
Companies increasingly aim to control how users interact with their 
content online, threatening user freedom. As more companies crack down 
on browser extensions and other third-party software used by internet 
users to customise their experiences, two recent German court cases on 
adblockers could strengthen the legal case for user control over 
technology.
</p>
<p>
Interesting? <a href="/news/2023/news-20231220-01.html">Read our news 
item to find out more</a> about this topic.
</p>

<h3 id="#Ada-&amp;-Zangemann">"Ada &amp; Zangemann": What pupils write about proprietary software and why it motivates the author</h3>
<p>
Pupils all over the world are learning about the story of "Ada &amp; 
Zangemann - A Tale of Software, Skateboards and Raspberry Ice Cream": it 
is encouraging to see how new generations are inspired to start coding 
and to write to Zangemann about his behaviour. <a href="/news/2023/news-20231207-01.html">Check out this message</a> from 
our president, Matthias Kirschner, to our readers.
</p> 

<p>
The story of "Ada &amp; Zangemann" is now available in 
French and, thanks to the French Ministry of Education, you can download 
the ebook free of charge at <a href="https://cfeditions.com/ada">https://cfeditions.com/ada</a>(FR). And if 
you want to read the story about how this book was translated into 
French by some students, do not forget to read the quote there (FR) 
from Alexis Kauffmann, head of the Free Software and educational 
resources project at the Ministry of Education and Youth and founder of 
Framasoft.
</p>


<h3 id="#Italian-Community-Meeting-2023">Italian Community Meeting 2023</h3>
<p>
More than 20 volunteers and associations’ members from all over Italy, 
online and in person, gathered in Bolzano for the Italian Community 
Meeting during SFSCON 2023 to discuss the future of Free Software 
in Italy. You can enjoy <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/7SfNACpkJ1oiE8NHwYXbjL">the recording of 
the workshop in our Peertube Channel</a>.
</p>

<p>A sneak peek at the main topics discussed by our participants: Free 
Software in schools, the creation of a toolkit which can be adopted by 
all organizations to encourage the use of Free Software, and raising 
awareness about Free Software with the general public through simplified 
information!
</p>

<h3 id="#Get-involved">Get Involved: I Love Free Software Day</h3>
<p>
On 14 February, we gather to celebrate "I Love Free Software Day". Join 
our local groups’ events on that date, organise your own gathering, 
and/or send a message to thank the contributors of the Free Software 
project you really like.
</p>

<p>
For “I Love Free Software Day 2024: Forging the future with Free 
Software”, we want to focus on engaging young generations in Free 
Software as they are the ones who will shape the next years. For more 
information, ideas, and inspiration check out the <a href="https://ilovefs.org/">‘I Love Free Software’ activity page!</a>.
</p>


<h3 id="#quote-of-the-month">Quote of the Month</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>“Dear Zangemann,<br/>
I used to like your inventions in fact I still like them but you are 
starting to use them in the wrong way. It’s not fair that some people 
have to eat, drink and listen to music they don’t like. When you do that 
to people can see you inside and how selfish you are. It’s much better 
if you share your inventions because it doesn’t mean they are stealing 
it, it means they just are borrowing it, and making it better. So please 
share your ideas. It will make our planet much better.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>— Nikita (from one of <a href="/activities/ada-zangemann/letters.html">the letters sent to Zangemann</a>)</p>
<h3 id="contribute-to-our-newsletter">Contribute to our Newsletter</h3>
<p>
We would love to hear from you. If you have any thoughts, pictures, or 
news to share, please send them to us at 
<email>newsletter@fsfe.org</email>. You can also <a href="/donate/donate.html">support us</a>, <a href="/contribute/contribute.html">contribute to our work</a>, and <a href="/about/groups.html">join our community</a>. We would like to thank 
our community and all the volunteers, supporters, and donors who make 
our work possible, with a special mention to our translators who make it 
possible for you to read this newsletter in your mother tongue.
</p>

<p><i>Your editors,<br/>
Ana and Tommi</i></p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/f5/12/ffddcc73fe45a2be26905cf75c61.png" alt="Image collage with an illustration of a heart in a screen with 1 and 0; the router freedom sticker and the software freedom podcast logo"/>
    <link>/news/nl/nl-202401.html</link>
    <tags>
	<tag key="front-page"/>
	<tag key="newsletter">Newsletter</tag>
	<tag key="routers">Router Freedom</tag>
	<tag key="pmpc">Public Money? Public Code!</tag>
	<tag key="ada-zangemann">Ada and Zangemann</tag>
	<tag key="sfscon">SFSCon</tag>
	<tag key="ilovefs">I love Free Software</tag>
	<tag key="internship">Internship</tag>
	<tag key="ngi">Next Generation Internet</tag>
	<tag key="deviceneutrality">Device Neutrality</tag>	
	<tag key="podcast">Software Freedom Podcast</tag>	
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1120"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
