<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2024-06-04" type="newsletter">
    <title>EU election +++ DMA &amp; Apple +++ REUSE tool</title>
    <body>
      <p>
In this issue, we explain our plans to make a movie of the story of Ada 
&amp; Zangemann and we are asking for your support. A new REUSE version 
released; read the FSFE opinion to the European Commission on 
Apple’s new strategy to comply with DMA and its impact on Free Software.
 </p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>EU election +++ DMA &amp; Apple +++ REUSE tool</h1>

<p>
In this issue, we explain our plans to make a movie of the story of Ada 
&amp; Zangemann and we are asking for your support. A new REUSE version 
released; read the FSFE opinion to the European Commission on 
Apple’s new strategy to comply with DMA and its impact on Free Software.
 </p>

<figure>
	<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/3f/21/24d04ba4d35dfa3e42d79e36909d.png" alt="Picture collage showing an illustration of Ada, REUSE software logo, and an illustration of a city hall"/>
</figure>

<div class="toc">
  <p>Table of contents</p>
	<ul id="toc">
		<li><a href="#quote-of-the-month"><strong>Quote of the Month</strong></a></li>
		<li><a href="#take-action"><strong>Take action! Talk to your politicians, like our FSFE Netherlands coordinator</strong></a></li>
		<li><a href="#reuse"><strong>REUSE v.3.1.0a1</strong></a></li>
		<li><a href="#interoperability-apple"><strong>Apple's approach to DMA will harm Free Software</strong></a></li>
		<li><a href="#ada-video"><strong>Ada goes to the set: let’s make an animated movie!</strong></a></li>
		<li><a href="#stories-community"><strong>Stories from our community</strong></a></li>
                <li><a href="#more-conferences"><strong>And even more: LibreItalia, DORS/CLUC 2024 and esLibre 2024 conferences</strong></a></li>
		<li><a href="contribute"><strong>Contribute to our Newsletter</strong></a></li>
	</ul>
</div>
	
<h3 id="quote-of-the-month">Quote of the Month</h3>
<blockquote>
	<p>“Socks. I want the socks. I love the FS socks. And if you have, others too”</p>
	<cite>-FOSDEM 2024 FSFE attendant-</cite>
</blockquote>


<h3 id="take-action">Take action! Talk to your politicians, like our 
FSFE Netherlands coordinator</h3> 

<p>In a couple of days, the European 
citizens will choose their next representatives in the European 
Parliament. <a href="/activities/publiccode/get-active.html">Get 
active</a> to ensure that Software Freedom is part of the larger 
political debate! </p> 

<p>The FSFE Netherlands coordinator <a href="/news/2024/news-20240530-01.html">has added his voice for Free 
Software to Amsterdam's digital city debate</a>. Now it's your chance 
to highlight the importance of Free Software in the lead-up to the 
upcoming European Elections next week. </p> 

<figure>
  <peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/bfXqXqTZwipM9zbubjbDHV"/>
  <figcaption>FSFE Netherlands coordinator question (in Dutch):"I think 
  in March something beautiful happened in Amsterdam: the proposal 
  'Amsterdam Digital Independent' (or 'autonomous') was adopted. I was 
  wondering: in it open source is mentioned to promote autonomy, but 
  also to promote transparency. I would say this aligns with the points 
  of the NSC. What will you do in Europe to bring that further and to 
  support governments and municipalities to really make progress with free and 
  open source software?"
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="reuse">REUSE v.3.1.0a1</h3>

<p>The REUSE tool v3.1.0a1 has just been released! This is an alpha 
release that includes the new REUSE.toml functionality that replaces 
.reuse/dep5 (which is being soft-deprecated). The main purpose of 
REUSE.toml is to resolve .reuse/dep5 scenarios as described in <a href="https://github.com/fsfe/reuse-tool/issues/779">https://github.com/fsfe/reuse-tool/issues/779</a>: 
if a file has a header 
and is also covered by .reuse/dep5, and the two sources of information 
disagree about the licence, which licence applies?</p>

<p>In three steps, REUSE software addresses a fundamental problem with 
Free Software licensing at its source: what licence is a file licensed 
under, and who owns the copyright? The REUSE project consists of a set 
of best practices and a tool that makes it easy and simple to add this 
legal information to every single file in a project.</p>

<p>We are working on releasing <a href="https://reuse.software/spec-3.2/">version 3.2</a> of this tool soon, 
so stay tuned!</p>
 
<h3 id="interoperability-apple">Apple's approach to DMA will harm Free Software</h3> 

<p>The FSFE continues to work on the implementation of the Digital Markets 
Act (DMA), monitoring the strategies adopted by affected companies 
(gatekeepers), and their impact on Free Software. We submitted <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/device-neutrality/202404-FSFE-apple-report-EC.pdf">a 
comprehensive stakeholder position</a> to the European Commission on how 
Apple cannot be compliant with DMA, and their strategy will reinforce 
their anti-competitive position. Our report lists that:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Apple should not limit business and end-users in their software freedom by 
overstating arguments of integrity and security of devices. </li>
<li>Apple should not discriminate against Free Software.</li>
<li>Apple should not be allowed to impose DRM encryption for app distribution regarding Free 
Software.</li>
<li>Apple should not be allowed to impose 
arbitraryinteroperability request forms, but interoperability 
should be granted automaticallyand effectively.</li>
</ul>

<p>This study received substantial contributions from experts and other 
organizations including F-Droid, Onion Browser, and AppFair.</p>

<figure>
	<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/6a/92/2e2ca130f208449ebfd0dbed4a6c.png" alt="Image showing one of FSFE staffers participating sitting with a laptop and talking to a microphone on the table"/>
		<figcaption>FSFE at the DMA compliance workshop about Apple</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>This report concludes that, while the DMA aims to promote contestability 
and fairness, Apple's proposed changes may reinforce its monopolistic 
behaviour by restricting software freedom, strengthening the dependency 
of developers and users on its own services and products, and increasing 
switching costs. <br/><br/>The report also sets forth how integrity of 
operating systems must not be used for summarily imposing restrictions 
on 3rd party app stores</p>


<h3 id="ada-video">Ada goes to the set: let’s make an animated movie!</h3>

<p>The illustrated book 'Ada &amp; Zangemann: A Tale of Software, 
Skateboards, and Raspberry Ice Cream' has made it into homes and libraries 
around the world. Now we need your help to reach even more kids! <a href="/news/2024/news-20240515-01.html">Help us make a film of this 
story</a> and continue doing readings to spark more 
kids’ interest in coding and tinkering!</p>
 
 
<h3 id="stories-community">Stories from our community</h3>
 
<p>On 25 and 26 May, the RoboCup France Junior took place in Bordeaux. 
Nursery and primary kids presented their robots while the teens and 
young adults competed with theirs in various competitions from soccer 
to rescue. On Sunday 26 May, Théo (15y) and Émilie (12y), two young 
French supporters, repurposed some of their local robot club (CDSR) 
booth into their first FSFE booth! They proudly shared FSFE 
stickers and presented the children's book Ada &amp; Zangemann.</p>

<p>Also in France, in this case in Lyon, FSFE volunteer Vincent Lequertier 
participated in the Days of the Software Libre (JDLL is its acronym in 
French) with two readings of the illustrated book "Ada &amp; Zangemann: 
Un conte sur les logiciels, le skateboard et la glace à la framboise".</p>

<p>And in the Netherlands, André Ockers, volunteer and deputy 
coordinator of the Dutch FSFE team, presented (in English) the Free 
Software Foundation Europe at WikiconNL 2024, the annual conference on 
Wikipedia, Wikimedia, digital heritage, and free access to information 
in a changing world.</p>

<p>
Do not forget to check out <a href="https://planet.fsfe.org/">planet.fsfe.org</a>; our blog aggregator 
has several articles that you might find interesting!
</p>


<h3 id="more-conferences">And even more: LibreItalia, DORS/CLUC 2024 and esLibre 2024 conferences</h3>

<p>At the beginning of May, we took part in the LibreItalia 
Conference. It was a great occasion to meet and chat with the Italian 
Free Software community. We had the possibility to talk about Public 
Money? Public Code! and engage with a younger audience thanks to the Ada 
and Zangemann story!</p>

<p>A bit later last month, we participated in DORS/CLUC, a conference 
in Zagreb with two talks, one about "Making AI Really Open: The 
Current Landscape of Free Software and AI Licensing" and another about 
"When our routers are not free: the challenges for an Open and Neutral 
Internet".</p> 
<p>Finally, we travelled to Valencia to attend esLibre 
2024. There we presented the competition YH4F, talked about CRA, PLD, 
and liability in Europe and explained why Free Software is important
for our society!</p> 

<p>
Our talks from esLibre and DORS/CLUC were recorded so we will upload 
them in our usual channels as soon as they are available!
</p>

<figure>
	<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/22/33/416769c56617d2e3dc856f085944.png" alt="Image collage showing different FSFE staffers giving talks at DORS/CLUC and esLibre"/>
</figure>


<h3 id="contribute">Contribute to our Newsletter</h3>
<p>
We would love to hear from you. If you have any thoughts, pictures, or 
news to share, please send them to us at newsletter@fsfe.org. You can 
also <a href="/donate/donate.html">support us</a>, <a href="/contribute/contribute.html">contribute to our work</a>, and <a href="/about/groups.html">join our community</a>. We would like to thank 
our community and all the volunteers, supporters, and donors who make 
our work possible, with a special mention to our translators who make it 
possible for you to read this newsletter in your mother tongue.
</p>
<p>
Your editor,<br/>
Ana
</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/3f/21/24d04ba4d35dfa3e42d79e36909d.png" alt="Picture collage showoing an illustration of Ada, REUSE software logo and an illustration of a city hall"/>
    <link>/news/nl/nl-202406.html</link>
    <tags>
    <tag key="newsletter">Newsletter</tag>
    <tag key="front-page"/>
    <tag key="pmpc">Public Money? Public Code!</tag>
    <tag key="elections">EU elections</tag>
    <tag key="legal">Legal</tag>
    <tag key="ada-zangemann">Ada and Zangemann</tag>
    <tag key="fr">France</tag>
    <tag key="es">Spain</tag>
    <tag key="nl">Netherlands</tag>
    <tag key="hr">Croatia</tag>
    <tag key="event">Event</tag>
    <tag key="dma">Digital Markets Act</tag>

    <tag key="highlights"/>
</tags>
  </news>
</newsset>
