<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-02-08" type="newsletter">
    <title>I Love Free Software +++ Public authorities in Fediverse</title>
    <body>
      <p>
  In this issue we invite public institutions to join free, 
  decentralised social networks. Watch our info-session on German 
  municipalities using Free Software. An FSFE volunteer doubts the 
  reliability of AI-generated text. I Love Free Software Day is just 
  around the corner. Celebrate with us!
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>
    

<h1>I Love Free Software +++ Public authorities in Fediverse</h1>

<p>
  In this issue we invite public institutions to join free, 
  decentralised social networks. Watch our info-session on German 
  municipalities using Free Software. An FSFE volunteer doubts the 
  reliability of AI-generated text. I Love Free Software Day is just 
  around the corner. Celebrate with us!
</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/e0/29/ab54fd23aa23910d475412815739.png" alt="Pictures of a person, a heart, and a mastodon in front on of a building."/>
</figure>


<h3 id="i-love-free-software-day">I Love Free Software Day</h3>

<p>
  We know you love Free Software. We do too. Think of the program that 
  means the most for you, or one that positively surprised you this 
  year. Share a ‘thank you’ message on the 14th of February with 
  #ilovefs to show your appreciation to its contributors. We celebrate 
  ‘I Love Free Software Day’ with events too. <a href="/news/2023/news-20230126-01.html">Join us 
  here</a>:
</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/8a/90/6da6e380bd372a8d3e229a006feb.png" alt="Digits and flags of Germany, Greece, Italy, Netherlands, and Switzerland."/>
</figure>

<ul>
  <li>🇩🇪 Germany - Berlin, Frankfurt a.M., Bonn, Hamburg</li>
  <li>🇬🇷 Greece - Thessaloniki </li>
  <li>🇮🇹 Italy - online, Merano </li>
  <li>🇳🇱 Netherlands - Arnhem </li>
  <li>🇨🇭 Switzerland - Zurich</li>
</ul>


<h3 id="invite-public-bodies-to-the-fediverse">Invite public bodies to the Fediverse</h3>

<p>
  <a href="/news/2023/news-20230109-01.html">If public 
  bodies are on social networks they should also talk with Fediverse 
  users</a>. FediGov, the campaign of the FSFE’s Swiss country team and 
  GNU/Linux.ch, asks public bodies to use Mastodon, Pixelfeld and 
  Peertube. Join the campaign and demand that your public institutions 
  use ethical communication channels. The <a href="https://social.network.europa.eu/@EU_Commission">European 
  Commission</a> and several <a href="https://social.network.europa.eu/directory">EU public 
  institutions</a> are already on Mastodon.
</p>

<h3 id="video-and-mailing-list-on-german-municipalities">Video and mailing list on German municipalities</h3>

<p>
  Dortmund is opening a new chapter in Free Software governance and 
  inspiring municipalities across Germany. The recording of the 
  dedicated  event we hosted on 11 January 2023 is now <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/n8e8zKHjMHukYmzb4pEWJQ">online</a>. 
  Are you interested in Free Software and working in a municipal 
  administration or in politics? <a href="/news/2023/news-20230119-01.html">Join our new 
  mailing list</a> to exchange information about Free Software in local 
  institutions!
</p>

<figure>
  <peertube url="https://media.fsfe.org/w/n8e8zKHjMHukYmzb4pEWJQ"/>
</figure>

<h3 id="a-word-from-the-planet">A word from the Planet</h3>

<p>
  Watermarks  that can verify whether a text was produced using AI, the 
  provision of sources that led to the output of the text, or the 
  count of back-references to a page can increase trust in AI- 
  generated texts, <a href="https://vl8r.eu/posts/2023/01/29/artificial-intelligence-is-not-willing-to-be-correct/">according 
  to FSFE suporter Vincent Lequertier</a>. You can follow the thoughts 
  of members of the FSFE community in our <a href="https://planet.fsfe.org/">Planet</a>.
</p>


<h3 id="past-events">Past events</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Last weekend we were at <a href="/news/2023/news-20230123-01.html">FOSDEM 2023</a> with a booth and various talks.</li>
  <li>We have held several Upcycling Android workshops and now it is your turn! Do you want to organise a workshop and teach others how to flash phones? Check out our <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/uZZYCA31SzTT5bMpNaDzz3">train the trainers workshop</a>. Marvin, one of the speakers, said in a recent interview that despite the imperfections so far, <a href="https://www.c-radar.de/2022/12/c-radar-dezember-2022-android-alternativen-hacking-in-parallel/">GNU/Linux systems on phones have the highest potential to extend the life of devices</a> without running into security problems.</li>
  <li>Raul Masu presented ‘Public Money? Public Code!’ at LibreItalia Conference in Empoli 
in December 2022.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="groups">Groups</h3>

<p>
  <strong>Germany</strong>: The <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Bonn">FSFE local group in 
  Bonn</a> met online on 9 January. The group discussed how to make 
  large amounts of data (JSONs) searchable in a browser and how to 
  integrate Free Software Text-To-Speech into a blog. The question of 
  coding without a 'real' computer led to a brief  look at 
  Android IDEs for mobile app development. Kilux and Chemnitzer Linux 
  Tage might be good opportunities to meet besides FrOScon. The group 
  is also interested in free musical instruments, this time featuring 
  an opentheremin. Meanwhile, the FSFE <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Berlin">local group in 
  Berlin</a> was discussing with the youth Free Software in schools and 
  the benefits of the <a href="https://aleksis.org/">AlekSIS</a> 
  system.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Greece</strong>: In January the group discussed practices 
  about <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Greece/2023-01-meeting">translating 
  Free Software into Greek</a>. The group shared collaborative 
  translation platforms and glossaries.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Netherlands</strong>: The government released the code of 
  DigiD, the identity verification app. This great news comes after 
  some months of advocacy by  the team.  <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Events/Netherlands/2023-01-18">This 
  victory was therefore the main topic of the last monthly meeting, in 
  January</a>.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Switzerland</strong>: After a successful launch of the 
  FediGov campaign, the <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Events/Zurich/2023-01-19">Zurich group 
  discussed next steps</a>. Creating a Mastodon instance for public 
  institutions in Switzerland or contacting data protection officers 
  are ongoing ideas.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Women</strong>: In January the FSFE Women group discussed the 
  Python tools <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/Women/Notes">Conda, 
  Poetry, and mypy</a>.
</p>

<p>
  <strong>Translators</strong>: 337 FSFE translations in 2022! Our 
  exceptional <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/Translators">translators team</a>  
  has created 337 new files in 2022. The leader is Italian with 120 new 
  pages, followed by Dutch, German, Spanish, and Portuguese. Get 
  involved by proofreading or translating our material.
</p>

<h2 id="contribute-to-our-newsletter">Contribute to our Newsletter</h2>

<p>
  If you would like to share any thoughts, pictures, or news, please 
  send them to us. As always, the address is <email>newsletter@fsfe.org</email>. 
  We're looking forward to hearing from you! If you also want to 
  support us and our work, join our community and support us with a <a href="https://my.fsfe.org/donate?referrer=newsletter">donation or a 
  monthly contribution</a>. Thanks to our community and all the 
  volunteers, supporters, and donors who make our work possible. And 
  thanks to our translators, who enable you to read this newsletter in 
  your native languages.
</p>
   
<p>Your editor, Fani Partsafyllidou</p>


  </body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/e0/29/ab54fd23aa23910d475412815739.png" alt="Pictures of a person, a heart, and a mastodon in front on of a building"/>
    <link>/news/nl/nl-202302.html</link>
    <tags>
    <tag key="front-page"/>
    <tag key="newsletter">Newsletter</tag>
    <tag key="pmpc">Public Money? Public Code!</tag>
    <tag key="ilovefs">I Love Free Software</tag>
    <tag key="AI">AI</tag>
    <tag key="upcyclingandroid">Upcycling Android</tag>
    <tag key="localgroup">Local group</tag>
    <tag key="de">Germany</tag>
    <tag key="berlin">Berlin</tag>
    <tag key="gr">Greece</tag>
    <tag key="nl">Netherlands</tag>
    <tag key="ch">Switzerland</tag>
    <tag key="women-group">Women group</tag>
      
  </tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/989"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
