<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2022-04-05" type="newsletter">
    <title>AI in EU +++ Open letter to Bundestag +++ Plasma Mobile +++ Meshnet</title>
    <body>
      <p>
    In our April Newsletter, we welcome the promising developments on 
    AI in the EU. We address the German Government to demand a clear 
    budget for Free Software. We interview Plasma Mobile developer 
    Bhushan Shah, and talk with Elektra Wagenrad in a podcast episode 
    about Mesh Networking. We congratulate KDE on the world's first 
    eco-certified software.
  </p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1 id="ai-in-eu-open-letter-to-bundestag-plasma-mobile-meshnet">AI in EU +++ Open letter to Bundestag +++ Plasma Mobile +++ Meshnet</h1>

  <p>
    In our April Newsletter, we welcome the promising developments on 
    AI in the EU. We address the German Government to demand a clear 
    budget for Free Software. We interview Plasma Mobile developer 
    Bhushan Shah, and talk with Elektra Wagenrad in a podcast episode 
    about Mesh Networking. We congratulate KDE on the world's first 
    eco-certified software.
  </p>

<h2 id="european-parliament-recognises-free-software-as-key-for-fair-ai">European Parliament recognises Free Software as key for fair AI</h2>
  
  <p>
    The Special Committee on Artificial Intelligence in a Digital Age 
    (AIDA) of the European Parliament voted on its resolution on 
    Artificial Intelligence in a Digital Age on March 22nd, and 
    underlined the importance of Free Software for AI with a broad 
    majority. We now ask EU co-legislators to take this position into 
    account and to include provisions and guidelines on Free Software 
    in the upcoming legislation.
  </p>

  <p>
    Public authorities using AI systems should make them publicly 
    available. Public research inventing AI systems should make them 
    publicly available. Transparency in AI technologies is necessary to 
    test them, evaluate their results, and improve them. <a href="/news/2022/news-20220330-01.html">The FSFE 
    is following closely the legislative process</a> and analysed <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/campaigns/AIandFS/fsfe_AIandFreesoftware.pdf">how 
    AI can remain verifiable and trustworthy as well as lead to further 
    innovation</a> with Free Software.
  </p>

<h2 id="germany-has-ambitious-free-software-plans-will-it-realise-them-">Germany has ambitious Free Software plans. Will it realise them?</h2>

  <p>
    The coalition agreement of the German government set digitisation 
    as a priority and Free Software as a secure and transparent 
    solution. 100 days into the new German government in office, no 
    action has been taken. On the contrary, German administrations are 
    alarmingly close to using Microsoft products, giving up the chance 
    to adopt a strategy based on open interfaces. Alexander Sander, the 
    FSFE's Policy Consultant, explains: "Instead of finally 
    providing a 'Free Software cloud' for administrations, the 
    new government will again rely on costly proprietary 
    applications." <a href="/news/2022/news-20220315-01.html">We call 
    upon the government to follow its own plans</a>.
  </p>

  <p>
    Specifically, together with other actors such as the Open Source 
    Business Alliance and the Open Knowledge Foundation Germany, the 
    FSFE demands that the German government <a href="/news/2022/news-20220328-01.html">includes 
    digital sovereignty in the 2022 federal budget</a> and implement 
    already announced initiatives for software freedom. In an <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/policy/letters/20220328-German-Budget-and-Free-Software-2022.de.pdf">open 
    letter (DE)</a> the signatories address the government groups in 
    the Bundestag.
  </p>
  
<h2 id="plasma-mobile-running-a-privacy-respecting-and-secure-gnu-linux-phone">Plasma Mobile: Running a privacy-respecting and secure GNU/Linux phone</h2>

  <p>
    What are my options if I want to run my phone with Free Software? 
    We interviewed Plasma Mobile developer Bhushan Shah to learn more 
    about the project. Plasma Mobile is a full Linux-based system which 
    offers a completely transparent development process. When it comes to 
    privacy, Plasma Mobile is one of the most secure operating systems 
    for phones. There is no tracking, spying, nor data mining to craft 
    targeted ads. <a href="/news/2022/news-20220323-01.html">Bhushan 
    gives a clear overview of Plasma Mobile, including how it is 
    developed, and how to get it</a>.
  </p>

  <figure>
    <a href="/news/2022/news-20220323-01.html">
      <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/b9b1f761fd936faa0aab1e11fe3f70bd.jpg" alt="7 people in front of a garden and a building in a summer day"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Bhushan Shah (second from left), developer in the Plasma Mobile project since 2015.
    </figcaption>
  </figure>

<h2 id="listen-to-our-new-podcast-episode-discover-mesh-networking-">Listen to our new podcast episode. Discover mesh networking.</h2>
  
  <p>
    <a href="/news/podcast/episode-14.html">In our new 
    Software Freedom Podcast episode, Matthias Kirschner talks with our 
    guest, Elektra Wagenrad, about the origins of Freifunk, the 
    B.A.T.M.A.N. protocol, and the Mesh Potato project</a>. If you are 
    new to the world of mesh networking this episode is an easy 
    entrance to it. Elektra explains the theory behind the protocols 
    and dives deeper into its philosophical idea.
  </p>

  <figure>
    <a href="/news/podcast/episode-14.html">
      <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/0bf10017e47d8510d09d6058db413290.png" alt="Portrait of a woman smiling"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Elektra Wagenrad, one of the original developers of the 
      B.A.T.M.A.N. protocol and of the Mesh Potato project. Image is 
      licensed under CC-BY-SA 3.0 and created by Andrea Behrendt.
    </figcaption>
  </figure>

<h2 id="the-most-energy-efficient-pdf-reader-is-free-software-congrats-okular-">The most energy-efficient PDF reader is Free Software. Congrats, Okular!</h2>

  <p>
    To be exact, Okular is a universal document viewer. This means you 
    are not only able to read PDFs, comics, and EPub books, but also 
    you can browse your image files, visualize Markdown documents, and 
    much more. In February 2022, Okular was awarded the Blue Angel 
    ecolabel, the official environmental label awarded by the German 
    government. In 1978, the German Environment Agency was the first to 
    establish an environmental label; this year the label's scope 
    was extended to include software products, making Okular the first 
    ️ever eco-certified computer program.
  </p>

  <p>
    In order to receive the Blue Angel ecolabel, a program needs to 
    meet many requirements, including transparency, backwards 
    compatibility, and the ability to run the application on hardware 
    at least five years old. Free Software usually excels in these 
    conditions. The FSFE <a href="/news/2022/news-20220316-01.html">congratulates 
    Okular and all of the KDE community</a>!
  </p>

  <figure>
    <a href="/news/2022/news-20220316-01.html"><img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/bb97d5abf32d0f8f5c38ca7e190c4030.png" alt="Screenshot of comics opened with Okular"/></a>
    <figcaption>
      Screenshot from KDE's Okular, Illustrations from David Revoy CC-BY-SA-4.0
    </figcaption>
  </figure>
  
<h2 id="save-the-date-">Save the date!</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>
      Thursday 14 April is the day of three FSFE local group meetings. 
      At 18:00-21:00 <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Events/Zurich/2022-04-14">Zurich will 
      have its regular in-person monthly meeting</a>. Anyone interested 
      in Free Software and wanting to stand up for the ideals of Free 
      Software can join. The group will discuss ways to reach out to 
      new people and the upcoming Open Education Day. <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Hamburg">Hamburg is 
      having its regular in-person monthly meeting</a> too. Please join 
      the group's mailing list for more information. <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Berlin">Berlin</a> has 
      its regular online monthly meeting. Subscribe to the <a href="https://lists.fsfe.org/postorius/lists/berlin.lists.fsfe.org">mailing 
      list</a> or follow the group's <a href="https://libranet.de/profile/fsfeberlin">Mastodon page</a> 
      to stay tuned.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On Wednesday 20 April, <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/BNL">the FSFE country 
      team Netherlands</a> will have its regular online monthly 
      meeting.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      Date TBA. The FSFE local group Aarhus, Denmark, has delayed its 
      first meeting. If you are interested, now is a great time to 
      contact Carsten Agger (agger [at] fsfe [dot] org).
    </p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-we-have-done">What we have done</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 30 March, Erik Albers, FSFE Programme Manager and 
      sustainability expert, showcased in the Digital Social Summit 
      that software design and Free Software licencing impacts the 
      sustainability of hardware and infrastructure.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 24 March, <a href="https://libranet.de/display/0b6b25a8-2162-39a4-b089-4a2078010682">the 
      FSFE local group Berlin brainstormed with Jessica Wawrzyniak from 
      Digital Courage how an allowlist of suitable Free Software for 
      Education could work</a>, and how the German administration could 
      compile such a list.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 20 March, the FSFE Women group met online to discuss past and 
      future events.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 19 March, the participants of the Upcycling Android workshop 
      flashed phones in Berlin.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 16 March, <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Events/Netherlands/2022-03-16">the 
      FSFE Country team Netherlands had its monthly online meeting</a>. 
      The team discussed the new telecommunications law in Belgium, and 
      the potential actions to secure Router Freedom. The volunteers 
      have already contacted Neutrinet. The government's open 
      source strategy was also an important topic, as well as the 
      increased dependency on DigID, the Dutch digital identity app. On 
      19 March the team met in person in the Netherlands Linux Users 
      meeting.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 15 March, Erik Albers participated in 'Sustainable 
      software for phones that last', a webinar organised by 
      Fairphone. <a href="https://media.fsfe.org/w/4WvPgN79fuex3eaSR378yH">A panel of 
      experts</a> discussed why the longevity of phones continues to 
      decline. Within the panel, Erik took a stand on how the universal 
      right to install Free Software operating systems on any device 
      will help us to live in a more sustainable digital society.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 12 March, Matthias Kirschner, author of Ada &amp; Zangemann, 
      read the book during Chemnitzer Linux-Tage. A video from an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2bHLxFqTnRo">author 
      reading</a> during Wintercongress is now available.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 10 March, <a href="https://libranet.de/display/0b6b25a8-1262-279c-0282-3d4767329405">the 
      FSFE local group Berlin had its monthly meeting</a>. The 
      participants discussed matters of financing and security related 
      to Free Software. The group discussed the recent plans of Mozilla 
      to create privacy-friendly advertising.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 10 March, <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Events/Zurich/2022-03-10">the FSFE 
      local group Zurich discussed ways to reach out to new people, and 
      explored possible actions such as workshops and information 
      events</a>. 
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      On 9 March, the <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Hamburg">FSFE local group 
      Hamburg had its monthly meeting</a>.</p>
  </li>
</ul>


<h2 id="contribute-to-our-newsletter">Contribute to our newsletter</h2>
  <p>
    If you would like to share any thoughts, pictures, or news, please 
    send them to us. As always, the address is <email>newsletter@fsfe.org</email>. 
    We're looking forward to hearing from you! If you also want to 
    support us and our work, join our community and support us with a 
    donation or a monthly contribution <a href="https://my.fsfe.org/donate?referrer=newsletter"/>.
    Thanks to our community and all the volunteers, 
    supporters, and donors who make our work possible. And thanks to 
    our translators, who enable you to read this newsletter in your 
    native languages.
  </p>
  
  <p>Your editor, Fani Partsafyllidou</p>

  </body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/c2f8622627d6d635020e8220380e4225.png" alt="Collage with four images. An illustration of a newspaper. An illustration of a neoclassical building with ones and zeros as its columns. An illustration of three phones depicting screens from Plasma Mobile home page, calendar, and calculator.  A photograph of a woman."/>
    <link>/news/nl/nl-202204.html</link>
    <tags>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
      <tag key="newsletter">Newsletter</tag>
      <tag key="AI">AI</tag>
      <tag key="european-parliament">European Parliament</tag>
      <tag key="open-letter">Open letter</tag>
      <tag key="de">Germany</tag>
      <tag key="upcyclingandroid">Upcycling Android</tag>
      <tag key="interview">Interview</tag>
      <tag key="podcast">Software Freedom Podcast</tag>
      <tag key="localgroup">Local group</tag>
  </tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/825"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
