<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2021-12-14" type="newsletter">
    <title>Upcycling Android ++ Major step for Device Neutrality ++ Nico Rikken + Ada + Job</title>
    <body>
      <p>
    In the December Newsletter we talk about Upcycling Android, an 
    initiative to overcome software obsolescence with Free Software. 
    The EU is voting on the Digital Markets Act, a major step for 
    device neutrality. Germany aims to adopt PMPC! We interview Nico 
    Rikken for 20 Years FSFE. Meet Ada, a character in a children's 
    book. Spot a job opportunity.
  </p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>
	  
<h1>Upcycling Android ++ Major step for Device Neutrality ++ Nico Rikken + Ada + Job</h1>
  
  <p>
    In the December Newsletter we talk about Upcycling Android, an 
    initiative to overcome software obsolescence with Free Software. 
    The EU is voting on the Digital Markets Act, a major step for 
    device neutrality. Germany aims to adopt PMPC! We interview Nico 
    Rikken for 20 Years FSFE. Meet Ada, a character in a children's 
    book. Spot a job opportunity.
  </p>

<h2>Upcycling Android: Keep using your phone with Free Software</h2>
  
  <p>
    In the European Week for Waste Reduction, the FSFE launched its new 
    initiative <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/">"Upcycling 
    Android"</a>: Every time we keep using our phone instead of 
    buying a new one we support a more sustainable use of our 
    resources. Upcycling Android helps people to tackle software 
    obsolescence and to keep using their phones with Free Software.
  </p>
  
  <figure>
      <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/a0da43aac80cf4d611b0a45e2e6a925f.jpg"/>
  </figure>

  <p>
    On the initiative's website, you will find background 
    information and our multi-language video that explains in a 
    nutshell the environmental benefits derived from an extended 
    hardware lifespan by using Free Software. In addition you will find 
    professional <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/informationmaterial.html">information 
    material</a> from infographics to expert talks to our study on the 
    sustainability of Free Software.
  </p>

<h2 id="upcoming-dma-vote-might-be-a-major-victory-for-device-neutrality">Upcoming DMA vote might be a major victory for Device Neutrality</h2>
  <p>
    A potential first success for Device Neutrality is about to be 
    determined. The EU Digital Markets Act (DMA) aims to regulate 
    internet companies that act as gatekeepers in digital markets. Such 
    gatekeepers may be internet platforms, service providers, 
    manufacturers, and vendors satisfying criteria defined by law. The 
    Digital Markets Act is an opportunity to create fairer and more 
    competitive markets for online platforms in the EU. Open Standards 
    and interoperability will secure interests of European consumers as 
    well as facilitate Free Software use and adoption in said markets.
  </p>

  <p>
    As a major checkpoint, the <a href="/news/2021/news-20211122-01.html">four 
    principles we called for</a> were included into the DMA after the 
    Internal Market and Consumer Protection Committee <a href="https://emeeting.europarl.europa.eu/emeeting/committee/en/agenda/202111/IMCO">voted 
    during its meeting on 22 November</a>. All eyes are now turning to 
    the plenary voting for the final position of the European 
    Parliament's first reading on <a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/sed/doc/news/flash/26441/SYN_POJ_December_STRb_EN.pdf">15 
    December 2021</a>. Stay tuned!
  </p>

<h2 id="new-german-government-introduces-public-money-public-code-">New German government introduces 'Public Money? Public Code!'</h2>
  <p>
    Promising news does not end here. The newly formed German 
    government agrees with the FSFE 'Public Money? Public 
    Code!' demand and declares it as <a href="https://mastodon.social/@fsfe/107332820789284114">one of the 
    aims of the coalition</a>. It should be noted that this development 
    did not come out of the blue but only after persistent advocating 
    from the FSFE: giving workshops, working together with local German 
    groups, creating an <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Activities/Bundestagswahl_DE">activity 
    package</a> (DE) for volunteers, conducting <a href="/news/2021/news-20210920-01.html">5 
    interviews</a> (DE) with representatives of German political 
    parties, forming a <a href="https://digitalezivilgesellschaft.org/digitalvisionen/">vision 
    for the upcoming decades and concrete demands for the next 
    government</a> and analysing the <a href="https://digitalezivilgesellschaft.org/wahlpruefsteine/oeffentliches-gut/">election 
    programs of the parties</a>.
  </p>
   
  <p>
    The decision is an important development for the Free Software 
    movement in Germany.  We would like to thank everyone who advocated 
    with us in recent years and helped us arrive at this point. The 
    FSFE will now focus on the implementation of the decision.
  </p>

<h2 id="children-s-book-character-ada-learns-the-power-of-software">Children's book character Ada learns the power of software</h2>  
  <p>
    Ada unravels the mysteries of software in an adventure with her 
    friends, after an unfortunate meeting with the rich and famous 
    inventor Zangemann. A children's book for young and old 
    readers, 'Ada &amp; Zangemann' is a fun and educational 
    tale. Matthias Kirschner, author and FSFE president, conveys to 
    young readers the importance of software, and even the basics of 
    more complex topics around it. The book is published under a 
    Creative Commons license.
  </p>

  <figure>
      <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/b2b23d22357bfc0c568a472b45a56dd3.png"/>
  </figure>
  
  <p>
    'Ada &amp; Zangemann' is in German, and it was just 
    released in Germany. It is already sold out at the publisher, 
    O'Reilly, but you can still get copies from other booksellers. 
    The FSFE is looking for a suitable publisher for an English 
    edition. If you would like to see Ada's story in English and 
    more languages, we welcome <fsfe-cd-donate-link>donations</fsfe-cd-donate-link>.
    "After my son read the book last night, he told me the whole story 
    this morning... He wants to make something out of old pallets after 
    school today. And then he wants to learn programming" said Ingo 
    Wichmann, CEO of Linuxhotel GmbH.
  </p>

<h2 id="an-overview-of-the-past-year-software-freedom-in-2021">An overview of the past year: software freedom in 2021</h2>

  <p>
    Cancelling of large events, limitations in meetings, and travel 
    restrictions: none of this stopped the FSFE from advancing software 
    freedom in 2021. From Router Freedom to new podcast episodes to 
    co-organising the Legal and Policy devroom at FOSDEM, we keep 
    empowering people to control technology. 'Public Money? Public 
    Code!' online workshops were offered to volunteers, and an 
    online Legal and Licensing Workshop for legal experts was 
    organised. The FSFE assisted software projects to become REUSE 
    compliant with our new initiative, REUSE Booster.
  </p>

  <figure>
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/6f6e6a53a5c436a757ccfb9b4eef2706.JPG" alt="Group of people in front of a building"/>
    <figcaption>FSFE Staff after two-day participation in the SFSCon. Bolzano, Italy, November 2021.</figcaption>
  </figure>

  <p>
    Meanwhile, a two-year court case initiated by FSFE supporter Luca 
    Bonissi successfully came to an end, unequivocally recognising the 
    right to a Windows licence refund. Our <a href="/news/2021/news-20211110-01.html">yearly 
    report</a> corresponds to our work during November 2020 - October 
    2021. Overall, significant accomplishments for software freedom 
    marked 2021, the year FSFE is celebrating its 20th anniversary.
  </p>


  <hr/>  
   <p> Thanks to the trust of our supporters, the FSFE counts 20 years. 
   Our stable presence enables us to succeed in lengthy endeavours for 
   software freedom, and to be ready at all times to respond to related 
   developments. We are grateful for the trust of our supporters, and 
   we will keep on empowering people to control technology. To help us, 
   consider <fsfe-cd-donate-link>becoming a supporter</fsfe-cd-donate-link>
   and boost our charitable work for freedom in the information society 
   for the next 20 years. </p> 
  <hr/>

<h2 id="20-years-fsfe-interview-with-nico-rikken-on-country-teams-activities">20 Years FSFE: Interview with Nico Rikken on country teams' activities</h2>

  <p>
    20 Years FSFE is meant to be a celebration of everyone who has 
    accompanied us in the past or still does. In our fifth birthday 
    publication we interviewed Nico Rikken, who has been helping the 
    FSFE with his technical skills while contributing greatly to 
    community building since 2014. With this <a href="/news/2021/news-20211123-01.html">interview</a>, 
    you do not only get to know Nico Rikken, but also the FSFE 
    Netherlands country team, as he is one of their coordinators. How 
    do people start joining a country team? This was one of the 
    questions we asked Nico, and we quote a glimpse of his insight.
  </p>

  <figure>
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/5348a47e91da536190b08858a41f894a.png" alt="Three people talking around a table"/>
    <figcaption>FSFE stand at NLLGG booth in Utrecht. The Netherlands, 2019. </figcaption>
  </figure>

  <p>
    "People somehow gained in interest in Free Software and found 
    the FSFE as the designated party to uphold these values in Europe. 
    Then they found out about the NL country team, joined the mailing 
    list and attended a physical meeting. [...] It highlights the 
    importance of letting people know you exist as a local team, being 
    open to newcomers, and making it easy to join community meetings 
    [...] As we are all volunteers, it is important that our supporters 
    do what they enjoy doing. Most of us have our own topics and 
    efforts we work on, and the country team is a way to align and get 
    support."
  </p>
<h2 id="upcoming-events">Upcoming events</h2>

 <ul>
  <li>
    On 15 December, the <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/BNL">FSFE Netherlands 
    country team</a> will have its monthly online get-together.
  </li>
 </ul>
  
<h2 id="what-we-have-done">What we have done</h2>

  <ul>
    <li>The General Assembly of the FSFE held elections for its Council during its annual meeting on November 26th. Matthias Kirschner, Heiki Lõhmus, and Patrick Ohnewein were <a href="/about/legal/minutes/minutes-2021-11-27.en.pdf">re-elected</a> to the positions of President, Vice-President, and Financial Officer respectively. The Council is elected every two years.</li>
    <li>On 13 December, the FSFE held an online event discussing the <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/campaigns/pmpc/ES/PMPC%20Evento%20Folleto.pdf">modernisation of the public digital infrastructure with public code in Spain</a>. Experts such as Luis Falcón, founder of GNUHealth; Ricardo Muñoz from Lliurex; Alexis Puente Montiel from Pica Pica HackLab; Ana Albalat Martínez and Francesc Busquets representing Linkat; and Aleix Pol Gonzalez, president of KDE, shared their insights.</li>
    <li>On 13 December, the local group of the <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Bonn">FSFE Community Bonn</a> had its regular monthly meeting.</li>
    <li>On 10 December, Lina Ceballos, an FSFE Project Manager, participated at GnuHealthCon21. In her online talk, she showed the role that Free Software played in combatting the pandemic and how it could help overcoming other crises.</li>
    <li>On 7 December, the <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/Women">FSFE Women team</a> had its monthly online meeting and among other topics they discussed the upcoming <a href="https://events.ccc.de/">Remote Chaos Experience</a> event.</li>
    <li>On 1 December, Matthias Kirschner gave an <a href="https://gnulinux.ch/gln017-podcast">interview</a> [DE] about the 'Ada &amp; Zangemann' children's book to GNU/Linux podcast.</li>
  </ul>
  
<h2 id="get-active">Get active</h2>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <p>
        Are you a student in a German university with a technical 
        background? Check out our new <a href="/news/2021/news-20211206-01.html">job 
        posting</a>; it might be a great fit for you. We are looking 
        for a reliable, well-organised member of our technical teams 
        who is keen to learn about old and new technologies.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
		We are also looking for an <a href="/news/2021/news-20211210-01.html">office assistant</a>for 
		20-25 hours per week in our Berlin office. Our ideal candidate 
		has experience as an office administrator, secretary, event 
		organiser, or another relevant administrative role.
      </p>
    </li>
    <li>
      <p>
         Join our Upcycling Android movement and help us get the 
         message out. Discover our <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/informationmaterial.html">information 
         material</a>. We are offering stickers and a leaflet to you at 
         no cost so that you can share them with friends, put them in a 
         community space, or spread them online. Happy holidays from 
         all of us!
       </p>
    </li>
  </ul>

<h2 id="contribute-to-our-newsletter">Contribute to our newsletter</h2>
  <p>
    If you would like to share any thoughts, pictures, or news, please 
    send them to us. As always, the address is <email>newsletter@fsfe.org</email>. 
    We're looking forward to hearing from you! If you also want to 
    support us and our work, join our community and support us with a 
    donation or a <a href="https://my.fsfe.org/donate?referrer=newsletter">monthly 
    contribution</a>. Thanks to our community and all the volunteers, 
    supporters, and donors who make our work possible. And thanks to 
    our translators, who enable you to read this newsletter in your 
    native languages.
  </p>
  
  <p>Your editor, Fani Partsafyllidou</p>

  </body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/6f6e6a53a5c436a757ccfb9b4eef2706.JPG" alt="Group of people in front of a building"/>
    <link>/news/nl/nl-202112.html</link>
    <tags>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
      <tag key="newsletter">Newsletter</tag>
  </tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/777"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
