<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2024-03-05" type="newsletter">
    <title>I love FS celebrations +++ FOSDEM 2024 +++ SFP episode</title>
    <body>
      <p>
Our March newsletter is here! Last month took us to FOSDEM, while ‘I 
Love Free Software Day’ was celebrated all over Europe. We also launched 
a new SFP episode on the state of Free Software and a discussion on 
banking and Software Freedom. Check out some interesting reading and 
event recommendations!
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>I love FS celebrations +++ FOSDEM 2024 +++ SFP episode</h1>

<p>
Our March newsletter is here! Last month took us to FOSDEM, while ‘I 
Love Free Software Day’ was celebrated all over Europe. We also launched 
a new SFP episode on the state of Free Software and a discussion on 
banking and Software Freedom. Check out some interesting reading and 
event recommendations!
</p>

<ul id="toc">
<li><a href="#fosdem-was-a-blast">FOSDEM was a blast!</a></li>
<li><a href="#thanks-to-all-who-made-i-love-free-software-day-2024-a-great-success">Thanks to all who made I Love Free Software Day 2024 a great success!</a></li>
<li><a href="#sfp-the-status-of-free-software-with-karen-sandler-and-alexander-sander">SFP: The status of Free Software with Karen Sandler and Alexander Sander</a></li>
<li><a href="#software-freedom-in-banking">Software Freedom in banking</a></li>
<li><a href="#about-device-neutrality-dma-and-software-licensing">About Device Neutrality, DMA and software licensing</a></li>
<li><a href="#join-our-next-events">Join our next events!</a></li>
<li><a href="#take-action-spread-the-word-about-fedigov">Take action: spread the word about FediGov!</a></li>
<li><a href="#quote-of-the-month">#Quote of the month</a></li>
<li><a href="#contribute-to-our-newsletter">Contribute to our Newsletter</a></li>
</ul>

<figure>
	<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/19/e2/2ae27535a203e9472b8352ba1108.png" alt="Collage picture of a DIY IloveFS heart with lights, FSFE staff and volunteers at our FOSDEM 2024 booth, and an image of a phone with a 2FA app on it"/>
</figure>

<h3 id="fosdem-was-a-blast">FOSDEM was a blast!</h3>
<p>
At the beginning of February, FSFE volunteers and staffers went back to 
Brussels to take part in <a href="https://fosdem.org/2024">FOSDEM 
2024</a> with a booth and talks. While for some of us this has become an 
awesome yearly experience, it was the first time for others. We asked 
one of our interns to share his thoughts about his first time there, but 
we also collected the recordings of the talks and devrooms we were 
involved with.
</p>
<p><a href="/news/2024/news-20240301-01.html">Find out more</a>!</p>

<h3 id="thanks-to-all-who-made-i-love-free-software-day-2024-a-great-success">Thanks to all who made I Love Free Software Day 2024 a great success!</h3>
<p>
Together with hundreds of people and several organisations, we have 
celebrated another “<a href="https://ilovefs.org/">I Love Free Software 
Day</a>” on 14 February! On this day, we reached out to Free Software 
contributors to say “Thank you!” To all who joined us this time: Thank you 
for participating in this 14<sup>th</sup> edition of the “I Love Free Software Day” 
❤️❤️❤️!
</p>
<p>Read <a href="/news/2024/news-20240226-01.html">the report</a>!</p>

<h3 id="sfp-the-status-of-free-software-with-karen-sandler-and-alexander-sander">SFP: The status of Free Software with Karen Sandler and Alexander Sander</h3>
<p>
Have there been any changes for Free Software in Europe or the USA in 
the last year? How is Free Software viewed by legislators? What can we 
do to Support Software Freedom? Karen Sandler and Alexander Sander are 
active in the Free Software movement and share their views on the 
current status of Free Software in our society.
</p>
<p><a href="/news/podcast/episode-24.html">Listen to it</a> now!</p>

<h3 id="software-freedom-in-banking">Software Freedom in banking</h3>
<p>
Are you forced to use proprietary applications when dealing with your 
bank? What is the relationship between banking applications and Free 
Software? Our staff member Florian Snow has been 
researching this topic and found that banks are pushing the development 
and use of proprietary applications for two-factor 
authentification. In doing so, they are restricting users' freedom to 
choose a one-time password generator of their choice.
</p>
<p>
Read more and take part in <a href="https://lists.fsfe.org/pipermail/discussion/2024-February/013383.html">the 
discussion on the mailing list</a> and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@floriansnow/111980368441061603">on the 
fediverse</a>!
</p>

<h3 id="about-device-neutrality-dma-and-software-licensing">About Device Neutrality, the DMA, and software licensing</h3>
<p>
In recent years, the FSFE team has been working for <a href="/activities/deviceneutrality/">Device Neutrality</a>, 
promoting ways to re-empower users to control their devices by running 
Free Software on them. With the upcoming entrance into force of the latest 
EU legislation on this area – the Digital Markets Act – policy makers 
are interested in the strategies adopted by large tech corporations 
(gatekeepers) to comply with the DMA. The FSFE was contacted by the 
Headquarters for Digital Market Competition of Japan (HDMC) regarding 
Apple’s strategy to comply with the DMA and its impact on Free Software. 
Our staff prepared a study in collaboration with F-Droid. You can read 
the <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/device-neutrality/fsfe-apple-report-final.pdf">
report here</a> (PDF).
</p>
<p>
In regard to the DMA, we also recommend reading a paper 
that our Legal Programme Manager, Lucas Lasota, has published <a href="https://edoc.hu-berlin.de/handle/18452/28971">linking the DMA, 
Free Software, and freedom of terminal equipment</a>. This study puts 
into perspective the role Free Software has in facilitating the process of 
achieving fairness and contestability of digital markets. As a case 
study, this article presents the recent regulatory developments 
involving routers and modems in the EU, and the interaction telecom 
operators’ monopolistic practices have with Free Software.
</p>
<p>
Last but not least, the FSFE has also provided an in-depth analysis of 
the compliance workflow adopted for the Next Generation Internet (NGI) 
initiative. The study analyzes the <a href="https://edoc.hu-berlin.de/handle/18452/28972">compliance issues 
software projects may face during their implementation of Free Software 
licenses</a>. This article concludes with the lessons learned from the 
experience gathered in the three years of implementation of the 
compliance workflow established for the NGI initiative, and especially 
notes how <a href="http://reuse.software/">REUSE</a> plays a 
game-changing role in this context.
</p>
<p>Please share these publications to strengthen our efforts towards Software Freedom!</p>

<h3 id="join-our-next-events">Join our next events!</h3>
<p>
For first time, we are participating in the <a href="https://circonomiafano.it/">Circonomia Festival</a> in Fano (PU), 
Italy. There, we will be hosting, from 8 to 10 March, <a href="https://tommi.space/fedilab">a workshop</a> on decentralized and 
sustainable networks and Free Software, and a reading of the book “<a href="https://ada.fsfe.org/">Ada &amp; Zangemann</a>” in Italian. You 
are welcome to join us any of the three days! Find out more in <a href="/events/#event-20240308-01">the event page</a>.
</p>
<p>
A weekend later, on 16 and 17 March, you can meet as in the <a href="https://chemnitzer.linux-tage.de/">Chemnitzer Linux Days</a>! One 
more year we are attending this long-standing event for education about 
Linux and Free Software. We will be present with an information booth, 
and on Saturday, the FSFE’s Policy Project Manager, Johannes Näder, will 
present <a href="http://yh4f.org/">Youth Hacking 4 Freedom</a>, the Free 
Software competition for young people aged 14-18, currently in its 
third edition.
</p>
<p>
And if you are in Utrecht that Saturday, on 16 March, stop by at our 
info booth at the national <a href="https://nllgg.nl">Dutch Linux Users Group (NLLGG) meeting!</a>
</p>
<p>Remember that you can find all the information about our events at <a href="/events/">events.fsfe.org</a>.</p>

<h3 id="take-action-spread-the-word-about-fedigov">Take action: spread the word about FediGov!</h3>
<p>
<a href="https://fedigov.eu/">FediGov</a> is an initiative by the FSFE 
Swiss local group, together with GNU/Linux.ch, which aims to raise 
awareness among public institutions to use federated Free Software 
solutions to communicate with the public.
</p>
<p>
<a href="/news/2023/news-20230109-01.html">This campaign</a> 
encourages individuals to ask their governments to adopt federated 
and decentralized communications by explaining to their local 
authorities the importance of sovereign communications in the public 
sector.
</p>
<p>
You can help by spreading the word at the local level, but also by 
contributing to the website with translations or improvements! <a href="https://fedigov.eu/#section6_id">Take action!</a>
</p>

<h3 id="quote-of-the-month">Quote of the month</h3>
<blockquote>
<p>I think the best thing about YH4F is that it promotes Free Software 
alternatives to people who haven’t had the chance to realize the 
benefits of such projects. I use Free Software pretty frequently, 
especially when it comes to operating systems.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Alexia, <a href="https://yh4f.org/">Youth Hacking 4 Freedom</a> 2022 participant</p>

<h3 id="contribute-to-our-newsletter">Contribute to our Newsletter</h3>
<p>
We would love to hear from you. If you have any thoughts, pictures, or 
news to share, please send them to us at newsletter@fsfe.org. You can 
also <a href="/donate/donate.html">support us</a>, <a href="/contribute/contribute.html">contribute to our work</a>, and <a href="/about/groups.html">join our community</a>. We would like to thank 
our community and all the volunteers, supporters, and donors who make 
our work possible, with a special mention to our translators who make it 
possible for you to read this newsletter in your mother tongue.
</p>
<p>Your editors,<br/>
Ana and Tommi</p>
</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/19/e2/2ae27535a203e9472b8352ba1108.png" alt="Collage picture of a DIY IloveFS heart with lights, FSFE staff and volunteers at our FOSDEM 2024 booth, and an image of a phone with a 2FA app on it"/>
    <link>/news/nl/nl-202403.html</link>
    <tags>
	<tag key="front-page"/>
	<tag key="newsletter">Newsletter</tag>
	<tag key="fosdem">FOSDEM</tag>
	<tag key="podcast">Software Freedom Podcast</tag>
	<tag key="ilovefs">I love Free Software</tag>
	<tag key="ngi">Next Generation Internet</tag>
	<tag key="deviceneutrality">Device Neutrality</tag>
	<tag key="policy">European Public Policy</tag>
	<tag key="event">Event</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1135"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
