<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rss PUBLIC 
 "-//Netscape Communications//DTD RSS 0.91//EN"
 "http://my.netscape.com/publish/formats/rss-0.91.dtd">

 <!--  <!DOCTYPE rss SYSTEM "rss-0.91.dtd"> -->

 <rss version="0.91">
  <channel>
    <copyright>
      Copyright (C) 2002,2001 FSFE France -
      Verbatim copying and distribution of this entire article is
      permitted in any medium, provided this notice is preserved.
    </copyright>
    <docs>http://france.fsfeurope.org/server/server.en.html#Publishing%20News</docs>
<!-- Suppressed because DTD specification requires rfc-822 date format -->
<!--     <pubDate>$Date$</pubDate> -->
<!--     <lastBuildDate>$Date$</lastBuildDate> -->
    <description>
      Fresh news from the Free Software world in France.  
      News about Free Software and implication of FSFE France in
      technical actions, media, politics, philosophy towards defending
      and promoting Free Software.
    </description>
    <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/news.en.html</link>
    <title>FSFE France News</title>
    <managingEditor>raph@r4f.org (Raphaël Rousseau)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>webmasters@fsfeurope.org (FSF Europe Webmaster Team)</webMaster>
    <language>en-us</language>

<!-- To insert URLs in the <description>, use this :
&lt;a href="http://url"&gt;text&lt;/a&gt;
-->


    <item>
      <title>LSM: Copyright, law and legal maintainability</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2002-07-11-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	11 July 2002. Georg Greve covered an often neglected aspect of
	Free Software: it's legal maintainability. The current methods
	for ensuring legal protection and the dynamic nature of the legal
	system were discussed in detail.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>LSM: The concept of libre publisher</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2002-07-10-02.en.html</link>
      <description>
	10 July 2002. Ismael Olea learnt about editing books in
	classic ways. It offers many solutions to the problems of
	on-line editing. Electronic books are different but the
	process so similar that we can reuse the methodology.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>FSF Europe completes successful first year</title>
      <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2002q2/000042.html</link>
      <description>
      27 May 2002. The Free Software Foundation Europe (FSF Europe)
      finishes its second general assembly, completing the first year
      of activities. Members from Sweden, Italy, Germany and France
      drew a summary of last years activities, analyzed the current
      situation of Free Software and exchanged plans and visions for
      the upcoming year.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>FSF Europe recommendation for the 6th EU framework programme</title>
      <link>http://fsfeurope.org/documents/fp6/reasoning.en.html</link>
      <description>
	30 April 2002. FSF Europe and more than 40 European companies,
	organizations, research centers and projects sent a
	recommendation advocating for Free Software.  This document
	explains some of the reasons why Free Software should be
	included in the considerations on the 6th European Community
	framework programme 2002-2006 and gives input on how this
	could be done.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>EUCD and the first LiLiT meeting</title>
      <link>http://www.fsfeurope.org/news/article2002-04-26-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	29 April 2002. A short report of the first LiLiT meeting.  I
	was specially impressed by the talk about EUCD. Alexandre
	Dulaunoy (activist of the &lt;a
	href="http://www.ael.be/"&gt;AEL&lt;/a&gt;) clearly explained 
	how and why it is harmful. 
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>European Copyright Directive Alert</title>
      <link>http://www.lonix.org.uk/tnet-cgi/Lonix?CODE=userMeetings</link>
      <description>
	28 April 2002. On Monday 29 April 2002, at 6pm in London, we
	  invite you to join the &lt;i&gt; European Copyright
	  Directive Alert &lt;/i&gt; miniconference. Organized by
	  &lt;a href="http://uk.eurorights.org/"&gt;Campaign for
	  Digital Rights &lt;/a&gt; it will explain the dangers of
	  &lt;a href="http://www.fsfeurope.org/law/eucd/"&gt;EUCD&lt;/a&gt;. If we don't stop
	  it before December 2002, it will become legal in each
	  European country.
        </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Free Software Foundation Announces Support of the Affero
      General Public License, the First Copyleft License for Web
      Services</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/press/2002-03-19-Affero.html</link>
      <description>
	19 March 2002. The Free Software Foundation (FSF) announces
	support for and invites public comment on the first public
	license designed to protect software distributed as web
	services: the Affero General Public License (AGPL). The AGPL
	combines the GNU General Public License (GNU GPL) V2 with one
	additional provision to address software used by the public
	over a network. The new provision enables the author to ensure
	that users will have the right to use, study, copy, modify,
	and redistribute that software, by providing a mechanism for
	downloading the source and restricting the removal of the
	mechanism.
        </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Free Software Foundation Offers Resources to the Digital Speech Project</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/press/2002-03-18-digitalspeech.html</link>
      <description>
	18 March 2002. The Free Software Foundation (FSF) today
	heralded the launch of the Digital Speech Project: an effort
	to encourage and coordinate activism to protect our digital
	freedoms in light of the Digital Millennium Copyright Act
	(DMCA) and similar laws. The FSF has hired a Digital Freedom
	Organizer, Jonathan Watterson, to work actively on the the
	Digital Speech Project.
        </description>
    </item>


    <item>
      <title>Collusion Discovered between BSA and European
      Commission. Who is the EC is really working for ?</title>
      <link>http://petition.eurolinux.org/pr/pr17.html</link>
      <description>
	21 February 2002. The European Commission approved this
	wednesday a proposal of directive on software
	patents. Incidentally, the author of this document, according
	to the Microsoft Word file, is Francisco Mingorance, patent
	expert and director of public policy at BSA (Business Software
	Alliance), an association which represents the interests of
	large US software publishers in Europe.
        </description>
    </item>


    <item>
      <title>Guido van Rossum Awarded the Free Software Foundation Award for the Advancement of Free Software</title>
      <link>http://www.fsf.org/press/2002-02-16-FSF-Award.html</link>
      <description>
	18 February 2002. The Free Software Foundation (FSF) bestowed
	on saturday February the 16th its fourth annual FSF Award for
	the Advancement of Free Software. FSF President and founder,
	Richard Stallman, presented the award to Guido van Rossum for
	inventing and implementing as Free Software the Python
	programming language. The award ceremony was hosted at the
	Free and Open Source Software Developers' Meeting (FOSDEM) in
	collaboration with the Free Software Foundation Europe.
     </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Moral report on activities of APRIL in 2001</title>
      <link>http://www.april.org/articles/divers/rapport-moral-2001.html.en</link>
      <description>
	25 January 2002. During the year 2001, APRIL and FSFE France progressed
	in a symbiotic way. The moral report is a short summary of all technical projects,
	press contacts, political contacts etc. It gives a global view and we hope
	it will encourage many activists to strenghen Free Software in the year
	to come.
     </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>ANSOL becomes associated organization of the FSF Europe</title>
      <link>http://www.fsfeurope.org/news/article2002-01-18-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	18 January 2002. « This collaboration is a very important step
	for the Portuguese and European free software
	community. Problems faced by the free software community in
	Portugal are similar to those faced in other European
	countries; by joining forces with FSFE we can solve this
	problems more efficiently » said Jaime Villate, founding member
	of ANSOL.
     </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Brave GNU World issue #34</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-34.en.html</link>
      <description>
	23 December 2001. The latest issue of Georg's &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/intro.en.html"&gt;Brave
	Gnu world&lt;/a&gt; is out. This month's items : BZFlag,
	Arkanae, XShipWars, TRAMP, Kopi, CDArgs, and CDLoop. &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-34.en.html"&gt;Read
	the article&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Brave GNU World issue #33</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-33.en.html</link>
      <description>
	29 November 2001. The latest issue of Georg's &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/intro.en.html"&gt;Brave
	Gnu world&lt;/a&gt; is out. This month's items : GNU grep, GNU
	UnRTF, QTreeMap, Dap, GNUComm, GNU ccRTP, GNU ccAudio and
	ccScript. &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-33.en.html"&gt;Read
	the article&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>German Government and Software Patents</title>
      <link>http://swpat.ffii.org/vreji/papri/bmwi-fhgmpi01/indexen.html</link>
      <description>
	25 November 2001. Various online newspapers loudly claim that
	the German government is on the side of people who are against
	software patents (&lt;a
	href="http://fr.news.yahoo.com/011121/35/2a0op.html"&gt;yahoo&lt;/a&gt;,
	&lt;a
	href="http://www.vnunet.fr/actu/article.htm?numero=8803"&gt;vnunet&lt;/a&gt;,
	&lt;a
	href="http://www.zdnet.com/zdnn/stories/news/0,4586,2826171,00.html"&gt;zdnet&lt;/a&gt;
	etc.). It turns out to be very misleading, as explained in the
	&lt;a
	href="http://swpat.ffii.org/vreji/papri/bmwi-fhgmpi01/"&gt;FFII
	article&lt;/a&gt; on the subject. It is to be noted that the FFII
	article is the only one to link to the &lt;a
	href="http://www.sicherheit-im-internet.de/themes/themes.phtml?ttid=2&amp;amp;tsid=333"&gt;actual
	statement&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>RMS week in Paris</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-11-21-01.fr.html</link>
      <description>
	24 November 2001. Richard Stallman came for a short visit in
	Paris, from 20 to 23 November 2001. This document is not 
	a report. It is an outline of his activities and pointers
	to the corresponding articles and reports.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>ZDNet: Advocates against software patents go further</title>
      <link>http://fr.news.yahoo.com/011121/7/2a34r.html</link>
      <description>
	21 November 2001. This news, written in french, says that
	many initiatives to reverse the tendency toward the patentibility 
	of software are launched by the Free Software Foundation Europe.
	It cites the recent meeting between Noël Mamère (french deputy
	of the green party and candidate to the presidential election)
	and Richard Stallman.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Exceptional visit of Richard Stallman in Paris</title>
      <link>http://www.april.org/articles/communiques/pr-20011119.html</link>
      <description>
	19 November 2001. Richard M. Stallman, considered to be
	the founder of the Free Software movement, founder and president
	of the &lt;a href="http://www.fsf.org/"&gt;Free Software
	Foundation&lt;/a&gt; and initiator of the GNU project in 1983,
	will be in Paris during this week. He will attend various
	events during his visit.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>SourceForge drifting</title>
      <link>http://www.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-10-20-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	11 November 2001.  Over the past few months the &lt;a
	  href="http://www.sourceforge.net/"&gt;SourceForge&lt;/a&gt;
	  development facility, which hosts a large number of &lt;a
	  href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html"&gt;Free
	  Software&lt;/a&gt; projects, has changed its policies. Features
	  for exporting a project from SourceForge have been
	  removed. The implementation used to be exclusively Free
	  Software but is now based
	  on non-free software. Finally, VA Linux has become
	  rather underhand in their attempts to grasp exclusive
	  control of contributors' work. SourceForge did a lot of good
	  for the Free Software community, but it's now time to break
	  free.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Juridical Coup at the European Patent Office</title>
      <link>http://petition.eurolinux.org/pr/pr14.html</link>
      <description>
	7 November 2001.  Press release from EuroLinux : Juridical
Coup at the European Patent Office. EuroLinux demands European
governments to replace the current board of the European Patent Office
and to strengthen democratic control
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Free Software in Portugal</title>
      <link>http://www.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-10-26-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	30 October 2001.  On October 12th, the city of Porto hosted
	  the second edition of &lt;a
	  href="http://www.cidadetecnologica.org/workshops.htm"&gt;Porto
	  Cidade Tecnológica 2001&lt;/a&gt;, an event dedicated to
	  Free Software in Portugal.  In an old market slightly above
	  the river, a conference room was installed in the
	  center. Booths, cyber cafe and install parties surrounded
	  it. The city of Porto provided the organisational
	  infrastructure and many people supported the initiative.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Brave GNU World issue #32</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-32.en.html</link>
      <description>
	26 October 2001. The latest issue of Georg's &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/intro.en.html"&gt;Brave
	Gnu world&lt;/a&gt; is out. This month's items : Ganesha's
	Projekt (Free Software helps stopping child labor in Nepal),
	Logidee-tools (more efficient creation of courses and
	tutorials), HTMLDOC (making information accessible based on
	HTML), GNU Passwords On Card (store your passwords in a secure
	way) and Sketch (Free Software vector drawing &amp;amp; a new way of
	support). &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-32.en.html"&gt;Read
	the article&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>GNU GPL and European Law</title>
      <link>http://www.advogato.org/article/356.html</link>
      <description>
	24 October 2001.  An interesting debate between Luke Kenneth
	Casson Leighton and Bruce Perens focused on a
	misinterpretation of the GNU GPL and European Copyright
	Law. It tells us that these issues require a deep
	understanding of the legal system.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Public announcement of the creation of ANSOL</title>
      <link>http://www.ansol.org/docs/lancamento.en.html</link>
      <description>
	13 October 2001.  The creation of the &lt;a href="http://www.ansol.org/ansol.en.html"&gt;National Association for
	Free Software&lt;/a&gt; (in Portuguese: Associação Nacional para o
	Software Livre), ANSOL, was made on Friday October 12th, at 2001's
	edition of &lt;a href="http://www.cidadetecnologica.org"&gt;Oporto,
	Technological City&lt;/a&gt;, in the northern Portuguese city of Oporto.
      The announcement was made by a group of free software advocates who
	have been working during the last months towards the participation of
      Portugal in the recently created &lt;a href="http://www.fsfeurope.org"&gt;Free
	Software Foundation Europe&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Free Japan visiting Paris</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-10-10-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	10 October 2001.  Masayuki Ida (ida@sipeb.aoyama.ac.jp) arrived
	  in Paris Saturday 6 October for a short stay. He was coming
	  from Dusseldorf and departed to London two days after. He
	  flied from Japan for a European tour of Free Software
	  organizations.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The GNU has come of age</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-09-26-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	26 September 2001. The french chapter of FSF Europe wishes to
	celebrate in this very year 2001 the announcement of the GNU
	project 18 years ago on September 1983 the 27th.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Brave GNU World issue #31</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-31.en.html</link>
      <description>
	18 September 2001. The latest issue of Georg's &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/intro.en.html"&gt;Brave
	Gnu world&lt;/a&gt; is out. This month's items : Free games,
	XWeb, GSP, GNU Classpath and IDX-PKI. &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-31.en.html"&gt;Read
	the article&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Free Software Experts</title>
      <link>http://www.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-08-23-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	26 August 2001. Have you ever been depressed, possibly more than once, to
	    discover that a so called &lt;a
	    href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.fr.html"&gt;Free
	    Software&lt;/a&gt; project was financed despite the fact that
	    it had nothing to do with Free Software? Europe will soon
	    be financing new projects and you could help prevent
	    similar travesties by becoming &lt;a
	    href="http://candidature.cordis.lu/expert-evaluators/"&gt;External
	    Experts&lt;/a&gt;. It will then be more difficult to claim that
	    nothing could be done: your skills are required to
	    validate the candidate projects.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Hourtin Summer University</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-08-22-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	22 August 2001. A round table on Free Software was organized by the
	annual &lt;a
	href="http://www.crepac.com/calendrier/evenement.asp?numero=327"&gt;summer
	university at Hourtin&lt;/a&gt;, France. This event is the
	traditional meeting where government officials meet with
	companies and non profit organizations on the general subject
	of information society. Frédéric Couchet managed for us to
	be invited at the round table to speak in the name of the Free
	Software movement.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>FSFE France activity report</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-08-20-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	20 August 2001. The activities of FSFE France from June to
	August cover contacts with Free Software organizations world
	wide and actions in the field of education, law and
	science. We help the GNU project to grow and benefit from
	it. The happy crowd of volunteers is growing and get involved
	in important and gratuitous tasks, depending on their mood.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Brave GNU World issue #30</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-30.en.html</link>
      <description>
	16 August 2001. The latest issue of Georg's &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/intro.en.html"&gt;Brave
	Gnu world&lt;/a&gt; is out. This month's items : TINY, GNU
	TeXmacs, CD-ROM Control, Saxogram, GNU libiconv, Mozart/Oz,
	Free Software and 3D. &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-30.en.html"&gt;Read
	the article&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Brave GNU World issue #29</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-29.en.html</link>
      <description>
	15 August 2001. We forgot to tell you that the previous issue
	of Georg's &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/intro.en.html"&gt;Brave
	Gnu world&lt;/a&gt; was out. Last month's items : GCompris,
	FSFE - Free Software and Education, Chemical Development Kit,
	Alma, libgcrypt. &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-29.en.html"&gt;Read
	the article&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Press Review about Free Software : first parcel successfully sent</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/collecte.en.html</link>
      <description>
      30 July 2001. A first set of articles about Free Software
      reached the FSF.  Collecting articles in France and adding them
      to the archives at the FSF (Boston, USA) is a very workable
      &lt;a
      href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/collecte.en.html"&gt;system&lt;/a&gt;. Your
      contributions are welcome, even during holidays ;). A &lt;a
      href="http://mail.gnu.org/mailman/listinfo/fsfe-france-pr"&gt;mailing
      list&lt;/a&gt; is now available.
      </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geographical representation of Free Software Developpers</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/coposys/</link>
      <description>
	22 July 2001. A tool allowing geographical representation of
	Free Software Developpers on a terrestrial globe map is now
	available &lt;a
	href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/coposys/index.en.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Transcription of Richard Stallman's conference at NYU</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/events/rms-nyu-2001-transcript.txt</link>
      <description>
	22 July 2001. A transcription of Richard M. Stallman's &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/audio/audio.html#NYU2001"&gt;conference
	at NYU&lt;/a&gt; given on May 29th 2001 is &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/events/rms-nyu-2001-transcript.txt"&gt;available
	here&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Electronic voting and Free Software</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/voting/voting.en.html</link>
      <description>
	21 July 2001. Although the subject of electronic voting is frequently
	raised in various countries, both for votes on a nation wide
	scale and votes in companies, it is rarely associated with
	Free Software. 
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Richard Stallman inaugurates Free Software
      Foundation-India, first affiliate in asia of the Free Software
      Foundation</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/press/2001-07-20-FSF-India.html</link>
      <description>
	20 July 2001. Richard M.  Stallman today officially
	launched the Free Software Foundation of India (&lt;a
	href="http://www.fsf.org.in"&gt;FSF-India&lt;/a&gt;),
	the first affiliate in Asia of the Free Software Foundation
	with a speech at the Freedom First! Conference on Free
	Software in Trivandrum, Kerala, India.  Yesterday, he was
	received as an honored state guest by government officials to
	discuss the philosophy behind the movement and the use of free
	software as a viable, cost-effective alternative for
	government, educational institutions, and businesses, as well
	as for all the people of India.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Libre Software Meeting - Photos from some FSF and/or GNU
      project related people</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-07-09-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	9 July 2001. Some photos taken during the second &lt;a
	      href="http://lsm.abul.org"&gt;Libre Software Meeting&lt;/a&gt;
	      (Bordeaux, France) with FSF and/or GNU project related
	      people are available.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>AAUL meeting at LSM</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-07-05-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	5 July 2001. The AAUL is the Association Africaine des Utilisateurs
	de Logiciels Libres (Free Software Users African
	Association). The second L is missing from the acronym. The
	organization used the &lt;a href="http://lsm.abul.org/"&gt;LSM&lt;/a&gt;
	meeting as an opportunity to report what was done during the
	past year. The FSF Europe was there to propose help.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Free Software organizations at LSM</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-07-04-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	4 July 2001. People involved in Free Software organizations in Italy,
	Portugal, United States, Canada and France went for diner in
	the old town of Bordeaux (France) after the sessions of &lt;a
	href="http://lsm.abul.org/"&gt;LSM&lt;/a&gt;
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>The GNU project and its contributors received the 2001 USENIX Lifetime Achievement Award.</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/press/2001-06-28-USENIX.html</link>
      <description>
	28 June 2001. The GNU project and its contributors received
	the 2001 USENIX Lifetime Achievement Award. On behalf of all
	GNU contributors, Robert J. Chassell accepted the award at the
	2001 USENIX Annual Technical Conference at the Copley Marriott
	Hotel in Boston, MA, USA. A copy of the &lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/events/bob-usenix-lifetime-accept.txt"&gt;acceptance speech&lt;/a&gt;, and
	a copy of the
	&lt;a href="http://www.gnu.org/events/bob-usenix-press-conference.txt"&gt;press
	conference statements&lt;/a&gt; are available.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Press review: collect articles about Free Software</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/collecte.en.html</link>
      <description>
	27 June 2001. The FSFE France launch an appeal for &lt;a
        href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/collecte.en.html"&gt;contribution
        to collect articles about Free Software&lt;/a&gt; for the
        FSF. What we are looking for are articles that say something
        new; go into great depth about an aspect; consider the wider
        social or legal meanings; give a good overview of the subject;
        talk about the history in depth; or other well-written pieces.
        Something that is just so-so or just says the same-old-thing
        would not really contribute to our collection.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>A software against software patents</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-06-26-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	26 June 2001. Richard M. Stallman (President of the &lt;a
	href="http://www.fsf.org/"&gt;FSF&lt;/a&gt;) and Jacques Le
	Marois (CEO
	of &lt;a
	href="http://www.mandrakesoft.com/"&gt;MandrakeSoft&lt;/a&gt;)
	met in Paris to talk about software patents.
	Richard M. Stallman suggested to Jacques Le Marois that a
	detailed information about the dangers of software patents be
	displayed to every user of a Mandrake distribution. The user
	would then be given the choice to declare readiness to take part in
	some actions against software patents. 
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Workshop adaptation/translation in french of the GNU GPL
        during the Libre Software Meeting (FSFE France PR)</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/press/pr-gpl-lsm.en.html</link>
      <description>
	19 June 2001. During the &lt;a
	href="http://lsm.abul.org"&gt;Libre Software Meeting&lt;/a&gt;
	(Bordeaux, France, July 4-8 2001), in the topic &lt;a
	href="http://lsm.abul.org/program/topic16/topic16.php3"&gt;"Law,
	Economy, Politic and libre software"&lt;/a&gt;, a workshop
	will take place to let all the people involved in the
	translation/adaptation in French of the &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"&gt;GNU
	GPL&lt;/a&gt; to meet and discuss.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Brave GNU World issue #28</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-28.en.html</link>
      <description>
	19 June 2001. The latest issue of Georg's &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/intro.en.html"&gt;Brave
	Gnu world&lt;/a&gt; is out. This month's items : TuxFamily.org
	(a European Sourceforge alternative), Chrooted SSH CVS-Server
	HOWTO, AutoGen (repeated C sourcecode made easy), Free
	Software and Commercialization (is it okay to make money with
	Free Software?). &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-28.en.html"&gt;Read
	the article&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>First meeting of the members of the FSFE-Portugal mailing list</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-06-19-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	19 June 2001. Minutes of the first physical meeting of the
	members of the FSFE-Portugal mailing list.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>GNU Compiler Collection Version 3.0 Is Released; Includes
      Support for Java and IA-64 (FSF PR)</title>
      <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2001q2/000009.html</link>
      <description>
	19 June 2001. Boston, Massachusetts, USA - Monday, June 18,
	2001 - The Free Software Foundation announced today the 3.0
	release of the GNU Compiler Collection (GCC).  GCC is a Free
	(as in freedom) Software compiler toolset, licensed under the
	GNU General Public License (GPL).
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>CoopX : standard format to exchange information on projects hosting systems</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-06-14-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	14 June 2001. The goal of &lt;a
	href="http://coopx.eu.org/"&gt;CoopX&lt;/a&gt; is to define a standard
	format based on XML to exchange information on projects hosted
	by facilities such as &lt;a
	href="http://www.sourceforge.net"&gt;SourceForge&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
	href="http://serveur-libre.enst-bretagne.fr/"&gt;Serveur
	Libre&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.tuxfamily.org/"&gt;tuxfamily&lt;/a&gt;,
	&lt;a href="http://savannah.gnu.org/"&gt;Savannah&lt;/a&gt;. With this
	format a project maintainer could migrate his project from one
	hosting platform to the other or mirror it.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Activity in fsfe-portugal list</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-06-11-02.en.html</link>
      <description>
	11 June 2001. Activity report from the members of the list
	fsfe-portugal@gnu.org (list of open discussions about FSF
	Europe and Portugal). 	The members of the list fsfe-portugal have taken the first
	steps towards the goal of forming a support association for a
	future Chapter of the &lt;a
	href="http://www.fsfeurope.org/"&gt;FSFE&lt;/a&gt; in Portugal.

      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>US Internet Patents to be Enforced in EU ? (Eurolinux PR)</title>
      <link>http://petition.EuroLinux.org/pr/pr11.html</link>
      <description>
	08 June 2001. This press release of the &lt;a
	href="http://petition.EuroLinux.org/"&gt;Eurolinux&lt;/a&gt;
	alliance warns us against the Hague convention draft that
	would provide legal grounds for global internet censorship and
	the extension of american software patents to Europe, among
	other cool things. Many dnagerous threats for Free Software.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>GNU Project and GET about projects hosting systems (french)</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-05-29-01.fr.html</link>
      <description>
	29 May 2001. The GNU project and the GET (&lt;a
	href="http://www.enst.fr/"&gt;ENST&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
	href="http://www.enstb.fr/"&gt;ENST Bretagne&lt;/a&gt; and
	&lt;a href="http://www.int-evry.fr/"&gt;INT Evry&lt;/a&gt;)
	had a meeting today to define a cooperation field about
	development and rollover of hosting systems ala SourceForge.
	The GNU project is using the &lt;a
	href="http://savannah.gnu.org/"&gt;Savannah&lt;/a&gt; platform
	and the GET the &lt;a
	href="http://serveur-libre.enstb.fr/"&gt;serveur
	libre&lt;/a&gt; one (article in french).
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>FSF, APRIL, FSFE France and GNU working together</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-05-28-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	28 May 2001. On May 21, 2001 &lt;a
	href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/"&gt;FSFE France&lt;/a&gt;
	shipped me (&lt;a href="mailto:loic@gnu.org"&gt;Loïc
	Dachary&lt;/a&gt;) to Boston. I was to install a new set of
	hardware for the &lt;a
	href="http://savannah.gnu.org/"&gt;Savannah&lt;/a&gt;
	development tool. In the plane back to Paris I realized that
	this week was so intense that you'd probably like to share
	some bits of it with me. (Update : see the &lt;a
	href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-05-28-01/"&gt;pictures
	of the trip&lt;/a&gt;)
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>FSFE France News available by mail</title>
      <link>http://mail.gnu.org/mailman/listinfo/fsfe-newsfr-en</link>
      <description>
	28 May 2001. The news published by FSFE France are now
	dispatched on a daily basis by mail on the &lt;a
	href="http://mail.gnu.org/mailman/listinfo/fsfe-newsfr-en"&gt;fsfe-newsfr-en@gnu.org&lt;/a&gt;
	mailing-list. This allows people interested in Free Software
	movement to keep informed of FSFE France activity. To subscribe
	to this mailing-list, &lt;a
	href="mailto:fsfe-newsfr-en-request@gnu.org?subject=subscribe"&gt;send
	a mail to fsfe-newsfr-en-request@gnu.org with the subject
	"subscribe"&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>FSFE France News syndication on my.userland.com</title>
      <link>http://my.userland.com/viewChannel$4391</link>
      <description>
	26 May 2001. The news published by FSFE France are now
	integrated in &lt;a
	href="http://my.userland.com/viewChannel$4391"&gt;my.userland.com&lt;/a&gt;. This
	allows users of this site to get informed of FSFE France news,
	as well as webmasters using userland.com's features to better
	take advantage on this feed. Coming soon : mail delivery of
	FSFE France news.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Richard Stallman Delivers Speech at NYU, Countering Mundie's Attack on Free Software</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/press/2001-05-25-NYU.html</link>
      <description>
	25 May 2001. Richard M. Stallman, president of the Free
	Software Foundation, announced today that New York University
	has asked him to deliver a talk that will counterbalance the
	speech made on May 3, 2001 at NYU by Craig Mundie of
	Microsoft. More details in &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/press/2001-05-25-NYU.html"&gt;the FSF
	press-release&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Report on APRIL - FSFE France - MTIC meeting (in french)</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-05-25-01.fr.html</link>
      <description>
	25 May 2001. Here is a report of the meeting of 22/05/2001 at
	the &lt;a href="http://www.mtic.pm.gouv.fr"&gt;Mission
	interministérielle de soutien technique pour le développement
	des technologies de l'information et de la communication dans
	l'administration&lt;/a&gt; (MTIC - French government agency
	about ICT development) between reprensatatives of MTIC, APRIL
	and FSFE France.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>FSFE France activity report</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-05-20-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	24 May 2001. The &lt;a href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/"&gt;FSF Europe
	presence in France&lt;/a&gt; started its activity on April 12, a
	little more than a month ago. We worked hard to launch the
	core activities that will allow us to implement the goals of
	the &lt;a href="http://www.fsf.org/"&gt;FSF&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a
	href="http://www.fsfeurope.org/"&gt;FSF Europe&lt;/a&gt; : provide
	Free Software for everything and everyone and protect its
	existence when it is threatened.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Loïc Dachary's interview on NewsForge</title>
      <link>http://www.newsforge.com/article.pl?sid=01/05/15/1543252&amp;mode=thread</link>
      <description>
	23 May 2001. Loïc Dachary, FSF Europe's vice-president was
	interviewed by Julie Bresnick for NewsForge. This interview
	details Loïc's resume as well as explaining the reasons of his
	involvement in the Free Software movement.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Free Software leaders stand together</title>
      <link>http://perens.com/Articles/StandTogether.html</link>
      <description>
	18 May 2001. The most prominent evangelists of the Free
	Software sign &lt;a
	href="http://perens.com/Articles/StandTogether.html"&gt;an
	open letter&lt;/a&gt; in response to the recent attacks of
	Microsoft against Free Software. An indisputable unanimity
	against Microsoft's practices, that reaffirms the importance
	of Freedom as a federating value of the Free Software movement
	and the Open Source movement.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Benjamin Drieu about de french translation of the GNU GPL (french)</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-05-15-01.fr.html</link>
      <description>
	17 May 2001. In the interview, Benjamin Drieu gives us an
	update on the process of translating and adapting the GNU GPL
	license to french law. The project started on request of
	Richard M. Stallman who gave its responsability to Mélanie
	Clément-Fontaine. The FSFE France provides its assistance under
	coordination of Frédéric Couchet.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Libre et Vie Locale</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-05-16-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	16 May 2001. APRIL and FSF Europe have a booth at the conference
	&lt;a href="http://libre.enst-bretagne.fr/LibreEtVieLocale/"&gt;
	Freedom and regional life&lt;/a&gt;. Development, usage, legal
	protection of Free Software are actively discussed. Loïc Dachary
	gives his side of the story for the first day of the conference.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Brave GNU World issue #27</title>
      <link>http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-27.en.html</link>
      <description>
	15 May 2001. The latest issue of Georg's &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/intro.en.html"&gt;Brave Gnu world&lt;/a&gt;
	is out. This month's items : The "GNU/Linux TerminalServer for
	Schools"-Project which tries to provide an easy means for the
	installation and administration of a GNU/Linux based terminal
	server; GNU HaliFAX, which has the goal to create a complete
	and comfortable fax environment in the GNU Project; the
	"GOSSIP Simulation Environment", a simulation environment for
	use in communications engineering and digital signal
	processing; Jude, a toolkit or framework for application
	development that allows the implementation of solutions for
	the "Data-Management" and "Workgroup Application" areas while
	being simple to use for users and developers at the same time;
	and finaly HyperBuilder, a tool to manage big static web sites
	with more than 100 pages. &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/brave-gnu-world/issue-27.en.html"&gt;Read
	the article&lt;/a&gt;.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Meeting with Technopole Logiciel Libre</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-05-09-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	10 May 2001. One hundred kilometers from Paris a  &lt;a
	href="http://www.soissons-technopole.org"&gt;technopole unlike
	any other&lt;/a&gt; is created : it is dedicated to Free
	Software. Frédéric
	Couchet and Loïc Dachary went to Soisson to 
	establish a first contact between the technopole
	and the Free Software Foundation Europe.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
    <title>Free Software Foundation Europe aiming for more
    coordination between Free Software Developers. (PR. FSF
    Europe)</title>
    <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2001q2/000006.html</link>
      <description>
        7 May 2001. Free Software Foundation Europe aiming for more
        coordination between Free Software Developers. On May 6th
        2001, the first general assembly of the Free Software
        Foundation Europe took place at the Villa Vogelsang in Essen,
        Germany. It was the first meeting of the members of the
        recently founded sister organisation of the FSF (Boston,USA).
        Representatives from France, Germany and Sweden agreed on
        future areas of engagement for the FSFE. See also 
        &lt;a
        href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/photo/first-assembly/"&gt;photos
        by Olivier Berger&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
        href="http://adele.gerwinski.de/~peter/fsfe-20010506/"&gt;photos
        by Peter Gerwinski&lt;/a&gt;.

      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
    <title>The GNU General Public License Protects Software Freedoms (PR. FSF USA)</title>
      <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2001q2/000005.html</link>
      <description>
        4 May 2001. The GNU General Public License Protects Software
        Freedoms. Richard M. Stallman, president of the Free Software
        Foundation, and Professor Eben Moglen, general counsel for the
        Free Software Foundation, issued statements addressing points
        raised in remarks by Craig Mundie of Microsoft.  Stallman and
        Moglen focused on the importance of freedom for software users
        and programmers, how the GPL protects those freedoms, and
        Microsoft's attempt to cast such freedoms in an unfavorable
        light.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
    <title>The (french only) guide Unix + network goes to GFDL</title>
      <link>http://www-internal.alphanet.ch/~schaefer/unixguide.html</link>
      <description>

	6 May 2001. At the very time of the first general assembly
	of the Free Software Foundation Europe in Essen (Germany), the
	french guide "Short information about the Unix system and
	computer networks" (in french "Courte information sur le
	système Unix et les réseaux téléinformatiques") by Marc
	Schaefer goes to &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html"&gt;GNU Free
	Documentation License&lt;/a&gt;.  The decision was made on the
	IRC channel #fsfeurope (openprojects.net) after a discussion
	between Marc Schaefer and a french member of the FSF Europe
	who was present in Essen (Note: for the moment, only the LaTeX
	source of the document was updated). Now the guide is under
	GNU FDL, come a good time to make updates to it; Marc awaits
	your comments.

      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>They know their freedom</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/libre.en.html</link>
      <description>
	4 May 2001. During the  First Thursday, 23 persons 
	accurately enumerated the four fundamental freedom of
	Free Software. The FSFE France officialy
	 &lt;a
	href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/libre.en.html"&gt;
	thank them &lt;/a&gt; now and forever.
	Join them and become a part of the family.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Savannah Machine</title>
      <link>https://savannah.gnu.org/pm/task.php?func=detailtask&amp;project_task_id=80&amp;group_id=11&amp;group_project_id=1</link>
      <description>
	1 May 2001. The new machine for &lt;a
	href="http://savannah.gnu.org/"&gt;Savannah&lt;/a&gt; arrived
	today in the FSF office in Boston. Financed by donations
	relayed by &lt;a
	href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/donations/donations.en.html"&gt;FSF
	France&lt;/a&gt; it will allow to open the service to all Free 
	Software projects.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Donations to FSF</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/donations/donations.en.html</link>
      <description>
	30 April 2001. Donators who contributed to the FSF thru the
	&lt;a href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/index.en.html"&gt;FSF
	France&lt;/a&gt; now have &lt;a
	href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/donations/donations.en.html"&gt;their
	page&lt;/a&gt;. Donations are used by the  &lt;a
	href="http://www.fsfeurope.org/"&gt;FSF Europe&lt;/a&gt; or the
	&lt;a href="http://www.fsf.org/"&gt;FSF&lt;/a&gt; to advance
	the &lt;a
	href="http://www.gnu.org/"&gt;GNU&lt;/a&gt; project or protect
	the Free Software movement worldwide. Around 45 000 FF
	were recieved during the month of April.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>News syndication</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/server/#Publishing%20news</link>
      <description>
	27 April 2001. The news published by FSFE France are now
	integrated in &lt;a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/somenews/config/francefsf.cnf"&gt;SomeNews&lt;/a&gt;. They are therefore
	displayed on all the web sites using this plugin.
      </description>
    </item>

    <item>
      <title>Savannah Migration</title>
      <link>http://france.fsfeurope.org/news/article2001-04-26-01.en.html</link>
      <description>
	26 April 2001. A &lt;a
	href="http://www.valinux.com/products/2200/2200ts.html"&gt;test machine&lt;/a&gt; lent by &lt;a
	href="http://www.valinux.com/about/contact/"&gt;VA Linux
	France&lt;/a&gt; arrived in the FSFE France office. 	&lt;a href="http://savannah.gnu.org/"&gt;Savannah&lt;/a&gt; is now used
	by more than 100 packages of the GNU project and will be open
	to all Free Software projects.
      </description>
    </item>

  </channel>
 </rss>

