<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<newsset>
  <news date="2015-05-27">
    <title>FSFE is looking for a systems administrator and
    architect</title>
    <body>
      <h1>FSFE is looking for a systems administrator and
      architect</h1>
      <p newsteaser="yes">The Free Software Foundation Europe was
      founded in 2001 and has gone through a tremendous growth
      since then, both in the number of volunteers and staff, and
      also in the complexity of our technical infrastructure and
      the number of services we run and offer for both internal and
      external use. We're currently looking for a system
      administrator and architect that, for a limited time, can
      support us in our work to migrate our services to a new
      infrastructure.</p>
      <p>The migration project will move our services to a new
      infrastructure and revise the services we currently offer.
      The goal of the project is to make the infrastructure more
      coherent, with less dependencies, and with a separation of
      services that make it easier for volunteers to manage and
      help the organisation manage individual services in the long
      term.</p>
      <h2>Who we're looking for</h2>
      <p>We're looking for a senior system administrator or systems
      architect that can work in close coordination with our
      existing system administrators, staff and volunteers, to
      support our migration project through all of its stages,
      starting with the archaeological challenge of creating a high
      level overview of our services and their dependencies, and
      ending with the migration of our core services. Key skills
      will include technical documentation, virtualization
      environments, MTAs (Postfix), database servers and web
      services.</p>
      <h2>What we need to do</h2>
      <p>The person we're looking with will be tasked with the
      following. Please note that the first steps are more detailed
      than the latter steps, and we'll work together to
      continuously revise this plan as we go. All of this will also
      involve coordination with others, and a lot of information,
      especially for the first parts, can be gotten from existing
      documentation or from other system administrators.</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Create a high level service documentation, with a focus
        on (for each service): 
        <ol>
          <li>Authentication mechanisms</li>
          <li>Code base (custom work, patches, or off the shelf
          components)</li>
          <li>Interdependencies with other services</li>
          <li>Physical / virtual infrastructure location</li>
          <li>Usage (estimate usage from logs etc, as well as a
          brief synopsis of who the main users are:
          external, internal, etc)</li>
        </ol></li>
        <li>Additional documentation that may be needed for
        specific services (such as mail), the nature of which will
        need to be discussed and determined at a later time, when
        the first high level overview is complete.</li>
        <li>Analyse the current services and propose a new
        architecture, focusing on the services and the dependencies
        between them.</li>
        <li>Provide a migration plan that detail the steps needed
        to be taken in order to successfully migrate our existing
        services to the new architecture and infrastructure.</li>
        <li>Migrate, and support the migration, of core services to
        it, including shutting down and removing old services in an
        orderly fashion.</li>
      </ol>
      <h2>Location and travel</h2>
      <p>The FSFE system administrators work largely remotely, and
      most of the work can be done from anywhere in the world. It's
      beneficial for communication that the person helping us is
      roughly located in Europe, and one or two trips may be needed
      to meet with other system administrators and staff.</p>
    </body>
    <sidebar promo="about-fsfe"></sidebar>
    <tags>
      <tag>front-page</tag>
    </tags>
  </news>
</newsset>
