<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<newsset>

  <news date="2001-09-20">
    <title>FSF Europe receives charitable status in Germany</title>
    <body>FSF Europe e.V. (the central association) receives
          confirmation of its charitable status in Germany by the authorities.
    </body>
  </news>

  <news date="2001-08-26">
    <title>Georg Greve talks about "Copyright in the internet age"</title>
    <body>Slides (in German) available at
       <a href="http://gnuhh.org/work/presentations/IFA-2001/">http://gnuhh.org/work/presentations/IFA-2001/</a>.
    </body>
  </news>

  <news date="2001-07-20">
    <title>Richard Stallman inaugurates Free Software Foundation-India</title>
    <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2001q3/000017.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2001-07-16">
    <title>FSF Europe in German magazine</title>
    <body>The FSF Europe is mentioned in the German magazine
           <a href="http://www.focus.de">FOCUS</a> issue 29/2001, page 106 in a
           story about the GNU/<a href="http://linuxtag.org">LinuxTag</a>.
    </body>
  </news>

  <news date="2001-06-29">
    <title>FSF Europe at LinuxTag and Libre Software Meeting</title>
    <body>The FSF Europe will be present at the LinuxTag and
          Libre Software Meeting for the first time. Please see the
          press release for additional information.
    </body>
    <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2001q2/000013.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2001-05-07">
    <title>FSF Europe general assembly is over</title>
    <body>The FSF Europe general assembly is over. See the press release
       and <a href="http://france.fsfeurope.org/photo/first-assembly/">photos
       by Olivier Berger</a> and <a href="http://adele.gerwinski.de/~peter/fsfe-20010506/">photos by Peter Gerwinski</a>.
    </body>
    <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2001q2/000006.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2001-04-24">
    <title>Free Software Foundation Europe finishes founding process</title>
    <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2001q2/000003.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2001-04-24">
    <title>First general assembly of the Free Software Foundation Europe</title>
    <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2001q2/000002.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2001-12-17">
    <title>&quot;Freedom, Quality and Fraternity&quot; OLinux interview iwth Georg C. F. Greve</title>
    <body>&quot;[...] Keep on spreading the word. What we do today will
          influence the future of mankind for the next 200 years to come -
          we have to make sure that people understand the issues of
          Free Software and the importance of freedom. [...]
          Freedom counts! &quot;
    </body>
    <link>/news/article2001-12-17-01.html</link>    
  </news>

  <news date="2001-11-28">
    <title>FSF Europe appoints new Vice President</title>
    <body>
        Jonas Oberg was appointed new Vice President of the FSF
        Europe: "The future of Free Software depends a lot on
        what we do today. I plan to work to preserve the ability to
        use and develop Free Software in all of its forms, for
        example by helping to extend the efforts already underway
        against software patents and helping the media, government
        and companies understand the underlying issues of Free
        Software."
    </body>
    <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/announce/2001-November/000030.html</link>
   </news>

   <news date="2001-11-19">
     <title>We Speak about Free Software</title>
     <body>
         Launch of the <b>&quot;We speak about Free
         Software&quot;</b> campaign: There are compelling reasons to
         think and speak about Free Software and its philosophy. It 
         is rather common knowledge this applies to society as a
         whole, but it has not yet been widely understood that it
         benefits companies, as well. Therefore the FSF Europe launches
         this campaign on behalf and with support of several Free
         Software companies.
     </body>
     <link>/documents/whyfs.en.html</link>
   </news>
</newsset>

