<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2024-02-14" end="2024-02-14">
        <title>I Love Free Software Day in Bologna: Free Software syndicates - Study Group in Bologna, Italy</title>

    <body>		
      <p>For the first time live, TWC study groups return.</p>
      <p>Free software has a fundamental value for the economy of the technological supply chain. Without FOSS the startup model would be fundamentally different, or would not really exist. In spite of this, FOSS methodologies promote a collaborative model, rather than competitive, of design and production of digital technologies, thus helping to establish alternative technology design practices to Big Tech.</p>
      <p>Most of the challenges we encounter in building distributed collaboration networks are organizational, non-technical: the software is compared to a stream, a stream, with an original source that can branch into different flows where necessary. For example, some centralized software communities tend to recreate the power structures of the physical world through member distribution and audience choice. Does it make sense to continue developing free software as we have done in recent decades? Where can we learn from our mistakes? How to build free software communities we so much hope?</p>
      <p>As a better opportunity for Free Software Foundation Europe’s I Love Free Software Day to thank all people working on the ecosystem with a study group on the future and present of FOSS. Synware: free syndicates software is a collection of essays on the use, creation and collective maintenance of digital technologies in techno-syndicalist optics.</p>
      <p>We are waiting for you on February 14 in Bologna to discuss together the future of FOSS.</p>
    </body>

    <link>https://mobilizon.it/events/e3fbc8f0-321c-4516-9484-08b5fa59baaf</link>
    <tags>
      <tag key="it">Italy</tag>      <tag key="talk"/>
<tag key="workshop"/>
<tag key="meeting"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
