<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2024-08-17" end="2024-08-18">
        <title>FSFE at FrOSCon in Sankt Augustin, Deutschland</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>FSFE will be present at the Free and Open Source Software Conference (FrOSCon) with a booth, several talks and a reading:</p>
      <ul>
      <li>On 17.08 at 16:30h in room HS8: Johannes Näder, FSFE policy project manager, will give a talk on &quot;It's not just about money!&quot; (&quot;Geld ist nicht alles!'&quot;), explaining approaches for better Free Software procurement - <a href="https://programm.froscon.org/2024/events/3111.html]"></a>.</li> 
      <li> On 17.08 at 17:45h in room HS8:Right afterwards, at 17:45h. and in the same room (HS8), Bernhard Reiter will encourage voluntary payments for Free Software in his talk &quot;Just pay for it!!? - your Free Software!&quot; (&quot;Bezahlt sie doch einfach!!? - eure Freie Software&quot;) - <a href="https://programm.froscon.org/2024/events/3126.html"></a>.</li> 
      <li>On 17.08 at 14:00h in room HS6: as part of the children's programme, Isabel Drost-Fromm will read Matthias Kirschner's book &quot;<a href="/activities/ada-zangemann">Ada and Zangemann - A Tale of Software, Skateboards, and Raspberry Ice Cream</a>&quot;- <a href="https://programm.froscon.org/2024/events/3082.html"></a>.</li> 
      <li>On 17.08 at 15:00hh in room C117,Guido Günther will give a Phosh status update in the "FOSS on mobile" project room - <a href="https://programm.froscon.org/2024/events/3153.html"></a>.</li> 
      <li>In the FSFE booth we will answer all your questions about <a href="https://www.ngi.eu/ngi-projects/ngi-zero/">the NGI Zero</a> applications during the NGI0 Open Consultation Hour (time to be announced).</li>
      </ul>
       <p>Our talks and most of the conference will be in German. You do not need to buy a ticket or register. Just drop by!</p>
    </body>
    <link>https://froscon.org/programm/</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="de">
          Deutschland      </tag>
            <tag key="talk"/>
<tag key="infobooth"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
