<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-10-11">
    <title>Joint Statement by Free Software Foundation Europe and Software Freedom Conservancy Regarding Eben Moglen and Software Freedom Law Center</title>
    <body>
      <p>Both Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE) and <a href="https://sfconservancy.org/news/2023/oct/11/joint-statement-fsfe/">Software Freedom
Conservancy (SFC)</a> are committed to defending and expanding software freedom
and the rights of people to use, understand, share and improve their software.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>Joint Statement by Free Software Foundation Europe and Software Freedom Conservancy Regarding Eben Moglen and Software Freedom Law Center</h1>

<p>Both Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE) and <a href="https://sfconservancy.org/news/2023/oct/11/joint-statement-fsfe/">Software Freedom
Conservancy (SFC)</a> are committed to defending and expanding software freedom
and the rights of people to use, understand, share and improve their software.</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/03/69/2f17ef7aadf4fe570b22e3a6fb50.png" alt="FSFE and SFC logos"/>
  </figure>

<p>As part of this work, both FSFE and SFC strive to create a software freedom community that is egalitarian, fair, kind, and welcoming to everyone.
  Sadly, though, we are also aware that toxic behavior, bullying, and other violations of
  Codes of Conduct do occur throughout our community. As such, both
  organizations make substantial efforts to protect our volunteers and staff
  from bad behavior.</p>

<p>Historically, both FSFE and SFC collaborated and coordinated with a third organization –
Software Freedom Law Center (SFLC), and specifically with SFLC's founder/President/Executive Director, Eben Moglen.
However, some time ago, both our organizations ended our collaborations and affiliations with SFLC.
Furthermore, both FSFE and SFC now have internal policies to avoid any situations where our employees or volunteers might work directly with him.</p>
  
<p>We arrived at these decisions through our organizational 
processes. After years of reported abusive behavior by Moglen 
toward members of the staff and volunteers of both organizations, each 
organization independently made a categorical rule that we would avoid 
Eben Moglen and not invite him to our events and fora. (Examples of reports of his behavior – towards <a href="https://ttabvue.uspto.gov/ttabvue/v/ttabvue-92066968-CAN-109.pdf#page=8">SFC 
staff (page 8)</a>, <a href="https://ttabvue.uspto.gov/ttabvue/v/ttabvue-92066968-CAN-109.pdf#page=51">FSFE 
staff (page 51)</a>, and <a href="https://ttabvue.uspto.gov/ttabvue/v/ttabvue-92066968-CAN-122.pdf#page=28">others 
(page 28)</a> – have been (with reluctance) documented publicly 
in the proceedings of the ongoing <a href="https://sfconservancy.org/blog/2017/nov/03/sflc-legal-action/">trademark 
cancellation petition that SFLC filed against SFC</a> in the <a href="https://ttabvue.uspto.gov/ttabvue/v?pno=92066968">United States 
Trademark Trial and Appeal Board</a>).</p>

<p>Today, we share — with the community at large — our 
policy to not work with Moglen or SFLC. We have chosen to speak publicly 
on this matter because we feel we have an obligation to warn volunteers 
and activists in software freedom that this pattern of reported behavior exists. Of course, everyone should read the 
publicly available source materials and make their own decisions 
regarding these matters. While we are loathe to publicly speak of these 
unfortunate events, the decades of ongoing reports of abusive 
behavior — and the risk that behavior creates for unknowing 
members of the Free Software community — ultimately requires that we no 
longer remain quiet on this issue.</p>

<p>Abusive behavior is a distraction from the mission of any activist 
organization. We urge everyone to separate themselves as best they can 
from such behavior (and from those who tolerate and/or employ it), and 
focus on the important work of increasing software freedom.</p>
</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/03/69/2f17ef7aadf4fe570b22e3a6fb50.png" alt="FSFE and SFC logos"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20231011-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
</tags>
  </news>
</newsset>
