<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-11-15">
    <title>German Parliament receives Upcycling Android Open Letter 
</title>
    <body>
      <p>On 14 November, the Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE) handed 
over the Open Letter “The right to install any software on any device"
to Tabea Rößner, Chair of the Digital Affairs Committee at the German 
Bundestag. The letter aims to enable a more sustainable use of 
electronic products and devices in the European Union.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>German Parliament receives Upcycling Android Open Letter</h1>

<p>On 14 November, the Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE) handed 
over the Open Letter “The right to install any software on any device"
to Tabea Rößner, Chair of the Digital Affairs Committee at the German 
Bundestag. The letter aims to enable a more sustainable use of 
electronic products and devices in the European Union.</p>


<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/fb/41/fe1888ae201853581b722a6e1952.jpg" alt="CC-BY-SA-Elias Tetzlaff. Image showing Johannes Näder handing over the letter to Tabea Rößner"/>
  <figcaption>CC-BY-SA Elias Tetzlaff</figcaption> 
  </figure>

<div> 
<p>
To achieve this goal, the <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/openletter.html">Open Letter</a> sets out four key 
demands:
</p> 
<ol> 
	<li>Users have the right to freely choose operating 
systems and software running on their devices</li> 
	<li>Users have the right to freely choose between service providers to connect their 
devices with</li> 
	<li>Devices are interoperable and compatible with 
open standards</li> 
	<li>Source code of drivers, tools, and interfaces 
are published under a free license</li> 
</ol> 
</div> 

<p>Signed by more than 3000 individuals and by 147 organisations, the Open Letter to 
European Union legislators was presented on 14 November to the Chair of the Digital Affairs Committee (Ausschuss für 
Digitales) at the German Bundestag, by a delegation from the FSFE.</p>


<p>
<blockquote>Tabea Rößner, Chair of the Digital Committee, commented 
when receiving the open letter:"So many devices end up on the 
scrapyard after just two or three years. But the devices are still in 
good condition and could be made to last with new software. We could 
bring them back to life, especially with Free Software. It would be a 
real sustainability effect if we had the right to install any software 
on any device. That's why this initiative is absolutely worth 
supporting.”</blockquote>
</p>

<p>Rößner announced that she would hand over the Open Letter to Steffi 
Lemke, Germany's Federal Minister for the Environment, Nature 
Conservation, Nuclear Safety and Consumer Protection.</p>

<p>
<blockquote>"The Open Letter is part of 
our Upcycling Android campaign, which we started to raise awareness 
about how Free Software can help to improve the sustainability of our 
digital devices. In addition to the Open Letter, the initiative has 
held workshops, developed policy recommendations, and received a lot of 
public attention, promoting the right of every user to install any 
software on any device. Moreover, upcycling our devices is an important 	 
step in rethinking our short-term, linear consumption of electronic 
devices in favour of a circular economy”, explains Johannes Näder, FSFE Senior Policy Project Manager.</blockquote>
</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/cc/61/cbf7f6c6f7fd9356f4b0e024d062.JPG" alt="Image showing the Open Letter printed"/>
</figure>
 
<h2>About Upcycling Android</h2>

<p>Launched in November 2021, under the name  <a href="/activities/upcyclingandroid/">“Upcycling Android"</a>, this 
FSFE initiative has also helped people to flash their phones with Free 
Software operating systems. This not only promotes the right of any 
user to install any software on any device, but also enables a more 
sustainable use of electronic products.</p>

<p>Even after the project has officially ended, the Upcycling Android 
material can be freely used by others who want to continue promoting 
the use of Free Software while overcoming software obsolescence.</p>


</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/fb/41/fe1888ae201853581b722a6e1952.jpg" alt="CC-BY-SA- Elias Tetzlaff. Image showing Johannes Näder handing over the letter to Tabea Rößner"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20231115-01.html</link>
    <tags>
 <tag key="front-page"/>
 <tag key="de">Germany</tag>
 <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
 <tag key="upcyclingandroid">Upcycling Android</tag>
 <tag key="deviceneutrality">Device Neutrality</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1101"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
