<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-09-15">
    <title>Router Freedom: German telcos want to exclude fiber</title>
    <body>
      <p>German network operators have requested the national regulator 
Bundesnetzagentur to start procedures to exclude Router Freedom from 
fiber networks. In a consultation, the FSFE picks apart all the telcos’ 
arguments and calls on the regulator to respect consumer rights.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>Router Freedom: German telcos want to exclude fiber</h1>

<p>German network operators have requested the national regulator 
Bundesnetzagentur to start procedures to exclude Router Freedom from 
fiber networks. In a consultation, the FSFE picks apart all the telcos’ 
arguments and calls on the regulator to respect consumer rights.</p> 


<figure class="no-border">
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/5a92ce4766c686c21f06f0fec28618e1.jpg" alt="Image showing diverse ports of a router"/>
</figure>


<p>The German telecommunications regulator Bundesnetzagentur,<a href="https://www.bundesnetzagentur.de/DE/Fachthemen/Telekommunikation/Unternehmenspflichten/Schnittstelle_netzabschluss/start.html"> has opened 
procedures</a> to analyse a request made by fiber network operators 
requesting to exclude Router Freedom from fiber networks. The request 
contains the fiber operators’ arguments, including security of the 
network, cost of support, quality of service and interoperability 
issues.</p>

<p>In the <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/routers/fsfe-bnetza-fiber-de-2023.pdf">public consultation (in German)</a> the FSFE has called on the regulator 
to dismiss the request since it goes against the German law and the EU 
regulatory framework of net neutrality, which has clearly set rules 
safeguarding freedom of terminal equipment for end-users. Although the 
network operators have tried to pose fiber networks as a special case, 
we have demonstrated that there is no objective technological necessity 
to abolish Router Freedom. On the contrary, Router Freedom represents 
also for fiber freedom of choice, security, consumer welfare, fair 
competition and sustainability.</p> 

<p>The FSFE’s arguments were also 
supported by empirical data collected in the comprehensive Router 
Freedom survey, where more than 1.600 participants have stated their 
problems with ISPs hampering their rights to use their own routers and 
modems.</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/85/86/6a74ab703ca9297fa8bd6b564be3.png" alt="Illustration showing a graphic with answers about router freedom principles"/>
  <figcaption>Router Freedom is key for a neutral, fair and secure Internet access</figcaption>
</figure>

<div> <blockquote><p>"German fiber networks are pushing the boundaries 
against Router Freedom. However, telcos were not able to prove the 
necessity to revisit the law, making their request void. We call on the 
Bundesnetzagentur to consider end-users rights and interests and 
safeguard Router Freedom in fiber networks".</p> <p class="author"> - Alexander Sander, FSFE’s Senior Policy Consultant.</p></blockquote>
</div>

<p><strong><italic>You can download the FSFE’s consultation paper <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/routers/fsfe-bnetza-fiber-de-2023.pdf">here (in German)</a></italic></strong></p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/5a92ce4766c686c21f06f0fec28618e1.jpg" alt="Image showing diverse ports of a router"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230915-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
   <tag key="routers">Router Freedom</tag>
   <tag key="de">Germany</tag>
   <tag key="deviceneutrality">Device neutrality</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1073"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
