<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-05-15">
    <title>European citizens demand Router Freedom</title>
    <body>
      <p> A pan-European survey, run by the Free Software Foundation Europe, 
has collected information from more than 1600 end-users and highlighted 
several obstacles to Router Freedom, such as lack of freedom of choice, 
provider lock-in and promotion of equipment running exclusively 
proprietary software. </p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>European citizens demand Router Freedom</h1>

<p> A pan-European survey, run by the Free Software Foundation Europe, 
has collected information from more than 1600 end-users and highlighted 
several obstacles to Router Freedom, such as lack of freedom of choice, 
provider lock-in and promotion of equipment running exclusively 
proprietary software. </p>


<figure>
<a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/85/86/6a74ab703ca9297fa8bd6b564be3.png">
<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/85/86/6a74ab703ca9297fa8bd6b564be3.png" alt="Graphic with participants’ level of agreement on Router Freedom principles."/>
 </a>
<figcaption>This chart demonstrates the participants’ level of agreement on Router Freedom principles. More than a simple technical issue, Router Freedom is a policy demand</figcaption>
</figure>


 
<p> More than a thousand consumers from across Europe have shared their 
experience of the commercial practices of Internet Service Providers 
(ISPs) in the <a href="/news/2023/news-20230515-02.html">most comprehensive end-user survey regarding freedom of 
terminal equipment to date</a>, resulting in a 
call for Router Freedom. The responses from end-users all over Europe 
demonstrate how network operators still hamper consumer freedom of 
choice, exercise lock-in over internet equipment and promote 
proprietary devices, negatively affecting consumer welfare, security, 
privacy and data protection. </p>


<p>Router Freedom is the right that customers of any internet service 
provider have to be able to choose and use a private modem and router 
instead of equipment provided by the ISP. Freedom of choice for routers 
and modems has been regulated in the EU since 2015 (Net Neutrality 
Regulation) but national implementation has led to fragmentation of the 
digital markets, negatively impacting end-users’ rights. <a href="https://download.fsfe.org/routers/rf-survey-report-2023.pdf">The survey 
demonstrated that Router Freedom is not only a technical issue, but 
also a policy demand</a>. More than 90% of the survey participants agreed 
that freedom of terminal equipment is key for net neutrality and open 
internet, security and data protection, fair competition and digital 
sustainability.</p>

<p>
</p>
<blockquote>
 <em> “The outcome of this survey serves as key insight for 
 policy makers regulating Router Freedom and consumer organisations 
 protecting and promoting the rights of end-users.  Critically important 
 are the reported practices that could be considered infringements 
 against Router Freedom. Limitation to freedom of choice, ISP’s lock-in, 
 provision of proprietary devices, security issues and unlawful 
 practices are some of the threats reported against end-users”, states 
 Lucas Lasota, FSFE’s senior project manager.
 </em>
</blockquote>
<p/>


</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/85/86/6a74ab703ca9297fa8bd6b564be3.png" alt="More than a simple technical issue, Router Freedom is key  to a healthy digital ecosystem"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230515-01.html</link>
    <tags>
 <tag key="front-page"/>
 <tag key="routers">Router Freedom</tag>
 <tag key="deviceneutrality">Device Neutrality</tag>
 <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1030"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
