<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2023-06-14">
    <title>EU: Majority for AI Act – and safeguards for Free Software</title>
    <body>
      <p> The European Parliament today voted in favour of the AI Act with 499 
votes in favour, 28 against, and 93 abstentions. Free Software is given 
safeguards; these rules  must now be defended in the trilogue and 
transferred to the Cyber Resilience Act and the Product Liability 
Directive.</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>EU: Majority for AI Act – and safeguards for Free Software</h1>

<p> The European Parliament today voted in favour of the AI Act with 499 
votes in favour, 28 against, and 93 abstentions. Free Software is given 
safeguards; these rules  must now be defended in the trilogue and 
transferred to the Cyber Resilience Act and the Product Liability 
Directive.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/a3/7c/94aa5b295f62e4cefb03bc1ad1ed.png" alt="Screenshot of the final vote of the AI Act in the European Parliament"/>
</figure>

<p> With a large majority, the plenary of the EU Parliament today 
confirmed the  <a href="/news/2023/news-20230511-01.html">compromises</a> of the lead 
committees from May. The AI Act contains a far-reaching exemption from 
this regulation for non-profit organisations as well as small Free 
Software projects up to the size of micro-enterprises. The position of 
the EU Parliament must now be defended in the upcoming trilogue, in 
which the final text will be negotiated together with the Council and 
the Commission.</p>


<blockquote><em> "With today's decision, the EU Parliament has 
demonstrated how Free Software can be regulated in a meaningful way. 
Developers must be protected, but at the same time those who 
significantly benefit on the market with the use of Free Software must 
also be responsible. This principle must now also be anchored in the 
Cyber Resilience Act and the Product Liability Directive", explains 
Alexander Sander, Senior Policy Consultant of the Free Software 
Foundation Europe (FSFE).</em></blockquote>

<p> More information on the negotiations on the Cyber Resilience Act 
and the Product Liability Directive can be found <a href="/news/2023/news-20230323-01.html">here</a>.
</p> 

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/original/a3/7c/94aa5b295f62e4cefb03bc1ad1ed.png" alt="Screenshot of the final vote of the AI Act in the European Parliament"/>
    <link>/news/2023/news-20230614-01.html</link>
    <tags>
 <tag key="front-page"/>
 <tag key="european-parliament">European Parliament</tag>
 <tag key="policy">European Public Policy</tag>
 <tag key="AI">AI</tag>
 <tag key="european-union">European Union</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/1040"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
