<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<newsset>
  <news date="2002-12-18">
    <title>FSF Europe calls for participation</title>
    <body>Press-release of the FSF Europe: "The Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE) invites all companies, organizations and research institutes interested in Free Software projects funded by the European Commission to join their effort."
    </body>
    <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2002q4/000047.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2002-06-13">
    <title>FFII Associated with FSF Europe</title>
    <body>
   The Foundation for a Free Information Infrastructure (FFII) is now an
   official associate organisation of the Free Software Foundation Europe
   (FSFE). The FFII is the first associate organisation of the FSF Europe
   based in Germany.
    </body>
   <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2002q2/000044.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2002-06-04">
    <title>Two Expressions of Interest (EoI) from FSF Europe</title>
    <body>
       In response to a
            call from the European Commission, the FSF Europe submitted an expression
            of interest for each of the instruments of the sixth framework
            programme (FP6).
    </body>
    <link>/documents/fp6/</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2002-05-27">
    <title>FSF Europe completes successful first year</title>
    <body>
        On May 26th 2002, the Free Software Foundation Europe (FSF
Europe) finishes its second general assembly, completing the first
year of activities. Members from Sweden, Italy, Germany and France
drew a summary of last years activities, analyzed the current
situation of Free Software and exchanged plans and visions for the
upcoming year.
   </body>
   <link>http://mailman.fsfeurope.org/pipermail/press-release/2002q2/000042.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2002-04-30">
    <title>Recommendation by the FSF Europe and supporting parties</title>
    <body>
 The FSF Europe and supporting parties has submitted a recommendation for
 the 6th European Community Framework Programme:
  "Free Software is a concept that has
              fundamentally changed the way some parts of the IT
              sector are working towards a more stable, lasting and
              sustainable approach with higher dynamics and increased
              efficiency. It is obvious that the first region to adopt
              and support this principle on a larger scale can profit
              enormously and get a head-start in the information age."
   </body>
   <link>/documents/fp6/recommendation.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2002-04-28">
    <title>Invitation to European Copyright Directive Alert miniconference</title>
     <body>
                 On Monday 29 April 2002, at 6pm in London, we invite you to
          join the <i> European Copyright Directive Alert </i>
          miniconference. Organized by the <a
          href="http://uk.eurorights.org/">Campaign for Digital Rights
          </a> it will explain the dangers of the <a
          href="law/eucd/">EUCD</a>. Unless it is stopped before
          December 2002, it will become legal in each European
          country.
     </body>
     <link>http://www.lonix.org.uk/tnet-cgi/Lonix?CODE=userMeetings</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2002-04-24">
    <title>FSF Europe present at first LiLit meeting</title>
    <body>On Friday 26 April 2002, the Free Software Foundation
              Europe will be present at the first LiLiT meeting in
              Liège, Belgium.  During this evening (night ?-) session,
              we will focus on the best means to explain the ethical
              value of Free Software. A global view of the on going
              actions will hopefully allow everyone to figure out how
              to promote and defend the Free Software ideals.
    </body>
    <link>/events/events.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2002-01-31">
    <title>FSF Europe at the Free and Open Source Software Developers Meeting</title>
    <body>
               Between the 16th and 17th of February, 2002, the Free
              and Open Source Software Developers Meeting will take
              place in Brussels, Belgium. Among the visitors will be
              Richard M. Stallman, president of the Free Software
              Foundation and Georg C. F. Greve, president of the Free
              Software Foundation Europe. The FSF Europe welcomes all
              members of the press who wish to meet the members and
              volunteers of the foundation.
    </body>
    <link>/news/article2002-01-31-01.en.html</link>
  </news>

  <news date="2002-01-18">
    <title>ANSOL becomes associated organization of the FSF Europe</title>
    <body>
        "This collaboration is a very important step for the Portuguese and
         European free software community. Problems faced by the free software 
         community in Portugal are similar to those faced in other European
         countries; by joining forces with FSFE we can solve this problems more
         efficiently" said Jaime Villate, founding member of ANSOL.
    </body>
    <link>/news/article2002-01-18-01.en.html</link>
  </news>

</newsset>

