<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2024-11-23T10:00:00Z" end="2024-11-24T18:00:00Z">
        <title>14th International Conference on Peer-to-Peer Networks and Trust Management (P2PTM 2024) in LONDON, United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>14th International Conference on Peer-to-Peer Networks and Trust Management (P2PTM 2024)<br />
November 23 ~ 24, 2024, London, United Kingdom</p>
     <p>https://acity2024.org/p2ptm/index</p>
     <p>SCOPE</p>
     <p>14th International Conference on Peer-to-Peer Networks and Trust Management (P2PTM 2024) will provide an excellent international forum for sharing knowledge and results in theory and applications of Peer-to-Peer Networks and Trust Management. The Conference looks for significant contributions to the Computer Networks and Communications for wired and wireless networks in theoretical and practical aspects. Original papers are invited on Networks, wireless and Mobile, Protocols and wireless networks and security. The aim of the conference is to provide a platform to the researchers and practitioners from both academia as well as industry to meet and share cutting-edge development in the field.</p>
     <p>Authors are solicited to contribute to the Conference by submitting articles that illustrate research results, projects, surveying works and industrial experiences that describe significant advances in the following areas, but are not limited to.</p>
     <p>TOPICS OF INTEREST</p>
     <p>Advances in Theoretical Foundations of P2P<br />
Ad hoc and Sensor Networks<br />
Commercial Applications<br />
Cooperation and Collaboration in P2P Systems<br />
Delay-tolerant P2P Systems<br />
Higher-level Query Support in P2P Systems<br />
Mobile P2P<br />
Overlay Architectures and Topologies<br />
Overlay Monitoring and Management<br />
P2P and Wireless Convergence<br />
P2P Applications and Services<br />
P2P Economics<br />
P2P Grids<br />
P2P Information Retrieval<br />
P2P Overlay Interaction with Underlying Infrastructure<br />
Peer to Peer and Overlay Networks<br />
P2P Technology and Sensors<br />
P2P Workload Characterization and Simulation<br />
Performance and Robustness of P2P Systems<br />
Protocols and Algorithms for Mobile and Wireless Peer-to-peer Networks<br />
Security in P2P systems<br />
Self-Organization in P2P Systems<br />
Semantic Overlay Networks and Semantic Query Routing in P2P Systems<br />
Social Networks<br />
Trust, Reputation and Fairness in P2P Systems<br />
Paper Submission</p>
     <p>Authors are invited to submit papers through the conference Submission System by November 02, 2024 . Submissions must be original and should not have been published previously or be under consideration for publication while being evaluated for this conference.</p>
     <p>The proceedings of the conference will be published by Computer Science Conference Proceedings in Computer Science &amp; Information Technology (CS &amp; IT) series (Confirmed).</p>
     <p>International Journal of Network Security &amp; Its Applications (IJNSA) – ERA, WJCI Indexed<br />
International Journal of Computer Science &amp; Information Technology (IJCSIT) – WJCI, INSPEC Indexed<br />
International Journal of Wireless &amp; Mobile Networks (IJWMN) – ERA, WJCI Indexed<br />
International Journal of Peer to Peer Networks (IJP2P)Information Technology in Industry (ITII)<br />
IMPORTANT DATES</p>
     <p>Second Batch : (Submissions after October 20, 2024)</p>
     <p>Submission Deadline: November 02, 2024<br />
Authors Notification: November 16, 2024<br />
Registration &amp; Camera-Ready Paper Due: November 19, 2024<br />
Contact Us</p>
     <p>Here’s where you can reach us: p2ptm@acity2024.org or p2ptmconf@gmail.com</p>
    </body>

    <link>https://acity2024.org/p2ptm/index</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="gb">
          United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland      </tag>
                  <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
