<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2024-11-23T10:00:00Z" end="2024-11-24T18:00:00Z">
        <title>15th International Conference on VLSI (VLSI 2024) in London, United Kingdom, United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p><br />
15th International Conference on VLSI (VLSI 2024)</p>
     <p>November 23 ~ 24, 2024, London, United Kingdom</p>
     <p>https://acity2024.org/vlsi/index<br />
Scope<br />
 <br />
15th International Conference on VLSI (VLSI 2024) will provide an excellent international forum for sharing knowledge and results in theory, methodology and applications of VLSI. Original, unpublished papers, describing research in the general area of VLSI are solicited. Both theoretical and experimental research results are welcome in the following areas, but are not limited to. The conference focuses on all technical and practical aspects of high performance computing, green computing, pervasive computing, cloud computing etc.<br />
Authors are solicited to contribute to the Conference by submitting articles that illustrate research results, projects, surveying works and industrial experiences that describe significant advances in the following areas, but are not limited to.<br />
Topics of Interest include, but are not limited to, the follow<br />
•	VLSI Design<br />
•	Computer-Aided Design (CAD)<br />
•	Low Power and Power Aware Design<br />
•	Testing, Reliability, Fault-Tolerance<br />
•	Emerging Technologies<br />
•	Post-CMOS VLSI<br />
•	VLSI Applications (Communications, Video, Security, Sensor Networks, etc)</p>
     <p>Paper Submission <br />
Authors are invited to submit papers through the conference Submission System by November 02,2024 . Submissions must be original and should not have been published previously or be under consideration for publication while being evaluated for this conference. The proceedings of the conference will be published by Computer Science Conference Proceedings in Computer Science &amp; Information Technology (CS &amp; IT) series (Confirmed).<br />
Selected papers from VLSI 2024, after further revisions, will be published in the special issue of the following journals<br />
•	International Journal of VLSI Design &amp; Communication Systems (VLSICS)<br />
•	Signal &amp; Image Processing : An International Journal (SIPIJ) - WJCI Indexed<br />
•	International Journal of Embedded Systems and Applications (IJESA)<br />
•	International Journal of Computer Science &amp; Information Technology (IJCSIT) - WJCI, INSPEC Indexed<br />
•	Information Technology in Industry (ITII)<br />
Important Dates<br />
•	Submission Deadline :November 02,2024<br />
•	Authors Notification:November 16, 2024<br />
•	Registration &amp; camera - Ready Paper Due: November 19, 2024</p>
     <p>Contact Us <br />
Here's where you can reach us : vlsi@acity2024.org or vlsiw@yahoo.com</p>
     <p>Paper Submission Link<br />
https://acity2024.org/submission/index.php</p>
     <p></p>
    </body>

    <link>https://acity2024.org/vlsi/index</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="gb">
          United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland      </tag>
                  <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
