<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2024-12-17T18:00:00Z" end="2024-12-17T22:00:00Z">
        <title>Flörgåsbord 2024! (free tenpin bowling all evening!) in Newcastle-under-Lyme, United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</title>
    <group>
     <name>Potteries</name> 
     <url/>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>IMPORTANT! Please RSVP or ask questions via the FSFE Potteries mailing list (or e-mail us) before coming.</p>
     <p>Mailing list: https://lists.fsfe.org/postorius/lists/potteries.lists.fsfe.org<br/>
E-mail: potteries@fsfe.org</p>
     <p>For it's second year running, we bring back "Flörgåsbord"... our annual tenpin bowling evening for the groups of FSFE Potteries, StaffsLUG, and ORG Stoke.</p>
     <p>This year it'll be on Tuesday 17th December from 6:00pm onwards (although most will arrive around 6:30pm)</p>
     <p>Stuff to know...</p>
     <p>The room - For this evening we have privately booked a room in the centre of Newcastle-under-Lyme, that can hold up to 40 people and comes complete with 4 full size ten pin bowling lanes. The room also has plenty of comfortable seating booths for people get a drink or eat food (with ordering possible via QR code). This room is located upstairs from the Vue cinema... and you can find exact directions in the 'How to find us' section.</p>
     <p>It's FREE - We're pickup up the bill for the bowling all evening!</p>
     <p>All the games are free and unlimited! - All 4 bowling lanes will be on unlimited free play for the whole evening, 6 people at most to a lane.</p>
     <p>It's a social - Just like any of our past socials, there will be places to sit and just have a quiet chat (no loud music if you don't want it!). Not everyone will be bowling anyway... so don't feel like you have to. </p>
     <p>There is food and drinks - The venue has a kitchen serving hot food (so you don't need to eat before coming out) as well as offering drinks. Please follow the hyperlink (related to this event that you're reading) to see the details of the food and drink offered by the venue ...and you can now order everything by using the QR codes shown on the tables of their new seating booths!</p>
     <p>Open to all in the FSF, LUG, and ORG - So a great mix of people in one social... but you're also welcome to bring friends and family too.  The only thing we ask is that you RSVP if you're coming as we need to be sure it'll be under 40 people. So don't worry if it doesn't look like many are coming, as this has gone out to other groups too.</p>
     <p>It's a veritable Flörgåsbord! - Forgive the silly name! It comes from trying to merge the acronyms FSF/LUG/ORG that then got us "Florg" which then turned into Flörgåsbord... kind of like Smörgåsbord (a Swedish buffet)... so basically people from lots of different local technology groups!.</p>
     <p>It's a Christmas thing! - We like running these at Christmas time... so you can consider this as a more fun way to get together... rather than a Christmas meal every year!</p>
     <p>Travel - Plenty of way to get to Newcastle-under-Lyme town centre (including buses... as it's got it's own bus station). If you're parking then you can either use the Vue cinema park car, or one of the council ran car parks.</p>
     <p>⏰ 6:00pm doors open<br/>
📍 Lymelight Lanes, 98-104 High Street, Newcastle-under-Lyme, Staffordshire, ST5 1PT. </p>
    </body>

    <link>https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Potteries/Lymelight%20Lanes</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="gb">
          United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland      </tag>
            <tag key="localgroup"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
