<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2024-09-10T17:30:00Z" end="2024-09-10T17:30:00Z">
        <title>Summer meetup! (Second Edition) in Keele, United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland</title>
    <group>
     <name>Potteries</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>Hello again! (no, you're not experiencing Déjà vu!)</p>
     <p>The summer meetup has been rescheduled and will now be...</p>
     <p>At the KPA Clubhouse on Tuesday 10th September from 6:30pm (BST, UK time).  </p>
     <p>Please note the time listed on the FSFE site is UTC which is currently one hour ahead of the UK which is in BST right now. </p>
     <p>If anyone wants to get any food from there, then they serve food until 8pm, and they will close up completely at 11pm (we've got assurances in email!). Feel free to get there earlier if you prefer to eat in peace before chatter commences!</p>
     <p>I've had a good amount of replies, and (as usual for socials) I've made this a joint event between FSFE Potteries, ORG Stoke, and StaffsLUG all in one place :) The previous attempt at organizing this social had about 20+ people coming, so hopefully you'll all try joining us again!</p>
     <p>Will be great to have a catch up, especially if the weather holds!</p>
     <p>Below are links to find the venue... a guide to Keele car parks (best to use E2 which is free after 5pm)... and bus information (coming from either Crewe/Nantwich or Newcastle/Hanley direction).</p>
     <p>Venue: https://osm.org/go/eu08CaVjf?way=136068963</p>
     <p>Parking: https://www.keele.ac.uk/about/howtofindus/parking/paytopark/s-misc-799-staff-parking-designations-pay-to-park.pdf</p>
     <p>25 bus (First): https://www.firstbus.co.uk/potteries/plan-journey/timetables?service=25-FP&amp;day=mf</p>
     <p>85 bus (D&amp;G): https://www.dgbus.co.uk/bus-services/85/</p>
    </body>

    <link>https://wiki.fsfe.org/LocalGroups/Potteries/KPA%20Clubhouse</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="gb">
          United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland      </tag>
            <tag key="localgroup"/>
<tag key="meeting"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
