<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2026-01-21T08:00:00Z" end="2026-01-16T18:00:00Z">
        <title>conference 5th world Neuroscience Neurology and Brain Disorders  Summit from January 14-16, 2026 Abu Dhabi, UAE  in  Liwa Oasis, United Arab Emirates</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>On behalf of the organizing committee, Neuroscience 2026 is cordially invited to attend the upcoming scientific conference 5th world Neuroscience Neurology and Brain Disorders Summit from January 14-16, 2026 in Abu Dhabi, UAE and Neuroscience under the theme of &quot; Advancing understanding of the brain and nervous system through research, innovation, and collaboration&quot;. The conference will provide both in-person and virtual participation opportunities to ensure that all attendees have a thorough and inclusive experience.</p>
     <p>UCGConferences 2026 will bring together a wide group of participants, including top scholars, respected doctors, cutting-edge innovators, and passionate practitioners. This conference offers a unique opportunity for debate, networking, and collaboration, providing an environment in which advances in neurology and brain disorders can be shared and explored. </p>
     <p>The conference will address a wide range of important neurology subjects, including the most recent research on neurodegenerative disorders such as Alzheimer's and Parkinson's, as well as emerging findings in neuroimmunology, neuropharmacology, and neurogenesis. Key topics will include advances in brain injury treatment, the convergence of cognitive neuroscience and psychology, and neuroinformatics and computational neuroscience. This comprehensive program aims to cover both core theories and recent advances in brain science. </p>
     <p>There will be a variety of presentations, including keynote addresses, panel discussions, and interactive workshops. These talks will focus on cutting-edge research, therapeutic discoveries, and technology developments, offering significant insights and chances for professional development and collaboration. </p>
     <p>Looking for the documents required to avail UAE Visa? Questions asked during the UAE Visa Interview? Process of UAE Visa? Not getting the UAE? Visa Appointment? Need an Invitation Letter?<br />
Join us at the 5th world Neuroscience Neurology and Brain Disorders Summit from January 14-16, 2026 in Abu Dhabi, UAE<br />
Bothered about UAE Visa?<br />
We are here to assist you in applying for a visa. We will guide you through the visa process once you have registered as a speaker/listener/poster. The visa will be valid for 5-10 years.<br />
Why Abu Dhabi? <br />
The Abu Dhabi is famous for its luxurious resorts and hotels, which provide unsurpassed luxury and service. Sheikh Zayed Mosque, Emirates Palace, Louvre Museum, Yas Island, Ferrari World, Emirates Park Zoo, Warner Bros World, Heritage Village, and the Al Ain Palace Museum.</p>
     <p>CALL FOR ABSTRACT IS OPEN!</p>
     <p>Track 1: Neuroscience Track 2: Neurology Track 3: Brain Disorders Track 4: Cognitive Neuroscience Track 5: Neurosurgery Track 6: Pain Disorder and Management Track 7: Central Nervous System Track 8: Pediatric Neurology Track 9: Neuro-Oncology and Brain Tumors Track 10: Neurophysiology Track 11: Cellular Neuroscience Track 12: Neuroimmunology <br />
To know more about topics visit: https://neuroscience.utilitarianconferences.com/submit-abstract<br />
Group Discount is Available (5+Members)<br />
The 5th world neuroscience neurology and brain disorders summit attracts over 1000+ attendees every year. Submit your Proposal to speak at an in-person conference event today Email: info@utilitarianconferences.com</p>
     <p>Important Information:<br />
Conference Name: 5th world Neuroscience Neurology and Brain Disorders Summit <br />
Short Name: #5ANNBDSUCG2026 <br />
Dates: January 14-16, 2026<br />
Venue: Adu Dhabi, UAE &amp; Virtual<br />
Email:info@utilitarianconferences.com<br />
Visit:  https://neuroscience.utilitarianconferences.com/<br />
Call for Papers:  https://neuroscience.utilitarianconferences.com/submit-abstract <br />
Register here: https://neuroscience.utilitarianconferences.com/registration<br />
Call/WhatsApp Us: https://wa.me/+442033222718<br />
Target Audience;     	<br />
Neuroscience professionals, mental health clinicians, researchers, academic institutions, healthcare providers, students, medical practitioners, psychologists, neurologists, psychiatrists, neuro-oncologists, neuropsychologists, cognitive and behavioural scientists, neuroscience societies, mental health organizations, neuroscience and mental health associations, research institutions, universities, pharmaceutical companies, clinical researchers, mental health advocates, neuroscience educators, health technology innovators, mental health campaigners, clinical practitioners, neuroimaging experts, cognitive researchers, neurorehabilitation specialists, epidemiologists, public health officials, healthcare administrators and mental health professionals. Professors,</p>
     <p>5ANNBDUCG2026-SUPPORTING JOURNALS<br />
Unified Citation Journals is a platform for the latest discoveries in Technology, Science, engineering, medicine, medical clinical, and advancing discoveries and health. We at Unified Citation Journals ensure the advancement of healthcare and improve performance for the benefit of humanity. Unified Citation Journals empower and publish scientific research work. We will be including special issues and symposia papers in related journals from all over the world. Apart from publishing, we also promote upcoming books covering different fields of science, medicine, engineering, technology, etc. Unified Citation Journals help Authors, Publishers, and Distributors, in growing their business multifold.</p>
     <p>Social Media</p>
     <p>https://www.linkedin.com/feed/<br />
https://x.com/m_resma28240<br />
https://www.instagram.com/m_resma28240/<br />
https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=61570645640257<br />
https://www.xing.com/profile/DrResma_Mohamed<br />
https://identity.flickr.com/c<br />
https://in.pinterest.com/settings#profile<br />
https://www.tumblr.com/dashboard<br />
https://www.reddit.com/user/Potential-Smile5171/</p>
     <p>More details: https://ucjournals.com/  <br />
Submit your e-posters today!<br />
Poster Community is a medium of electronic presentation of your scientific posters that allows you to present and publish the latest scientific research work of your interest in front of worldwide viewers, learners, and open access community. A poster is worth a thousand words; it’s self-explanatory – it stands on its own and does most of your explanation digitally. We welcome researchers to submit their posters and make it visible. Posters can contain many different rich resources such as research work, case reports, presentations, company profiles, assignments, images, trending news, projects, summaries, results, apps, links, etc. </p>
     <p>------------------------------<br />
Community: Utilitarian Conferences Gathering</p>
     <p>Companies House – GOV.UK Reg. No. 14991959<br />
Registered in England &amp; Wales, UK<br />
The above information is communicated by electronic means and authenticated by the Registrar of Companies under section 1115 of the Companies Act 2006</p>
     <p>Utilitarian Conferences Gathering offers a wide range of events, Meetings, Conferences, Workshops, and symposiums. We have a dedicated team who are aimed at acquiring the technologies, adopting the knowledge of business needs, and accelerating with the best ideas and strategies. Utilitarian Conferences Gathering is a pioneer in the area of Event Management, Collaboration. We are a full-service event provider specializing in the field of Medical, Clinical, Healthcare, Life Sciences, Engineering, Pharma, Environmental Science, Engineering, Business, Agricultural, and Food event services for Academic and Industrial Sectors. We stand out distinctively from our competitors for our commitment to quality, round-the-clock service, and unmatched price. We are able to provide you with the best event, Meeting experience under one roof. We at Utilitarian Conferences Gathering make sure that you as a client choose the most appropriate event.</p>
     <p>More Information: <br />
https://utilitarianconferences.com/<br />
https://twitter.com/UCGConferences<br />
Facebook: https://www.facebook.com/utilitarianconferences.gathering.7</p>
    </body>

    <link>https://neuroscience.utilitarianconferences.com/</link>
    <tags>
            <tag key="ae">
          United Arab Emirates      </tag>
            <tag key="meeting"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
