<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eventset>
  <version>1</version>
  <event start="2026-03-12T13:00:00Z" end="2026-03-12T14:40:00Z">
        <title>Philosophy of Free Software in Pesaro, Italia</title>
    <group>
     <name>None</name> 
     <url></url>
    </group>

    <body>
      <p>(Italian belowe)</p>
     <p>On Thursday, 12 March, at 2 p.m. in the auditorium of the “Guglielmo Marconi” Scientific High School in Pesaro, there will be a meeting about the philosophy of Free Software, supported by the Free Software Foundation Europe and organised by Giacomo Alessandroni.</p>
     <p>Pupils, and anyone else who wishes to attend, will have the opportunity to chat with Professor Lorenzo Angeli, researcher and lecturer at the University of Trento, and Emanuele Solferino, a young software developer about the philosophy of Free Software, seen as a new form of resistance.</p>
     <p>The meeting will conclude with a cake composed of lots of ice cream cones (a tribute to Ada &amp;amp; Zangemann, which older children also love) with the FSFE logo proudly displayed on top.</p>
     <p>The event is open to everyone and no registration is required. The official language of the event will be Italian. It will be held on Thursday, 12 March 2026, at 2:00 p.m. at Via Nanterre, 10, 61121, Pesaro.</p>
     <p>---</p>
     <p>Giovedì 12 marzo, alle ore 14:00 nell&amp;#039;aula magna del Liceo Scientifico &amp;quot;Guglielmo Marconi&amp;quot;, Pesaro, si terrà un incontro sulla filosofia del Software Libero, patrocinato dalla Free Software Foundation Europe e organizzato da Giacomo Alessandroni.</p>
     <p>Gli studenti, e chiunque vorrà partecipare, dialogheranno con il professor Lorenzo Angeli, ricercatore e professore presso l’Università di Trento ed Emanuele Solferino, giovane sviluppatore software sulla filosofia del Software Libero, inteso come nuova forma di resistenza.</p>
     <p>L&amp;#039;incontro si concluderà con una torta, composta con tanti coni gelato (per ricordare Ada &amp;amp; Zangemann, che piace tanto anche ai bambini grandi) dove sulla vetta farà bella mostra di sé il logo della FSFE.</p>
     <p>L&amp;#039;evento è aperto a tutti e non è necessaria registrazione. La lingua ufficiale dell&amp;#039;evento sarà l&amp;#039;italiano. Si terrà giovedì 12 marzo 2026 alle ore 14:00 in Via Nanterre, 10, 61121, Pesaro.</p>
    </body>

    
    <tags>
            <tag key="it">
          Italia      </tag>
            <tag key="infobooth"/>
<tag key="meeting"/>
      <tag key="front-page"/>
    </tags>
  </event>
</eventset>
