<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<service-status-data>
  <version>1</version>
  <incident name="Mailing list and git service">
    <update date="2026-06-02">
      We are experiencing exceptional traffic on our systems caused by a DDoS attack. We are taking measures for mitigation. Please apologise if systems are reacting slower that you expected or if your client has been blocked by mistake.
    </update>
  </incident>
  <incident name="Power outtage in Data Center">
    <update date="2026-06-02" resolved="true">
      One of the data centers FSFE is hosting servers in is affected by a power outage. The DC technicians are working to resolve the issue. Services disrupted include: Nextcloud, git, IMAP, XMPP...
    </update>
    <update date="2026-06-03">
      There were some follow-up network outtages early in the morning CEST. It is assumed that technicians in the DC did some maintenance work after the incident of yesterday.
    </update>
  </incident>
  <incident name="Federation of Matrix service disrupted">
    <update date="2026-05-04">
      The federation-that is the distribution of messages to and from other Matrix servers-of the FSFE Matrix server is currently disrupted. The reason for this is unknown at the moment. System Hackers are investigating the issue.
    </update>
    <update date="2026-05-05" resolved="true">
      Federation has been restored and the server is now catching up with the relayed postings. Hence it may be a bit slow.
    </update>
  </incident>
  <incident name="Login to git.fsfe.org not possible">
      <update date="2026-04-30">
          After the update of gitea at the 29th it seems that the login to git.fsfe.org is currently not possible. System Hackers are working to resolve the issue.
      </update>
      <update date="2026-05-05" resolved="true">
        The issue has been resolved.
      </update>
  </incident>
  <incident name="Matrix connection problems">
    <update date="2026-03-02">
      There have been reports of connection problems to our Matrix server on the weekend. System Hackers are investigating the problem.
    </update>
    <update date="2026-03-03">
      FSFE System Hackers have identified issues on the Database of the Matrix service and are working on resolving them.
    </update>
    <update date="2026-04-21">
      The Matrix server sees an unusual high system LOAD at the moment which is investigated by the System Hackers. This LOAD might cause problems of clients connecting to the server.
    </update>
    <update date="2026-04-22" resolved="true">
      The high LOAD problems have been resolved.
    </update>
  </incident>
  <incident name="planet.fsfe.org">
    <update date="2025-09-01">
      The blog aggregator is currently not available. Reasons are being investigated.
    </update>
    <update date="2025-11-05">
	  Reason is, that the used blog aggregator (venus) has been deprecated.
    </update>
    <update date="2026-01-07">
      Update from Chaos Congress, delayed due re-entry into normal time. System Hackers working on a replacement for the blog aggregator so that planet.fsfe.org hopefully sees new content <em>soon</em>.
    </update>
  </incident>
  <incident name="wiki.fsfe.org">
    <update date="2025-05-30">
      After a DDoS to the service we temporarily forbit some event listings.
    </update>
    <update date="2026-01-06">
	  The content of the wiki has been moved to docs.fsfe.org
    </update>
  </incident>
  <incident name="initial login at docs.fsfe.org">
	  <update date="2025-04-01">
		The initial import from LDAP of the user permissions does not work correctly. Please contact the techsupport(at)fsfe.org helpdesk after your initial login to docs.fsfe.org which will result in an error about missing permissions. We will add your account then into the correct usergroup of the wiki system.
	  </update>
  </incident>
</service-status-data>
