<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2021-10-08">
    <title>Learn about Free Software in the Legal Context with FSFE's Legal Education Day</title>
    <body>
      <p> 
    The FSFE is organizing a Legal Education Day on Saturday, 6 November 2021. 
    This online event is open for all to attend. It will include talks and Q&amp;A 
    sessions on the basics of copyright law, licenses, and other legal topics. 
    The event will help Free Software developers to understand these legal topics 
    so that their software projects can reach their full potential. 
  </p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

  <h1>Learn about Free Software in the Legal Context with FSFE's Legal Education Day</h1>

  <p> 
    The FSFE is organizing a Legal Education Day on Saturday, 6 November 2021. 
    This online event is open for all to attend. It will include talks and Q&amp;A 
    sessions on the basics of copyright law, licenses, and other legal topics. 
    The event will help Free Software developers to understand these legal topics 
    so that their software projects can reach their full potential. 
  </p> 

  <figure>
    <a href="/freesoftware/legal/led.html"><img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/0da56c8e80fb13769adfd7010e20e529.png"/></a>
  </figure>
  
    

  <p>
    We all love the <a href="/freesoftware/freesoftware.html#freedoms">four freedoms</a> that Free Software grants to users and developers, and how they benefit the 
    individual user as well as digital society as a whole. In order to ensure 
    these freedoms, users of Free Software rely on legal instruments and the 
    legal system to be able to enforce them when other try to take them away 
    from us.   
  </p>
  
  
  <p>
    Understanding and complying with the legal frameworks and licensing 
    obligations can sometimes feel daunting. Nonetheless, some basic knowledge 
    can keep you and your software project safer from legal aspects, while it 
    helps to build a healthy Free Software environment based on openness and 
    community.
  </p>
  
  
  <p>
   We are happy to be organizing the <a href="/freesoftware/legal/led.html">FSFE online Legal Education Day</a> on <strong>Saturday, 6 November 2021, at 12:00 CET</strong>. The event will be held <strong>online</strong> on the <a href="https://conf.fsfe.org/b/gab-kdi-9dp-m7c2">FSFE’s infrastructure</a> and is open for all to attend free of charge. With this event, we aim to spread basic legal education on the legal context of Free Software, so that licensing your project and meeting legal obligations in your software project will be less of a daunting task!.
  </p>


  <p>
    Stay tuned for more updates on the <a href="/freesoftware/legal/led.html">LED homepage.</a> In the meantime, you can optionally choose to <a href="https://registration.fsfe.org/LED2021">register</a> your attendance with us, so that we can get a good idea of how many people will be attending the event.
  </p>
  
  <p>
  We hope to see you there soon!
  </p>


</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/0da56c8e80fb13769adfd7010e20e529.png" alt=""/>
    <link>/news/2021/news-20211008-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="licensing">Licensing</tag>
  <tag key="reuse">REUSE</tag>
  <tag key="copyright">Copyright</tag>
  <tag key="compliance">Compliance</tag>
</tags>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/749"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
