<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2021-12-10">
    <title>The FSFE is looking for an office assistant</title>
    <body>
      <p>
    We are looking for an office assistant for 20-25 hours per week in our
    Berlin office. As part of our office management team you will organise the
    FSFE's day-to-day operations. Your job will be to provide clerical support
    to our staff and coordinate daily administrative activities.
  </p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

  <h1>The FSFE is looking for an office assistant</h1>

  <p>
    We are looking for an office assistant for 20-25 hours per week in our
    Berlin office. As part of our office management team you will organise the
    FSFE's day-to-day operations. Your job will be to provide clerical support
    to our staff and coordinate daily administrative activities.
  </p>

  <p>
    Our ideal candidate has experience as an office administrator, secretary,
    event organiser, or another relevant administrative role. As a family
    friendly organisation we can offer flexible working hours.
  </p>

  <h2>About the FSFE</h2>

  <p>
    Free Software Foundation Europe is a charity that empowers users to control
    technology. Software is deeply involved in all aspects of our lives and it
    is important that technology empowers rather than restricts us. Free
    Software gives everybody the rights to use, understand, adapt, and share
    software. These rights help support other fundamental freedoms like freedom
    of speech, press, and privacy.
  </p>

  <p>
    The FSFE helps individuals and organisations to understand how Free Software
    contributes to freedom, transparency, and self-determination. It enhances
    users' rights by abolishing barriers to Free Software adoption, encourages
    people to use and develop Free Software, and provides resources to enable
    everyone to further promote Free Software in Europe.
  </p>

  <p>
    We are involved in <a href="/activities/">many activities</a> in the legal,
    economic, political and technical areas around Free Software. Our work is
    made possible by a community of volunteers, supporters, donors, and staff.
    The office assistant's job will be to be the administrative backbone of our
    operations.
  </p>

  <figure>
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/e88678b1f41368ab7106657ce298706e.jpg" alt="Bulletin Board with a post saying: Make things happen"/>
  </figure>

  <h2 id="main-responsibilities">Main responsibilities</h2>

  <ul>
    <li>Handle sourcing vendors, (re)-ordering, organising, invoicing, shipping,
    and the inventory for our information material and merchandise.</li>
    <li>Support volunteers and staff with logistics and send packages for
    running information booths.</li>
    <li>Book meetings and schedule events.</li>
    <li>Make travel arrangements.</li>
    <li>Process incoming letters and file them.</li>
    <li>Order office stationery, supplies and promotional materials.</li>
    <li>Organise, store, and print organisational documents as needed.</li>
    <li>Manage office equipment including organising smaller and bigger office
    supplies, assets inventory, and key management.</li>
    <li>Help to constantly improve our administrative processes.</li>
  </ul>

  <h2 id="qualifications">Qualifications</h2>

  <ul>
    <li>Proven experience as an administrator, administrative assistant, or
    another related role.</li>
    <li>Familiarity with office equipment.</li>
    <li>Very reliable, well-organised, and supportive of colleagues.</li>
    <li>Problem-solving attitude with an eye for detail.</li>
    <li>Fluency in written and spoken German, intermediate command of written
    and spoken English; other European languages are considered an asset.</li>
    <li>Experience with office management tools (Free Software tools are a
    plus).
    </li>
  </ul>

  <h2 id="attitude">Attitude</h2>

  <p>
    We are looking for a reliable, well-organised, and punctual team player who
    will be part of our administrative backbone in Berlin and thus support the
    organisation in making the world better for future generations.
  </p>

  <figure>
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/f950c5bdd4accb6f9082f91f06a8f882.jpg" alt="A picture of our promo rack in the office"/>
  </figure>

  <h2 id="how-to-apply">How to apply</h2>

  <p>
    To apply, please send a maximum one-page cover letter and a maximum two-page
    CV (only PDFs are accepted) by email to <email>jobs@fsfe.org</email>, with the subject
    "organisational wizard". Please do not include pictures of yourself in the
    application.
  </p>

  <p>
    Your personal data will be deleted 3 months after we have made our decision.
    The closing date for applications is <em>Sunday, 2 January 2022</em>.
  </p>

  <p>
    Free Software is meant to serve everyone regardless of their age, ability or
    disability, gender identity, sex, race, nationality, religion or sexual
    orientation. Hence, we encourage applications from all backgrounds and
    promise to judge all applications on merit, without reference to any of the
    characteristics listed. To promote diversity and equality in the Free
    Software community, we shall give preference to applicants who identify as
    part of a traditionally marginalised demographic in technology for
    applications of equal strength.
  </p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/f950c5bdd4accb6f9082f91f06a8f882.jpg" alt="A picture of our promo rack in the office"/>
    <link>/news/2021/news-20211210-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="internal">Internal</tag>
  <tag key="career">Job position</tag>
</tags>
  </news>
</newsset>
