<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- ***************************************************** -->
<!-- This file has been automatically generated.           -->
<!-- Please do not modify it, and do not commit it to git. -->
<!-- ***************************************************** -->

<newsset>
  <news date="2021-12-03">
    <title>Infrastructure living the ideals of software freedom</title>
    <body>
      <p>
  Can organisations with limited resources be digitally sovereign and still
  provide modern services? It is not trivial, but the FSFE proves it's possible.
  Take a deep dive with us into our infrastructure to learn how we run all the
  different services within the FSFE and cope with numerous challenges. A story
  non only for techies.
</p>
    </body>
    <body-complete>

<h1>Infrastructure living the ideals of software freedom</h1>

<p>
  Can organisations with limited resources be digitally sovereign and still
  provide modern services? It is not trivial, but the FSFE proves it's possible.
  Take a deep dive with us into our infrastructure to learn how we run all the
  different services within the FSFE and cope with numerous challenges. A story
  non only for techies.
</p>

<p>
  Charity, non-profit organisations run into limits every day: personnel,
  budget, time, and the pressing question how to use donations most efficiently.
  When it comes to technical infrastructure, many organisations unfortunately
  decide to outsource and use proprietary, non-free services. By this, they give
  up software freedom and thereby digital sovereignty and independence.
</p>

<p>
  Since its founding more than 20 years ago, the FSFE has been pursuing the
  opposite way. Right from the start, we have relied on Free Software although
  it sometimes meant not being able to use and offer trendy services. Also,
  given the limited resources, we constantly have to choose between useful
  features and maintainability.
</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/a9669e241527f1769e2fe67418a77f0d.jpg" alt="The four freedoms and Free Software services on top"/>
</figure>

<p>
  And still, neither is our infrastructure perfect nor is it 1:1 transferable to
  other organisations. But we think it's important that organisations exchange
  their experiences and learning, especially when it's about something as
  important as software freedom.
</p>

<p>
  Therefore, let us take you on a journey through our infrastructure and its
  principles, from shiny user interfaces of our <a href="#services">services</a>, crossing the <a href="#virtualisation">virtualisation methods</a> and <a href="#monitoring">monitoring</a>, down to the <a href="#servers">bare metal
  servers</a> they are running on. This is a story not only for techies, but for
  everyone interested in making or keeping an NGO independent from proprietary
  service providers.
</p>

<h2 id="team">One team and its principles</h2>

<p>
  All of the FSFE's infrastructure is managed by the <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/System-Hackers">System Hackers</a>. Only a
  few years ago, in a time of larger technical debt and restructuring, the team
  was only three people. Fortunately, since then we have experienced a steady
  growth of membership. Today, it is a healthy team consisting of 9 active
  volunteers, complemented by two staff members who dedicate some of their
  working time to the team's tasks.
</p>

<figure>
  <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/04ff9b7b037924fa522e2a1e47ac3a94.JPG" alt="A group picture of the System Hackers in 2020"/>
  <figcaption>
    Picture from the 2020 meeting of the System Hackers in Lyon
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  With a team this size it was crucial to define the <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/System-Hackers/Principles">most basic
  principles of this team</a>. They form the basis of the System Hackers' goals:
  as much control as possible over services and servers by using 100% Free
  Software, internal and external transparency, and bearable complexity, and at
  the same time providing useful features for the various FSFE teams and the
  whole community.
</p>

<p>
  Aside from purely asynchronous work, emails, and chat, the System Hackers
  also met at least once per year in pre-pandemic times, and continue doing that
  in virtual form. During these meetings, we were able to tackle more complex
  decisions and technical changes efficiently, but also just enjoyed
  non-technical conversations and fun activities. The team is coordinated by us,
  the authors of this text, Albert and Max, who also maintain a large number of
  services and systems.
</p>

<h2 id="services">Services, services everywhere</h2>

<p>
  The FSFE's infrastructure is very service-oriented. Volunteers and staff rely
  on basic functionality like sending and receiving email or exchanging files,
  but also on a website fed by a version control system, a wiki, or video chat
  systems. To give an example for the complex interconnection of different
  components, just drafting and releasing this news item involved at least 12
  services that have to seamlessly work together.
</p>

<module id="banner-become-supporter"/>

<p>
  The currently most crucial and used services contain Mailman for mailing
  lists, or Gitea as our Git version control system. To allow sharing and saving
  knowledge our <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/Teams/WikiCaretakers">Wiki
  Caretakers</a> maintain MoinMoin, while Björn takes care of Nextcloud to share
  files, coordinate tasks, and collaboratively edit documents. We run our own
  BigBlueButton and Jitsi instances for video conferencing, and XMPP/Jabber for
  text-based chats. Very recent service additions are Matrix as another chat
  service, initiated and maintained by Michael, and Peertube for hosting and
  sharing our videos on own infrastructure, made possible by Alvar.
</p>

<p>
  The list of services is <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/TechDocs/Services">much
  larger</a> and also contains fundamental systems like the Account Management
  System and Community Database developed by <a href="/news/2021/news-20210305-01.html">Reinhard</a>, our own DNS servers, or
  Drone as our CI/CD system that processes data from Gitea, checks them, and
  deploys them on other servers eventually.
</p>

<p>
  Needless to say, the team regularly receives requests to provide
  additional services. Here, the challenge is to make a careful selection
  based on available resources (computing, space, volunteer time) and
  estimated use for the organisation, and evaluating whether a solution is
  well-maintainable, not largely overlapping with existing services, and
  generally leaving a good impression.
</p>

<p>
  Sometimes that also means we have to test solutions in practice over a
  longer period of time. Real-time editing of documents is a good example
  for that, for which we currently have multiple possibilities available.
  Longer documents are often edited as ODF files via Collabora Online
  attached to Nextcloud, but some editors prefer Etherpad or use Git directly.
  All solutions have advantages and downsides, and finding a good path
  between having diverse options on one side, and tool overload on the other
  is anything but trivial.
</p>

<h2 id="virtualisation">Virtualisation and deployment</h2>

<p>
  While the FSFE owns dedicated servers in actual racks (we will come to
  that later), all services run in some sort of virtualisation. In total
  there are 43 virtual machines distributed over different data centres
  at the time of writing this article. Some have a purely internal
  role, for instance being a gateway for other virtual machines or
  assisting web services with obtaining TLS certificates.
</p>

<figure class="no-border">
  <a href="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/big/0b41e57a4d5163ef911cfd913b9af640.png">
    <img src="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/0b41e57a4d5163ef911cfd913b9af640.png" alt="All virtual servers of the FSFE"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    An overview of the currently running virtual servers of the FSFE, and their
    distribution over the different clusters.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>
  Some others, in turn, themselves host a number of diverse services. Since 2017
  we have been using <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/explore/repos?q=docker&amp;topic=1">Docker</a> as a
  container engine. That has not been an easy choice since the technology adds
  a lot of complexity and sometimes requires stunning workarounds to be operated
  in a secure fashion. On the other hand, especially for smaller services or
  larger self-coded tools, it is great to spin them up quickly, test and deploy
  them via our Continuous Integration system, provide a more or less uniform
  local development environment, and maintain an (admittedly limited)
  reproducibility of configurations.
</p>

<p>
  We are regularly evaluating alternative engines that provide a more
  seamless rootless mode, are still compatible with our CI/CD system
  (Drone) and reverse proxy, and ideally do not require a major rewrite of
  existing deployment code. Also, here again, it is important for the
  System Hackers that at least two members understand a high-priority
  technology in depth.
</p>

<p>
  To bootstrap virtual machines and deploy non-container services in a
  reproducible way, we <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/explore/repos?q=ansible&amp;topic=1">rely a lot on
  Ansible</a>, a provisioning and configuration management tool. While Ansible
  deployments may also have their shortcomings, we appreciate the
  infrastructure-as-code approach that can be executed from any computer and
  does not require a central server. Meanwhile, only the minority of services
  are deployed via neither Ansible nor Docker which makes understanding existing
  infrastructure, onboarding new volunteers, and documenting changes much
  easier.
</p>

<h2 id="monitoring">The all-seeing eye and uniformity</h2>

<p>
  Dozens of servers and services: how do you know if there is a problem with one
  of them? We have to admit that up until two years ago we sometimes only learnt
  about a crashed server via an email from a random friendly community member.
  Now a <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers/monitoring">monitoring system
  based on Icinga2</a> takes care of this. Currently 50 hosts and 690 services
  are continuously checked, for example for pending upgrades of the operating
  system, systemd services, failed backups, disk space, or TLS certificate
  validity.
</p>

<p>
  This is eased by other parts of our strategy: except 4 virtual machines, all
  run on Debian GNU/Linux. After initial creation, a new machine will experience
  a <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers/baseline">baseline</a>
  setup taking care of fundamental security settings, monitoring, backup, and
  automatic upgrades. Thanks to this, maintenance of a server is mostly limited
  to the service it is running, and other improvements can be applied to a large
  number of hosts automatically within a few minutes.
</p>

<p>
  To further ease management and maintenance, we sometimes write our own
  tools. For instance
  <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers/ssh-key-distributor">ssh-key-distributor</a>
  provides a simple interface and deployment method to manage and
  document access via SSH on our servers. Or
  <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers/docker-utils">docker-utils</a>
  which is tailored to our Docker infrastructure and takes care of analysing and
  upgrading Docker images and containers. Both tools have been created by our
  working student Linus. You can find more tools and generally most
  Ansible/Docker deployment code in the System Hackers'
  <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers">Git organisation</a>.
</p>

<h2 id="servers">Bare metal servers</h2>

<p>
  Unlike the current trend of the IT industry, we are proud to run the
  vast majority of services on our own physical servers. This guarantees
  the most sovereignty, data security by full disk encryption, and
  technological independence for us. To increase resilience, we bundle
  three servers each into a Proxmox cluster with Ceph storage, so if one
  physical server crashes a virtual machine is just moved to one of the
  two other servers in the cluster.
</p>

<p>
  As an additional safety net, the three clusters and a solo machine are spread
  over four different data centres which <a href="/donate/hardware.html">kindly
  donate the colocation</a> to us.
</p>

<p>
  However, this is only possible thanks to a fortunate combination of
  conditions. First of all, we are lucky to have Albert with us who has a lot of
  experience with, among various other areas, Proxmox, Ceph, and the depths of
  networking. Then, we have the kind support of the data centres providing
  colocation as well as hardware donors, and the <fsfe-cd-donate-link>FSFE
  supporters</fsfe-cd-donate-link> that contribute financially. And we also
  profit from a more or less identical setup on all four sites which makes
  maintenance a bit easier. But still, we are considering giving up the cluster
  containing the oldest servers as well as the solo physical machine to reduce
  work and complexity.
</p>

<h2 id="challenges">Challenges behind and ahead</h2>

<p>
  Over the course of the years, we managed to overcome many challenges:
  technical debt, antique software that blocked operating system upgrades,
  lack of hardware resources, fatal crashes of single points of failures,
  and hard technical decisions about how to develop the infrastructure
  further. In one of these hard times, our back-then intern and since then System Hacker
  <a href="/about/people/interviews/lequertier.html">Vincent</a>
  played an important role and helped set the foundation for the good state we
  are in today. Despite all preparation and evaluation, we have made many
  mistakes, but most importantly we have learnt a lot by them.
</p>

<module id="banner-subscribe"/>

<p>
  Facing us right now are new hurdles. For example, with the high amount of
  servers, we can no longer give every virtual machine a dedicated IPv4 address.
  Unfortunately, many technologies and internet services, even large proprietary
  and supposedly professional companies, still do not support the more modern,
  future-proof, and already 20 years old IPv6 protocol. This requires us to
  fiddle around with a few hacks like <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers/ip-proxy/">reverse proxies</a>,
  <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers/docker2caddy/">container
  discovery services</a>,
  <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers/fsfe-gw">NAT</a>, and <a href="https://git.fsfe.org/fsfe-system-hackers/innernet-playbook">VPNs</a>.
</p>

<p>
  Another interesting decision ahead is the one of communication channels. While
  plain-text email and, since 2004, XMPP/Jabber
  have formed the de-facto standard within the FSFE, many people meanwhile
  prefer <a href="https://wiki.fsfe.org/TechDocs/Matrix">Matrix</a>,
  <a href="https://community.fsfe.org">Discourse</a>, or still the traditional
  IRC. While we see advantages and disadvantages for all of them, we also want
  to avoid fragmentation of our community. This is not a pure technical
  question, but a great example of the need for good inter-team communication
  and decision-making.
</p>

<p>
  Last but not least, we have a few technologies that are head scratchers
  for us. Let's take Mailman 2 as an example that has powered our 116
  mailing lists for years. Unfortunately, the project is no longer
  actively developed, and the successor and its alternatives all have
  serious downsides. Here, we need to conduct a careful evaluation and many
  tests, and eventually find the best solution in the mass of imperfect
  options.
</p>

<p>
  With all that said, we would like to express our thanks to the many Free
  Software projects and their developers out there. They grant us the ability to
  choose from different solutions, they form the basis of our infrastructure,
  and they provide astonishing solutions that make our lives easier every day.
  It is a pleasure to be part of this large community.
</p>

<h2>Why all of this?</h2>

<p>
  As you can see, the technical infrastructure of our organisation is anything
  but boring or simple. This is not only due to the size of the FSFE and its
  community, but also due to our own high standards: living software freedom in
  practice and maintaining as much technical independence and sovereignty as
  possible. At the same time, we care for technical accessibility to also allow
  non-technical contributors to interact with our services. That sometimes
  requires extra work and tools, but we are convinced that it is worth it.
</p>

<p>
  All of this depends on the dedication and long-time commitment of many people,
  and is fed by its productive use and the feedback of the whole FSFE community.
  And it is only possible thanks to the FSFE's supporters who enable us to
  invest resources in a fully Free Software infrastructure. If you share this
  ideal, <fsfe-cd-donate-link>please consider a donation</fsfe-cd-donate-link>.
</p>

</body-complete>
    <image url="https://pics.fsfe.org/uploads/medium/a9669e241527f1769e2fe67418a77f0d.jpg" alt="The four freedoms and Free Software services on top"/>
    <link>/news/2021/news-20211203-01.html</link>
    <tags>
  <tag key="front-page"/>
  <tag key="internal">FSFE Internal</tag>
  <tag key="tech-teams">Technical Teams</tag>
</tags>
    <author id="dengg"/>
    <author id="mehl"/>
    <discussion href="https://community.fsfe.org/t/775"/>
  </news>
</newsset>
