<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<textset>

<!-- ALL STATIC TEXTS -->

  <!-- Basic texts -->
  <text id="fsfeurope">Free Software Foundation&#160;Europe</text>
  <text id="fsfnetwork">
    FSFE has <a href="/about/fsfnetwork.html">sister organisations</a> in <a
      href="//www.fsf.org/">North America</a>, <a
      href="http://fsf.org.in/">India</a> and <a
      href="http://www.fsfla.org/">Latin America</a>.
  </text>


  <!-- Footer -->
  <text id="lastchanged"> Last changed: </text>
  <text id="translator1a">We thank </text>
  <text id="translator1b"> for this translation. </text>
  <text id="translator2">This is an unofficial translation. </text>
  <text id="translator3a">Please also see to the </text>
  <text id="translator3b">original text</text>
  <text id="translator3c"> of this page.</text>
  <text id="permission">
    Verbatim copying and distribution of this entire article is permitted
    in any medium, provided this notice is preserved.
  </text>


  <!-- Warning info boxes -->
  <text id="outdated">
    <strong>Warning: </strong>
    This page may be out of date with the original. Please use
    <a href="/contribute/contribute.html">this page</a> to see how you can help
    with translations, and other things.
  </text>
  <text id="outdated-1">
    <strong>Warning: </strong>
    This page may be out of date with the
  </text>
  <text id="outdated-2">
    Please use
    <a href="/contribute/contribute.html">this page</a> to see how you can help
    with translations, and other things.
  </text>
  <text id="notranslation">
    <strong>Warning: </strong>
    This page has not been translated yet. What you are seeing below
    is the original version of the page. Please use
    <a href="/contribute/contribute.html">this page</a> to see how you can help
    with translations, and other things.
  </text>
    <text id="under-construction">
    <strong>Warning: </strong>This page is under construction. Please <strong>do not spread</strong> or attempt translation as its content is subject to change.
  </text>
    <text id="project-complete">This project has been successfully finished. These pages are kept here for archiving purposes.  </text>
  
  
  <!-- Menu, Navigation, Buttons -->
  <text id="fsfe/about">About</text>
  <text id="fsfe/projects">Our Work</text>
  <text id="fsfe/campaigns">Campaigns</text>
  <text id="fsfe/help">Contribute</text>
  <text id="fsfe/press">Press</text>
  <text id="fsfe/contact">Contact us</text>
  <text id="support/donate">Donate</text>
  <text id="support/support">Support</text>
  <text id="support/order">Shop</text>
  <text id="support/thankgnus">Donors</text>
  <text id="fellowship/fellowship">Fellowship</text>
  <text id="fellowship/login">Login</text>
  <text id="fellowship/join">Join</text>
  <text id="fellowship/card">Card</text>
  <text id="fellowship/faq">F.A.Q.</text>
  <text id="campaigns/dfd">Document Freedom Day</text>
  <text id="campaigns/fya">Free Your Android</text>
  <text id="campaigns/pdf">PDF readers</text>
  <text id="campaigns/ayc">Ask your candidates</text>
  <text id="campaigns/drm">DRM.info</text>
  <text id="news/news">Latest News</text>
  <text id="news/events">Upcoming Events</text>
  <text id="news/press">Press Room</text>
  <text id="news/nl">Newsletters</text>
  <text id="news/planet">Planet blogs</text>
  <text id="ftf/legal">Legal support</text>
  <text id="ftf/services">Services and Fiduciary</text>
  <text id="ftf/doc">Documentation</text>
  <text id="ftf/network">Legal Network</text>
  <text id="ftf/conference">Conferences</text>
  <text id="ftf/contact">Contact FSFE Legal Team</text>
  <text id="fs/fs">Free Software</text>
  <text id="fs/basics">Free Software Basics</text>
  <text id="fs/def">Definition</text>
  <text id="fs/soc">Free Society</text>
  <text id="fs/edu">Education</text>
  <text id="fs/buz">Business</text>
  <text id="community/discuss">Free Software Discussions</text>
  
  <text id="motto-fsfs">Free Software, Free Society!</text>
  <text id="motto-fellowship">Join FSFE’s community!</text>
  <text id="learn-more">Learn more</text>
  <text id="press">Press</text>
  <text id="newsletter">Newsletter</text>
  
  <text id="go-to">Go to:</text>
  <text id="search">Search</text>
  <text id="submit">Submit</text>
  <text id="subscribe">Subscribe</text>
  <text id="news">News</text>
  <text id="receive-newsletter">Subscribe to FSFE's monthly newsletter</text>
  <text id="subscribe-newsletter">Subscribe to the newsletter</text>
  <text id="events">Events</text>
  <text id="more">See more</text>
  <text id="morenews">See all news</text>
  <text id="moreevents">See all events</text>
  <text id="contact">Contact</text>
  <text id="team">Team</text>
  <text id="microblog">Microblog</text>
  <text id="no-avatar">No Picture</text>

  <text id="change-lang">Change language</text>
  <text id="menu">Menu</text>
  <text id="content">Content</text>
  <text id="page-info">Page info</text>
  <text id="rootpage">Home</text>
  <text id="sitemap">Sitemap</text>
  <text id="go-top">Go to the top</text>
  <text id="source">Source code</text>
  <text id="contact-us">Contact us</text>
  <text id="translate">Translate this page?</text>
  <text id="contribute-web">Contribute to the Web team</text>
  <text id="imprint">Imprint</text>
  <text id="privacy-policy">Privacy Policy</text>
  <text id="tags">Tags</text>


  <!-- Article metadata -->
  <text id="author">Author</text>
  <text id="writtenby">Written&#160;by</text>
  <text id="published">on</text>
  <text id="revision">updated&#160;on</text>
  <text id="download">Download</text>


  <!-- Petitions -->
  <text id="osig">Organisations</text>
  <text id="isig">Individuals</text>
  <text id="bsig">Businesses</text>
  
  
  <!-- Sidebars -->
  <text id="related-news">Related News</text>
  <text id="our-work">Our Work</text>
  <text id="our-work-intro">
    <p>As a non-profit, non-governmental organisation, Free Software Foundation 
    Europe works to create general understanding and support for Free Software 
    and Open Standards in politics, business, law and society at large.</p>
  </text>
  <text id="about-fsfe">About FSFE</text>
  <text id="about-fsfe-intro">
    <p>
      Free Software Foundation Europe is dedicated to the furthering of Free 
      Software and working for <strong>freedom</strong> in the emerging digital 
      society.
    </p>
    <p>
      Access to software determines who may participate in a digital society.  
      The freedoms to <a href="/about/basics/freesoftware.html">use, study, 
      share, and improve</a> software allow <strong>equal</strong> 
      participation, and are extremely important.
    </p>
  </text>


  <!-- Motivational texts for fellowship, support or donations -->
  <text id="join">Join</text>
  <text id="join-paragraph">
    <p>Become a Fellow of the FSFE to empower our work and help to assure our financial independence. By joining the Fellowship you will become a donating, sustaining member of the FSFE - including access to our infrastructure.</p>
  </text>
  <text id="join-fellowship">Join the Fellowship</text>

  <text id="support">Support the FSFE</text>
  <text id="show-support">Show your support!</text>
  <text id="show-support-paragraph">
      <p>FSFE needs your support to get its voice heard! Every hit counts!</p>
  </text>
  <text id="support-fsfe">I support the FSFE!</text>

  <text id="donate">Donate</text>
  <text id="donate-paragraph">
    <p>
      The Free Software Foundation Europe is a non-profit non-governmental
      organisation. <a href="/work.html">Our work</a> is made
      possible by a community of
      <a href="/contribute/contribute.html">volunteers</a>,
      <a href="/fellowship">Fellows</a> and
      <a href="/donate/thankgnus.html">donors</a>. Your donations are critical to our
      strength and autonomy. They enable us to continue working for Free
      Software wherever necessary, and to be an independent voice.
    </p>
  </text>



<!-- ALL CAMPAIGN TEXTS -->

  <campaigns>
    <!-- campaigns to be displayed in a rotating box on frontpage --> 
    <campaign id="freesociety">
        <text>Free Software, <br />Free Society!</text>
        <link>/freesoftware/</link>
    </campaign>
    <campaign id="dfd">
        <photo>/graphics/robot-protest-light.png</photo>
        <text>
        Celebrating information accessibility and raising awareness of Open Standards.
        </text>
        <link>//documentfreedom.org</link>
    </campaign>

    <campaign id="ilovefs">
        <text>
        Show your love for Free Software and thank developers.
        </text>
        <link>/campaigns/ilovefs/ilovefs.html</link>
    </campaign>
    
    <campaign id="zacchiroli" tag="donors" pos="1">
      <photo>/donate/zacchiroli.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        A world without Free Software is a world where we are all hostages of
        proprietary software vendors that run our lives. To fight such a
        nightmare scenario we need organisations like Free Software Foundation
        Europe.
      </text>
      <author>Stefano "Zack" Zacchiroli, Former Debian Project Leader</author>
      <link>/fellowship/index.html</link>
    </campaign>

    <campaign id="becomefellow">
        <photo>/graphics/fellowship/fellowship-page-logo-300x91.png</photo>
        <text>
          Become a Fellow of the FSFE to empower our work and help to assure
          our financial independence! 
        </text>
      <link>/fellowship/</link>
    </campaign>
    
    <campaign id="appelbaum" tag="donors" pos="2">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/jacobappelbaum.png</photo>
      <text>
        I believe that actions of support for the FSFE are important for
        encouraging Free Software development and adoption in Europe as well
        as the rest of the world. I&#39;m an FSFE Fellow because financially
        supporting the cause of Free Software brings positive improvements to
        all societies throughout the world.
      </text>
      <author>Jacob Appelbaum - Spokesperson for The TOR Project</author>
      <link>/fellowship/index.html</link>
    </campaign>
  </campaigns>
  

  

<!-- ALL QUOTES -->

  <quotes>

    <!-- quotes for fellowship page -->
   <quote id="giedke" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/giedke.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I am a strong supporter of the ideas behind free software and a daily
user of free software. I think a voice that explains why Free Software
is good for society and what are the conditions under which the Free
Software ecosystem can grow is vitally important. By joining FSF and
FSFE, I wanted to say thanks to free software advocates and developers
and help in maintaining political conditions that allow and favor free
software development and use.
      </text>
      <author>Geza Giedke > (quantum information science,
quantum optics) at DIPC, San Sebastian, Spain</author>
    </quote>

   <quote id="mats" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/mats.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I joined as a Fellow since I wanted to support FSFE's work to promote
free software. As a person that uses computers quite heavily every
day, I'm very concerned with the current trend of locking down
computing which is taking control away from the users. This is
increasingly problematic since people's lives are more and more
dependent on computers for personal communications, managing finances,
employment, etc. Free software is a necessary requirement for
retaining control over your computing.
      </text>
      <author>Mats Sjöberg (Researcher in Computer Science)</author>
    </quote>

    <quote id="morris" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/annamorris.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        Free Software challenges you to learn: to do for yourself, to be 
        fearlessly independent when it comes to your tech. In the past few 
        years I have taken pride in watching my skill base catchup with and 
        overtake that of my proprietary-loving peers, even some paid 
        professionals, simply by having a free and curious mindset. Free 
        Software frees you in many ways.
      </text>
      <author>Anna Morris (Co-Founder of ethical-pets.co.uk and Free Software advocate)</author>
    </quote>

    <quote id="magnusson" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/magnusson.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I think the FSFE does important work. And it's the only organization that I
can think of that works within the EU system. It was a natural thing
for me to support with as much funds I could spare.
      </text>
      <author>Peter Magnusson (programmer)</author>
    </quote>

    <quote id="roy" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/hugoroy.png</photo>
      <text>
        The Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE) brings together dedicated 
        and engaged activists from all over Europe to seize the opportunities 
        to secure our rights to use, share, study, and improve software because 
        without Free Software, technology subjugates us instead of enhancing 
        our freedom.
      </text>
      <author>Hugo Roy (Law student)</author>
    </quote>

    <quote id="keijzer" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/kevinkeijzer.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I joined the Fellowship to stop being &#39;a minority of one&#39;, as 
        George Orwell once put it. I wanted to meet people who shared my ideals 
        and beliefs, so it would no longer feel as if I was fighting the system 
        all by myself. It&#39;s reassuring to know that you&#39;re not alone, 
        which probably motivates people to keep up with the work they are 
        doing, even if it&#39;s not always as successful as they would like it 
        to be.
      </text>
      <author>Kevin Keijzer (Political activist)</author>
    </quote>

    <quote id="nascimento" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/mauricionascimento.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        Freedom is one of the core values of our Society and one of the basic 
        concepts of Democracy. Supporting and spreading Free Software is one 
        way to build creative alternatives for social inclusion and to protect 
        our citizens from the digital exploitation. We are responsible to build 
        a better World as a gift for our future generations.
      </text>
      <author>Mauricio Nascimento (Middleware Engineer)</author>
    </quote>

    <quote id="guenther" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/guidoguenther.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I&#39;m very impressed with what the FSFE has achieved on the EU and 
        national level. Back when I was working in the public sector I was able 
        to glimpse the vast amounts of money that are thrown at lobbying for 
        proprietary software and so called industry standards in Germany and 
        the EU. It&#39;s astonishing how the FSFE has still managed to get 
        itself heard. Supporting this was one of my motivations for becoming a 
        fellow.
      </text>
      <author>Guido Günther (Freelancer and Debian Developer)</author>
    </quote>
    
    <quote id="verheesen" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/mauriceverheesen.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        Free software is important in our time. It needs professional 
        representation which is hard work and expensive. Joining the fellowship 
        meant a way for me to contributing my skills and some money back to the 
        free software movement to ensure it&#39;s future.
      </text>
      <author>Maurice Verheesen</author>
    </quote>

    <quote id="agger" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/carstenagger.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I was a solitary voice for years, explaining the principles behind Free 
        Software and its importance for people in my country in numerous 
        articles and blog posts. I wanted to belong to an organization with the 
        goal of building the digital society on 100% free software, and 
        supporting the FSFE and gaining access to its blogging and fellowship 
        infrastructure seemed like a logical first step.
      </text>
      <author>Carsten Agger (Software Engineer)</author>
    </quote>
    
    
    <quote id="kehl" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/robertkehl.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I joined the Fellowship because Free Software helps to bring more and 
        real freedom into the world. To fight for this is my goal as a Fellow 
        of the FSFE.
      </text>
      <author>Robert Kehl (IT Professional)</author>
    </quote>
    
    <quote id="appelbaum" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/jacobappelbaum.png</photo>
      <text>
        I believe that actions of support for the FSFE are important for 
        encouraging Free Software development and adoption in Europe as well as 
        the rest of the world. I&#39;m an FSFE Fellow because financially 
        supporting the cause of Free Software brings positive improvements to 
        all societies throughout the world.
      </text>
      <author>Jacob Appelbaum (Spokesperson for The TOR Project)</author>
    </quote> 
    
    
    <quote id="mortier" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/mortier.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I&#39;m a free sofware supporter for a long time, I fought against 
        software patents in Brussels, co-organised the system theme at the 
        Libre Software Meeting (RMLL) and run a Free Software company. Free 
        Software is an essential part of our global freedom, so it was natural 
        to become a Fellowship member at the FSFE.
      </text>
      <author>Benoit Mortier (Owner of OpenSides, Manager of FusionDirectory)</author>
    </quote> 
    
    
    <quote id="nermin" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/nermincanik.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        Free software and FSFE is to me: sharing, learning, being independent 
        of monopolies, producing things together, passion and freedom! Since 
        I've been a Fellow, I am finding new friends who help me in Free 
        Software and other topics, teaching new things every day even though we 
        are kilometers away. It is magnificent to be in a community that 
        continually supports my Free Software passion and motivation!
      </text>
      <author>Nermin Canik (IT Business Analyst)</author>
    </quote> 
    
    
    <quote id="guido" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/guidoarnold.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        Free Software needs a voice in politics. We volunteers do amazing 
        things together, but some tasks are not that much fun, or are time 
        sensitive or need extensive expertise. FSFE can only tap its full 
        potential with paid staff to do the things the volunteers wouldn't get 
        to. By now, I met all of the staff and can say that I don't regret a 
        cent I've given to allow the FSFE to operate.
      </text>
      <author>Guido Arnold</author>
    </quote> 
    
    
    <quote id="laura" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/lauralarjona.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        If software is licensed as free software, we can audit it, and be sure 
        that it does what it's intended to do (and nothing else). Public 
        institutions develop software, and hire companies to make it, and the 
        citizens should own and reuse all that code. I contribute to free 
        software with translations, user help desk, finding free software 
        alternatives at the University... but I cannot reach the policy-makers, 
        nor people and institutions in other countries. I'm fellow to support 
        the FSFE doing this task, and as one more way to say thank you to the 
        free software community.
      </text>
      <author>Laura Arjona Reina (IT Assistant at Technical University of Madrid and Debian contributor)</author>
    </quote> 
      
    <quote id="volker" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/Grabsch.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I have always been fascinated by free software. I'm supporting free 
        software projects in my spare time. My education as well as my work 
        would not be possible without free software. The fellow group in Berlin 
        showed me how to contribute to free software in a non-technical way. It 
        was and still is great fun to work with them in a cogenial atmosphere. 
        As I'm involed in the group now, I think it is time to join the FSFE 
        officially and to support them financially.
      </text>
      <author>Volker Grabsch (Software development)</author>
    </quote> 
 
    
    <quote id="johannes" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/JohannesZarl.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I join the fellowship because I'm seeing more and more that writing 
        free code is ultimately not enough to foster a culture where free 
        software is seen as an integral part of society. Free software should 
        not be a fringe topic supported solely by geeks.
      </text>
      <author>Johannes Zarl (IT Professional)</author>
    </quote> 

    <quote id="oliver" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/Springer.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I have been using free software for years, during the last couple month 
        I started "giving" back, by supporting on forums and writing smaller 
        patches. But I felt like free software deserves some money, too. And 
        the Free Software Foundation is simply the best place for the money to 
        go. I also wanted to show my support for Free Software publicly.
      </text>
      <author>Oliver Springer (Systems Administrator Trainee)</author>
    </quote> 

    <quote id="tom" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/Tom.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I started doing UNIX sysadmin work while a visiting scientist at MIT in 
        the early '90s, concentrated more and more on free software as time 
        went on, and have made a living entirely from sysadminning free 
        software for the past eight years.  It's well past time that I gave 
        money back.
      </text>
      <author>Tom Yates (Free Software Consultant Sysadmin)</author>
    </quote> 

    <quote id="nicole" tag="fellowship">
      <photo>/fellowship/graphics/people/Lieger.jpg</photo>
      <text>
        I'm interested in values, politics, society; in new forms of 
        production, based on free co-operation in egalitarian structures; in 
        knowledge commons and collective intelligence. That's why I'm here and 
        why I wish to support the free software movement. I have no technical 
        background, and neither do most of the people I know.
      </text>
      <author>Nicole Lieger (Political Scientist and member of Civil Society)</author>
    </quote> 
  </quotes>
  
</textset>
