<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<timeline>
  <version>2</version>
  <year value="2025">
    <event month="05" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Lanzamiento de la iniciativa Refund4Freedom</title>
      <url>https://en.refund4freedom.org/</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE y la Sociedad Italiana de Linux han puesto en marcha conjuntamente 
      Refund4Freedom, una iniciativa destinada a ayudar a los usuarios a 
      recuperar el coste de las licencias de Windows no deseadas que vienen incluidas con el
      hardware que acaban de adquirir.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="10" type="young-generation">
      <title>Se estrena la película de animación «Ada &amp; Zangemann»</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/ada-zangemann/movie</url>
      <body>
	  El libro de la FSFE «Ada &amp; Zangemann» se adaptó a una 
      película de animación, llegando así a nuevos públicos de todo el mundo. La película 
      supuso un paso importante en la estrategia a largo plazo de la FSFE para 
      fomentar el interés de las nuevas generaciones por la libertad del software.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="01" type="org-dev">
      <title>Definición de la Visión 2048</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2025/news-20250103-01.html</url>
      <body>
	 La FSFE analizó cómo podría ser el mundo en 2048 en los distintos ámbitos de nuestro trabajo y dio pasos importantes hacia esa visión.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="07" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Aportaciones de la comunidad sobre la Ley de Ciberresiliencia</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2025/news-20250717-01.html</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE y la Oficina Federal Alemana de Seguridad de la Información (BSI) 
      colaboraron con representantes de la sociedad civil, 
      el mundo académico, la industria y las autoridades públicas en un proyecto sobre la 
      Ley de Ciberresiliencia (CRA) y sus implicaciones para el Software Libre.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="legal-education">
      <title>Se lanza la columna «Legal Corner»</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/tags/tagged-legal-corner.html</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE ha comenzado a publicar «Legal Corner», una columna periódica cuyo objetivo es 
      explicar los diversos conceptos jurídicos con los que pueden encontrarse los desarrolladores de Software Libre, 
      así como analizar la actualidad en el ámbito jurídico 
      que afecta al Software Libre.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="05" type="pmpc">
      <title>Simposio «¿Dinero público? ¡Código público! en la práctica»</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2025/news-20250409-01.html/</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE organizó el simposio «¿Dinero público? ¡Código público! en 
      la práctica», en el que representantes de la administración pública, la política, el mundo empresarial, el ámbito académico y la sociedad civil debatieron sobre cómo la contratación pública de Software Libre, su financiación y la colaboración en el ecosistema pueden reducir las dependencias y reforzar la soberanía digital.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2024">
    <event month="09" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Demanda contra Apple en virtud de la Ley de Mercados Digitales</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2024/news-20240812-01.html</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE interviene en el litigio interpuesto por Apple contra la 
      Comisión Europea ante el Tribunal de Justicia de la Unión 
      Europea. El objetivo de la FSFE es garantizar la aplicación de la DMA de una forma que favorezca a los desarrolladores.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="07" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Se solicitó financiación pública sostenible a largo plazo</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2024/news-20240808-01.html</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE respondió al recorte de la Comisión Europea en la financiación de la Iniciativa NGI, 
      destacando su exigencia de una financiación garantizada a largo plazo 
      para el software libre en toda Europa.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="03" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Lanzamiento de la web «Neutralidad del Dispositivo»</title>
      <url>https://deviceneutrality.org/</url>
      <body>
	 La FSFE ha presentado una página web específica para explicar el 
     concepto de «Neutralidad del Dispositivo» de forma sencilla y accesible para 
     todos los usuarios, independientemente de sus conocimientos técnicos.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2023">
    <event month="06" type="pmpc">
      <title>«Openwashing» en el entorno de trabajo soberano alemán</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2023/news-20230606-01.html</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE examinó de forma crítica la iniciativa del Gobierno alemán «Sovereign 
      Workplace», que se calificó como «Software Libre». Planteamos 
      dudas sobre la falta de código fuente, la rendición de cuentas y el 
      gasto público.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="10" type="pmpc">
      <title>TEDective, ganador del premio del Datathon de la UE</title>
      <url>https://media.fsfe.org/w/fphnrcqwv8cFHVkaF7Rj2q</url>
      <body>
	  «TEDective» ganó el primer premio en el Datathon de la UE. Esta herramienta de Software Libre fue diseñada por la FSFE para ayudar 
      a los ciudadanos y a los periodistas a analizar y visualizar los datos sobre el gasto público procedentes de la base de datos TED de la UE sobre contratación pública.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="10" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Se publica la wiki técnica de «Libertad del Router»</title> 
      <url>https://docs.fsfe.org/en/teams/router-freedom-tech-wiki</url>
      <body>
      La FSFE ha presentado la nueva wiki técnica de «Libertad del Router», elaborada por nuestro equipo de voluntarios de los Países Bajos. El objetivo de esta guía es sustituir el módem de tu proveedor de servicios de Internet por uno propio. 
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="09" type="pmpc">
      <title>Día de la Educación en el Fediverso</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2023/news-20231025-01.en.html</url>
      <body>
	  En colaboración con instituciones públicas, la FSFE coorganizó uno de los primeros simposios dedicados al Fediverso en Alemania. Más de 70 participantes de distintos ámbitos debatieron sobre las redes sociales descentralizadas y su importancia para las sociedades democráticas.
      </body>
    </event>
   </year>
   <year value="2022">
    <event month="03" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Inteligencia Artificial y Software Libre</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2022/news-20220330-01.html</url>
      <body>
	 La FSFE analizó cómo la IA puede ser más verificable, fiable 
     e innovadora gracias al Software Libre, y formuló recomendaciones políticas. Este resultado se 
     presentó en diferentes conferencias.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="10" type="young-generation">
      <title>Primera edición de «Youth Hacking 4 Freedom»</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/yh4f/index.html</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE ha puesto en marcha con éxito Youth Hacking 
      4 Freedom (YH4F), un concurso de programación paneuropeo y anual 
      cuyo objetivo es animar a los adolescentes a interesarse por el Software Libre.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="12" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>‘Publicación del vídeo «¿Qué es el Software Libre?»</title>
      <url>https://media.fsfe.org/w/xs29yhLxSP1uKLYkSeoKKp</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE publicó «¿Qué es el Software Libre? ¡La libertad del software explicada en menos de tres minutos!» para explicar el complejo tema de 
      la libertad del software. Este vídeo ayuda a comprender y asimilar la importancia del Software Libre.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="06" type="legal-education">
      <title>Participación de la FSFE en la Iniciativa ZOOOM</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/zooom/</url>
      <body>
	 Financiado por la Comisión Europea, el consorcio ZOOOM promovió una comprensión sólida de los requisitos de licencia 
     y las necesidades empresariales en la intersección entre el Software Libre, los datos abiertos 
     y el hardware de Código Abierto.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="11" type="legal-education">
      <title>Carta abierta: «El derecho universal a instalar cualquier software en cualquier dispositivo»</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2022/news-20221121-01.html</url>
      <body>
	 Más de 100 organizaciones de la sociedad civil de distintos sectores firmaron nuestra carta abierta «El derecho universal a 
     instalar cualquier software en cualquier dispositivo». La carta fue 
     entregada en mano al presidente de la Comisión de Asuntos Digitales del 
     Parlamento alemán en 2023.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="11" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>Lanzamiento de FediGov</title>
      <url>https://fedigov.eu/</url>
      <body>
	 El grupo local suizo de la FSFE pone en marcha una iniciativa junto con GNU/Linux.ch para animar a las instituciones públicas a utilizar soluciones de Software Libre federadas para comunicarse con sus ciudadanos.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
   <year value="2021">
	<event month="11" type="legal-education">
      <title>Primera «Jornada de Educación Jurídica»</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/legal/led.html</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE organizó la primera «Jornada de Educación Jurídica» (LED) con el fin de 
      ofrecer formación jurídica básica sobre el contexto legal del 
      Software Libre: la ley de derechos de autor y el concepto de copyleft.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="03" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Caso judicial clave sobre el reembolso de la licencia de Windows</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2021/news-20210302-01.html</url>
      <body>
	  Luca Bonissi, colaborador de la FSFE, ganó un juicio de dos años de duración 
      contra Lenovo en Italia, en el que el tribunal condenó a la empresa a 
      pagar 20.000 euros en concepto de indemnización por negarse a reembolsar el precio de una 
      licencia de Windows preinstalada.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="11" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Lanzamiento de la campaña «Upcycling Android»</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/upcyclingandroid/</url>
      <body>
	 La FSFE puso en marcha esta iniciativa para ayudar a los usuarios a instalar sistemas operativos de 
     Software Libre en sus teléfonos, organizando talleres 
     por toda Europa y elaborando recomendaciones políticas para prolongar 
     la vida útil del hardware y reducir los residuos electrónicos.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="11" type="young-generation">
      <title>Publicación del libro infantil de Ada &amp; Zangemann</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/ada-zangemann/</url>
      <body>
	  La FSFE ha publicado «Ada &amp; Zangemann - Un cuento sobre 
	  Software, Monopatines y Helado de Frambuesa», un libro infantil 
	  escrito por el presidente de la FSFE, Matthias Kirschner, y 
	  publicado bajo una licencia Creative Commons.  
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="12" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>Creación el grupo «FSFE Women»</title>
      <url>https://docs.fsfe.org/en/teams/Women</url>
      <body>
	El grupo «FSFE Women» se creó para ayudar a las mujeres y a todas aquellas personas que 
    se identifiquen como mujeres a establecer vínculos entre ellas mientras 
    debatir sobre cuestiones tecnológicas. 
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="09" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Iniciativa de Neutralidad de Dispositivos</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/deviceneutrality/index</url>
      <body>La iniciativa de la FSFE para proteger la Neutralidad de los Dispositivos y la libertad del software, contrarrestando los bloqueos, reforzando el control de los usuarios finales sobre sus datos y defendiendo el derecho de los usuarios a instalar, ejecutar y desinstalar libremente software en sus propios dispositivos.</body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2020">
    <event month="04" type="pmpc">
      <title>Free Software for COVID-19 contact tracing apps</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2020/news-20200402-02.html</url>
      <body>
	  The FSFE advocated that all publicly funded COVID-19 contact 
	  tracing apps should be released under a Free Software licence. 
	  Both the EU and the WHO followed the FSFE's arguments and 
	  recommended that any COVID-19 contact tracing app be published as 
	  Free Software.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="07" type="young-generation">
      <title>“Learning like a pro” launched</title>
      <url>https://lernenwiedieprofis.ch/</url>
      <body>
    The local FSFE group in Zurich created a website which they explain why Free Software matters in education, described individual Free Software solutions and how these solutions in particular can be used to make school learning efficient and easy.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2019">
    <event month="10" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Router Freedom reaches the European level</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/routers/index.html</url>
      <body>
	  After victories in Germany, the FSFE expands its advocacy for 
	  Router Freedom at EU level, preparing a comprehensive activity 
	  package including a monitoring tool for people and organisations 
	  willing to advocate for freedom of terminal equipment.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="08" type="legal-education">
      <title>Reuse 3.0</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2019/news-20190807-01.en.html</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE released an updated set of best practices together with more assisting material and tools.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="08" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Tearing down barriers introduced by the Radio Lockdown Directive</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/radiodirective/</url>
      <body>
	  The European Commission collected 276 public comments on the 
	  Radio Equipment Directive, most of them critical. The FSFE 
	  continued pressing regulators to recognise that the right to 
	  install Free Software is fundamental to security, education, and 
	  innovation.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="01" type="pmpc">
      <title>Expert brochure published</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/publiccode/brochure</url>
      <body>
      The FSFE published the new expert policy brochure of Public Money? Public Code!" as a helpful source of information.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="pmpc">
      <title>First Parliament in Europe demands public code</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2019/news-20190514-01.html</url>
      <body>
	  The Parliament of Asturias became the first Parliament in Europe 
	  to vote in favour of signing our open letter demanding "Public 
	  Money? Public Code!".
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="10" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>Launch of the Software Freedom Podcast</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/podcast.html</url>
      <body>
	  The FSFE launched a podcast series to talk with people who have 
	  inspiring ideas about software freedom and to reach broader 
	  audiences beyond its traditional community.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2018">
    <event month="10" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Exclusion of Free Software in the European Union's Copyright Directive</title>
      <url>https://savecodeshare.eu/</url>
      <body>
	   The FSFE obtained the first limited exclusion for Free Software 
	   in a major EU legislation. In this case in the amendments 143 
	   and 150 of the current copyright reform proposal of the European 
	   Parliament's directive.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="11" type="legal-education">
      <title>The FSFE joined its first NGI consortium</title>
      <url>https://www.ngi.eu/ngi-projects/ngi-zero/</url>
      <body>
		The NGI is a European Commission initiative supporting 
		technologies that shape the internet into an open, inclusive, 
		and privacy-respecting platform. The FSFE is part of the NGI 
		Zero consortium, providing support on legal and licensing 
		questions.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="12" type="org-dev">
      <title>Creation of CARE team</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/about/codeofconduct#CARE</url>
      <body>
		To further ensure the availability and enforcement of our Code 
		of Conduct, we created a CARE team so that whenever our Code of 
		Conduct is breached within the FSFE community, you can contact 
		our central CARE team.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2017">
    <event month="11" type="legal-education">
      <title>REUSE Initiative launched</title>
      <url>https://reuse.software/</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE created an initiative to deliver the best development options
        for Free Software licensing compliance.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="10" type="legal-education">
      <title>Fiduciary Licensing Agreement 2.0 is released</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/ln/ln.html</url>
      <body>
        After 10 years of the Fiduciary License Agreement 1.2 (FLA-1.2). The
        FSFE joins forces with ContributorAgreements.org to produce FLA-2.0.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="09" type="pmpc">
      <title>Launch of 'Public Money? Public Code!'</title>
      <url>https://publiccode.eu/</url>
      <body>
		The FSFE initiates a campaign framework for legislation 
		requiring that publicly financed software developed for the 
		public sector be made publicly available under a Free Software 
		licence.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="06" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>Launch of git.fsfe.org</title>
      <url>https://git.fsfe.org/</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE launches a Gitea service instance for its contributors. 
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="09" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Launch of Save Code Share</title>
      <url>https://savecodeshare.eu/</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE starts a campaign to gather support against violations of Free
        Software in the EU Directive "Copyright in the Digital Single Market".
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2016">
    <event month="09" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>The FSFE organises its 2016 summit</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2016/news-20160804-01.html</url>
      <body>
        Marking its 15th anniversary, the FSFE calls in its community to join
        together under one roof for the first FSFE Summit.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="08" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Router Freedom established in Germany</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2016/news-20160725-01.html</url>
      <body>
		After three years of intense engagement with policy makers in 
		Germany, Router Freedom became a reality in the country. A 
		telecom law enabled customers to use their own routers with 
		their Internet connections, enabling them to use Free Software 
		for their connections.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="03" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>DFD campaign run by Digital Freedom Foundation</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2016/news-20160126-01.html</url>
      <body>
        After years of organising the Document Freedom Day, the FSFE handed over
        the campaign to the Digital Freedom Foundation who will continue
        organising the event every year in support of Open Standards.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2015">
    <event month="11" type="legal-education">
      <title>Legal Network reaches 400 participants</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/ln/ln.html</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE's Legal Network launched in 2006, reaches 400 participants from
        all over the world.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="10" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>
        The FSFE convinces 1125 public administration to remove proprietary
        software ads.
      </title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2015/news-20151013-01.html</url>
      <body>
        After a six years long campaign, the PDFreaders campaign closes after
        1125 public administrations have removed advertisement for proprietary
        software from their web pages.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="09" type="org-dev">
      <title>Matthias Kirschner is elected as new president</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2015/news-20150922-01.html</url>
      <body>
        Having worked with the FSFE since 2004, Matthias Kirschner was elected
        president together with Alessandro Rubini as vice president.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="young-generation">
      <title>The FSFE issues a position paper on OER</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2015/news-20150210-01.html</url>
      <body>
        The position paper is a boost of Open Educational Resources on the basis
        of Free Software
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2014">
    <event month="05" type="pmpc">
      <title>
        33 Free Software Pact supporters elected to the EU Parliament
      </title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2014/news-20140528-01.html</url>
      <body>
        33 newly elected MEPs across the political spectrum signed the Free
        Software Pact, promising to support Free Software and Open Standards
        during their time in Parliament.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="01" type="pmpc">
      <title>Italy puts Free Software first</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2014/news-20140116-01.html</url>
      <body>
        The Italian government has made Free Software the default choice for
        public administrations, setting a precedence for the rest of Europe to
        follow.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2013">
    <event month="09" type="org-dev">
      <title>First European Coordinators Meeting</title>
      <url>https://blogs.fsfe.org/lucile.falg/2013/10/01/first-european-coordinators-meeting-2/</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE coordinators from all over Europe meet in Berlin for the
        first time to exchange knowledge and discuss future strategies.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="06" type="market-regulations">
      <title>German parliament unanimous against Software Patents</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2013/news-20130612-01.html</url>
      <body>
        After many talks and expert meetings, the German Parliament unanimously
        approved the joint motion which included nearly all of the FSFE's core
        demands.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2012">
    <event month="11" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Analysis of warranty after flashing phones</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2012/news-20121106-01.html</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE's Legal team clarifies that flashing your phone in order to install
        Free Software doesn't void your warranty in the EU.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="11" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>German Government's White Paper on Secure Boot</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2012/news-20121120-01.html</url>
      <body>
        Device owners should be in full control of their devices, says Ministry
        of Interior, echoing the FSFE's core demands.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="06" type="pmpc">
      <title>Promoting fair public procurement in Finland</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2012/news-20120619-01.html</url>
      <body>
       The FSFE activists in Finland analyse hundreds of procurement notices, and
        contact public bodies that put Free Software at a disadvantage.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="05" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Open Standards consultation in the UK</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2012/news-20121101-02.html</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE helps the UK government set one of Europe's strongest policies
        on Open Standards.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="03" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Microsoft fined for violating settlement</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2013/news-20130312-01.html</url>
      <body>
        The European Commission impose a EUR 561 million fine on Microsoft for
        violating the web browser settlement. The FSFE had warned of the
        settlement's lack of a monitoring mechanism.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="03" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Free Your Android launched</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2012/news-20120228-01.html</url>
      <body>
        Most smartphones come with non-free software and some restrictions. The FSFE
        stars a campaign to help users free their phones and use Free Software
        apps.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="device-neutrality">
      <title>Concerns over the Nortel patent portfolio sale</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2012/news-20120214-01.html</url>
      <body>
       The FSFE calls on US competition regulators about faulty competition settlement
        regarding sale of Nortel patent portfolio. The lawsuit occurs in
        November 2013, as Rockstar sues Google over Android.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="legal-education">
      <title>First "Hacking for compliance" workshop</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2013/news-20130626-01.html</url>
      <body>
        At this workshop, the FSFE trains volunteers to identify and prove GNU GPL
        violations in embedded devices.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2011">
	<event month="12" type="legal-education">
      <title>AVM vs. Cybits case</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/avm-gpl-violation.html/</url>
      <body>
	  The FSFE supported the case of AVM vs. Cybits and the court 
	  confirmed FSFE's view that users of GNU GPLed software are 
	  allowed to modify and install it even if it is shipped as a part 
	  of an embedded device's firmware.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Input to EU's R&amp;D funding program</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2011/news-20111206-01.en.html</url>
      <body>
	  The FSFE provided input to the Commission in order to make Horizion 2020 (EU's R&amp;D funding program for the period 2014-2020) accessible for Free 
	  Software research and projects.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="05" type="market-regulations">
      <title>European Court of Justice hearing</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2011/news-20110523-01.html</url>
      <body>
	 The FSFE played a key role at a Microsoft hearing before the 
	 European Union's General Court, helping explain the intricacies of 
	 Free Software servers.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2010">
    <event month="05" type="org-dev">
      <title>The FSFE is awarded the Theodor Heuss Medal</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2010/news-20100510-01.html</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE receives the Theodor Heuss medal for its work on freedom in the
        information society.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="04" type="org-dev">
      <title> The FSFE's founding president awarded German Cross of Merit
      </title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2010/news-20100428-01.html</url>
      <body>
        Georg C. F. Greve, founding president of the FSFE, receives this high award (Verdienstkreuz am Bande).for his work on Free
        Software and Open Standards.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>First "I love Free Software" Day</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/ilovefs/</url>
      <body>
        Every 14 February since 2010, the FSFE asks Free Software users to
        thank the developers of the software they use
        every day.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2009">
    <event month="09" type="pmpc">
      <title> "Ask Your Candidates" launched</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2009/news-20090908-01.html</url>
      <body>
        For the federal elections in Germany, the FSFE started this initiative to ask the parties' candidates about their positions on Free Software and Open Standards
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>PDFReaders campaign</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2009/news-20090202-01.html</url>
      <body>
        Many websites from public administrations advertise proprietary PDF
        readers to read their documents. This is unfair advertising of an US software company. Therefore the FSFE informs
        about free PDF readers and contacts public institutions to tell them
        about it.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="06" type="org-dev">
      <title>Karsten Gerloff is elected as new president</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/about/people/gerloff/gerloff.html</url>
      <body>
        Team member of the FSFE since 2005, Karsten Gerloff was elected FSFE president together with Fernanda Weiden as vice president.  
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2008">
    <event month="03" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>Document Freedom Day campaign launched</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2008/news-20080220-01.html</url>
      <body>
        For the first time, the FSFE promotes this international day to celebrate
        and show support for access to information and Open Standards. 
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="legal-education">
      <title>First Free Software Licensing and Legal Workshop</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/news/2008/news-20080214-01.html</url>
      <body>
        The Free Software Licensing and Legal Workshop (LLW) gathers experts to discuss license and legal topics, organized by the FSFE's Freedom Task Force.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2007">
    <event month="09" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Victory on the Microsoft antitrust case</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/ms-vs-eu/ms-vs-eu.html</url>
      <body>
        From 2004 until its conclusion in 2007, the FSFE worked hard on this case with
        the Samba team to protect the interests of Free Software developers.
        As a result, Microsoft is required to publish interoperability information.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="07" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Against the standardisation of MS-OOXML</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/msooxml/msooxml.html</url>
      <body>
        Microsoft tried to make OOXML an Open Standard. This implementation
        lacks interoperability information and can be considered an attempt
        to undermine Open Standards. By informing about this issue, MS-OOXML ended up not being established well enough to be a danger anymore.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="legal-education">
      <title>Fiduciary License Agreement</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/fla/fla.html</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE releases the Fiduciary License Agreement (FLA) to ensure legal maintability of Free Software
        projects and rights in court. In 2008, KDE adopted it as well.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2006">
    <event month="11" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>First Fellowship conference</title>
      <url>https://lwn.net/Articles/200329/</url>
      <body>
	   The first Fellowship conference took place in Bolzano, Italy, enabling FSFE supporters to meet in person.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="11" type="legal-education">
      <title>The FSFE's Legal Team established</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/legal.html</url>
      <body>
       Operating in close collaboration with gpl-violations.org, "FSFE Legal" educates and supports Free Software
        developers in legal aspects.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="10" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>DRM.info campaign launched</title>
      <url>https://drm.info</url>
      <body>
        Under the slogan "Your devices don't trust you", the FSFE starts a campaign
        to inform about the dangers of digital restriction management (DRM).
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="11" type="legal-education">
      <title>Legal Network founded</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/ln/</url>
      <body>
        The Legal Network is a neutral, non-partisan, group of experts in different fields involved in Free Software legal issues and the aim of it is to promote discussion and foster better knowledge of the legal constructs that back Free Software.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2005">
    <event month="11" type="market-regulations">
      <title>EC's antitrust lawsuit against Microsoft</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/ms-vs-eu/ms-vs-eu.html</url>
      <body>
		In order to strengthen a culture of interoperability between 
		devices in EU member states, the FSFE files an application to 
		intervene in this important case".
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="06" type="market-regulations">
      <title>European Parliament votes against Software Patents</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/swpat/swpathtml</url>
      <body>
        After an intense campaign by the FSFE and other organisations, the
        European Parliament rejects the Software Patent initiative.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="06" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Karlsruhe Memorandum against Software Patents</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/swpat/memorandum.html</url>
      <body>
        Nearly 40 organisations and over 220 individuals took a stand against
        the Software Patents directive before its second reading in the European
        Parliament.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="02" type="org-dev">
      <title> The Fellowship of the FSFE</title>
      <url>https://blogs.fsfe.org/fellowship-interviews/?p=27</url>
      <body>
        European Free Software advocates can now become fellows by supporting the
        FSFE. As fellows, they can also use the FSFE's infrastructure to promote and spread our vision as volunteers."
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2004">
    <event month="11" type="market-regulations">
      <title>European Interoperability Framework</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/standards/eifv2.html</url>
      <body>
        The European Interoperability Framework (EIF) is a set of interoperability guidelines with a pan-European
        scope. The FSFE critically observes its evolution and the influence of lobby
        groups for proprietary software vendors.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="05" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Action week against Software patents</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/swpat/swpat.en.html</url>
      <body>
        To inform citizens, economists and politicians about the harmful
        consequences of the Software Patent initiative, the FSFE organized panel
        discussions and several demonstrations.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="05" type="market-regulations">
      <title>Open Standards definition</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/standards/def.html</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE contributes to redefine the Open Standards definition, which will be adopted by many
        organisations and companies in Europe.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2003">
    <event month="07" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>Education Task Force created</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/education/education.html</url>
      <body>
        To improve the access to Free Software in education, the Education Task Force was funded by volunteers of the FSFE. The members are experts in this topic.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
  <year value="2001-2002">
    <event month="11" type="volunteer-engagement">
      <title>"We speak about Free Software" campaign</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/activities/whyfs/whyfs.html</url>
      <body>
        The FSFE explains the advantage of using the term "Free Software" instead of "Open
        Source". Several companies and Bruce Perens supported the campaign.
      </body>
    </event>
    <event month="04" type="org-dev">
      <title>Foundation of the FSFE</title>
      <url>https://fsfe.org/</url>
      <body>
        The Free Software Foundation Europe (FSFE) is founded as a sister organisation of the FSF, with Georg C. F. Greve becoming the first president.
      </body>
    </event>
  </year>
</timeline>
