<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- <?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> -->
<!-- encoding: Identifies the character set used to encode the data.
     "ISO-8859-1" is "Latin-1" the Western European and English language character set.
     The default is compressed Unicode: UTF-8. -->

<!--
Old version of the XML DTD, before it became endorsed by OASIS

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD DocBk XML V3.1.3//EN"
                      "http://nwalsh.com/docbook/xml/3.1.3/docbookx.dtd" [
-->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                      "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ENTITY title "F.A.Q electronic manufacturers">
<!ENTITY subtitle "Frequently Asked Questions about drivers for GNU/Linux systems">

]>

<article class="faq" lang="en">

  <articleinfo>
    <title>&title;</title>
    <subtitle>&subtitle;</subtitle>

    <author>
      <affiliation>
	<orgname>AFUL
	  (Association Francophone des Utilisateurs de Linux et des Logiciels Libres)</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <pubdate>Juin 2001</pubdate>
  </articleinfo>



  <bridgehead>Questions / Réponses</bridgehead>

  <qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  Who is concerned by this document ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  Every manufacturer and distributor of electronic hardware.
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  My customers are asking for Linux drivers, what can I do ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  Pick one or more strategy in those :
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Announce there is no support for your hardware
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Publish your hardware interface specifications
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Developp drivers and release them in a binary form
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Developp drivers under an Open Source or Free Sofware licence
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  Is having a Linux support useful ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  It will generate sells.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Linux potential market is huge. It is the only operating system 
	  presently gaining market shares over all its competitors. It is 
	  favored by many computer specialists, who are prescriptors.
	  It is now commercially and financely backed by the biggest 
	  manufacturers (SUN, IBM, DELL, HP, ...).
	  Some goverments are studying the use of Free Software as standard 
	  for their administration (France, Poland, Argentina, China, ...)
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  Can I have my drivers developped for free ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  Yes. By giving your specifications to voluntary developpers.
	</para>
	<para>
	  But this approach has some drawbacks :
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The numbers of developpers rely in part on luck.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Voluntary people work at their own pace.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The drivers may therefore not be available for the commercial 
		release of the product.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		No extra sell can be expected before drivers availability.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		No control is exerced on the quality of resulting software.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  Can I avoid to release the specifications of my product ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  Yes. By developping and releasing binary drivers.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Advantages to keep secret the specifications are :
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		protecting your products from cloning
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		hiding weaknesses in low quality products.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	  Inconvenients are :
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
	      
		be deprieved of help and support from users for maintenance.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		a degraded image in the eye of the free software community
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		a superior cost in developpment
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		a market limited to platforms chosen initially
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	  Knowing that Linux versions appears at a much higher rate than others OSes and that the present progression of electronic makes cloning ineffective.
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  How can I make money if I give my products ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	Software is not a product, its a service. A product has a cost for
	mass-production and distribution. Your product is your hardware.
	</para>
	<para>
	Software drivers have not always been developped by manufacturers.
	Before, manufacturers did release their specifications and OS's 
	developpers or customers were in charge of developping software drivers.
	</para>
	<para>
	That method was unsatisfacting for many reasons. Some disappeared with
	the growth of Internet, some thanks to the GPL.
	</para>
	<para>
	The present system is unsatisfacting, too. It favors the appeareance 
	of monopolies which have the power to put customers and furnishers 
	under an unbearable pressure.
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  What advantages are to be expected from Open Source ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  Software can be adapted by users. 
	  It therefore remains in adequation to their needs. 
	  Minor, frustrating bugs can be corrected, new ideas can appear.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Free Software is a guaranty of the product lasting.
	  Should the furnisher disappears, software code could still be maintained.
	  In the decision of purchase, it is a supplementary guarantee for the customer, 
	  thus a selling point for the builder.
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  What is the difference between "Open source" and "Free Software" ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	In Open source, sources are published, but you remain the sole owner of the code. 
	The free software authorizes also modification and the redistribution. Open Source is only a characteristic of free software.
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  My developers are not formed in Linux. What should I do ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		form them
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Recruit new ones who have this field of competence
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		Address specialized companies of service
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  Do I risk pressures on behalf of influent OSes publishers ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	Some have an egocentric notion of the free-market economy.
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	Do you advise the Open source in every case ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  Non.
	</para>
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
            The downmarket products have no interest to display in broad 
	    daylight their mediocrity. The binary driver is then more suited.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
       	    The informers software, the hidden functions are afraid as well of the light. This case is a criterion which will tilt companies and governments to choose the manufacturers who opt for transparency.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	What are the existing licenses? Which one is best adapted to my case ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  On this subject, you can consult <ulink url="http://www.fsf.org/philosophy/license-list.html">http://www.fsf.org/philosophy/license-list.html</ulink>
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	May I use the penguin Logo freely?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  Yes. There is also a specific logo bound to a certification <ulink url="http://www.open-hardware.org">http://www.open-hardware.org</ulink>.
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

    <qandaentry>
      <question>
	<para>
	  Where may I learn more on free software ?
	</para>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<para>
	  You can contact the following structures:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<ulink url="http://www.aful.org">AFUL</ulink> 
		<ulink url="mailto:aful@aful.org?subject=Constructeurs">
		  &lt;aful@aful.org&gt;</ulink>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<ulink url="http://france.fsfeurope.org/">FSF France</ulink> 
		<ulink url="mailto:contact@france.fsfeurope.org">
		  &lt;contact@france.fsfeurope.org&gt;</ulink>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
      </answer>
    </qandaentry>

  </qandaset>



  <bridgehead>Conclusion</bridgehead>

  <para>
    A manufacturer has a strong interest in using Open source for the developments of his drivers, <emphasis> whatever the targeted operating system </emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>
    He also has interest to develop himself drivers, or at least their initial version because of:  
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  his better knowledge of the product,
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  his need to insure the quality,
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The necessity of their availability from the commercial launch,
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	the influence naturally taken by the initiator of a free project on it's evolution.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    Afterward, maintenance of the project according to the free software model,

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  allows to benefit from improvements brought by the users,
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  allows product's compatibility with a wider range of hardware and OSes
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
   	 improve your image within the computer specialists's community.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
   	decrease the project maintenance costs.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
   	frees customers fears felt in front of secret,
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	And then brings as many competitive advantages to whom practises it.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>



</article>

